<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
     <teiHeader>
         <fileDesc>
           
             <titleStmt>
               <title>Selected Letters from the Dr. Ivan S. Gilbert collection of Stephens family travel letters,
                 1834-1949 1909-1917</title>
             
               <editor><persName ref="#MEG">Meghan Elaine Griesemer</persName></editor>
               <editor role="Principal-editor"><persName ref="#HLU">H. Lewis Ulman</persName></editor>
           
           
           <respStmt>
             <resp>Creation of digital scans of manuscript pages: </resp>
             <persName>Laura Denning, Ohio State University Libraries</persName>
           </respStmt>
           
           <respStmt>
             <resp>Creation of initial machine-readable transcript: </resp>
             <persName ref="#SA">Steve Agricola</persName>
             <persName ref="#MEG">Meghan Elaine Griesemer</persName>
           </respStmt>
           
         </titleStmt>
           
           <editionStmt>
             <p>First Edition</p>
           </editionStmt>
           <!--      Fill this in! -->
           <extent>approx. xxx kilobites</extent>
           
           <publicationStmt>
             
             <publisher>The Ohio State University Library.
               <address>
                 <addrLine n="1">Rare Books and Manuscripts Library</addrLine>
                 <addrLine n="2">327 Main Library</addrLine>
                 <addrLine n="3">1858 Neil Avenue Mall</addrLine>
                 <addrLine n="4">Columbus, OH 43210</addrLine>
               </address>
             </publisher>
             
             <pubPlace>Columbus, OH</pubPlace>
             
             <!-- 
          The <idno> element is only required for documents with a standard id number
          such as a library call number..-->
             
             <!-- TODO -->
             <idno type="CallNumber">SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
             
             <availability>
               <p>The W. B. Anderson Collection is the property of the Rare Books and Manuscripts
                 Library of The Ohio State University Libraries. Any use of the material should
                 acknowledge such ownership.</p>
               <p xml:id="CreativeCommons">
                 <![CDATA[<a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"><img alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0" src="http://creativecommons.org/images/public/somerights20.png"/></a><br/>This work is licensed under a <a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0  License</a>.<br/>
                  This license does not transfer any rights regarding material used in the edition by permission of a third party.]]>
               </p>
             </availability>
             
             <date>2006</date>
           </publicationStmt>
           
           <sourceDesc>
             
	           <biblFull>
	             <titleStmt>
	               <title level="u">Civil War correspondence, 1862-1864</title>
	               <author>Anderson, William B. (b. 1822)</author>
	             </titleStmt>
	             <extent>Twenty-one handwritten letters, 4 documents, and 1 CD-ROM.</extent>
	             <publicationStmt>
	               <p>The W. B. Anderson Collection is the property of the Rare Books and Manuscripts
	                 Library of The Ohio State University Libraries. Any use of the material should
	                 acknowledge such ownership. The Ohio State University holds copyright to 
	                 all images of manuscript pages used in the edition.</p>
	             </publicationStmt>
	             <notesStmt>
	               <note type="descriptive">
	                 <p></p>
	               </note>
	               <note type="introductory">
	                 <p></p>
	               </note>
	             </notesStmt>
	           </biblFull>
             
             <!-- SEE STEPHENS FOR OTHER LIST TYPES -->
             <listPlace>
               <head>Places Mentioned in the Text</head>
               <place></place>
             </listPlace>
             
             <listBibl>
               <head>Works Cited in Notes</head>
               <bibl xml:id="HOAC" n="historyofallegheny">
                 <title level="m">History of Allegheny County, Pennsylvania</title>
                 <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                 <publisher>A. Warner &amp; Co. </publisher>
                 <date>1889</date>
               </bibl>
             </listBibl>
             
	        </sourceDesc>
           
         </fileDesc>
       
       <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
           <p>This edition represents a series of letters that William B. Anderson wrote to his wife, Louisa,
             at the time of  the Civil War. During the war, Anderson piloted steam ships along the Ohio River, carrying
             freight and passengers alike. At this time, letter writing was the most effective means of communication, and the
             only way to keep domestic affairs in order.</p>
           <p>The collection of letters penned by Anderson was purchased by the Ohio State Rare
             Books and Manuscripts library. They purchased the letters in an effort to increase
             their collection of wartime letters as well as documents that better illustrate the life-world of 
             the historical periods that the letters were written in. 
           </p>
           <p>The reason for digitizing these documents is that the editors are trying to make these
             documents as easily accessible to as many people as possible. These letters may be of intest
             to historians interested in the Civil War, the Steamship Industry, or even postal historians. These
             potential readers were given the most careful consideration in designing the digital texts. The hope is
             that by making these annotated and edited documents available on the world wide web, that the documents will be "streamlined
             and tailored in the service of ever greater efficiency" (Levy 69). Hopefully, the rich media and annotations
             provided will help make these documents more easily understood while the technology itself makes them
             more widely available to interested audiences.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
           <p>Encoding of the Anderson letters emphasizes diplomatic transcription, with supplemental
             information allowing for semi-modernized, corrected, regularized, or expanded views included as 
             the values of attributes associated with various elements. Accordingly, abbreviations, recoverable
             cancelations, punctuation, spelling, underscoring, capitalization, line breaks, and page breaks 
             have all been transcribed or tagged as they appear in the original manuscripts. Regularized
             versions of all names and referring strings have been encoded as the values of "reg"
             attributes. Standard format values for all dates have been encoded in "value" attributes.</p>
           <p>Corrections and emendations in Anderson's hand have been encoded as cancelations and interlinear 
             or marginal additions. In a few cases, omitted text has been supplied by the editors for the sake 
             of clarity and encoded with the TEI &lt;supplied&gt; element.</p>
           <p>The following structural elements of the letters are also encoded: opener (including salutation
             and dateline), body, lines, paragraphs, pages, and closers (including salutation and 
             signature). Notes and postscripts are identified as such.</p>
           <p>The critical apparatus used in particular views of the letters is explained at the bottom of each view.</p>
           <p>The XML and XSL files related to this
             edition are all available in the KB.
           </p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
           <p>The XML files that constitute this edition of the William B. Anderson letters
             are named according the letters' dates of composition, using the following naming
             convention: WBA_YYYYMMDD.xml. Dates of composition were determined from
             various sources of evidence: the datelines inscribed in the letters, internal
             evidence in the body of the letters, and perpetual calendars. If the year,
             month, or date on which a letter was written could not be determined, the 
             appropriate part of the filename is rendered with 0s. XSL style
             sheet documents are named with the prefix "WBA" followed by an underscore
             and a descriptive phrase (e.g., "WBA_diplomatic.xsl).</p>
           <p>To facilitate embedding or linking to image, audio, and video files, this edition
             supplements the Text Encoding Initiative's DTD by adding a URL attribute to 
             the &lt;xref&gt; element and an MMID (i.e., Media Manager ID) attribute to the 
             &lt;pb&gt; element. The values of the MMID attribute in &lt;pb&gt; elements and
             the file IDs in the URL attribute of &lt;xref&gt; elements that link to, or embed, 
             image, audio, and video files contained in the Media Manager are generated 
             by the Media Manager application.</p>
         </refsDecl>
         
         <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
             <bibl>
               <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
             </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         
       </encodingDesc>
       
       <profileDesc>
         <creation>
           <date>2006-06-06</date>
         </creation>
         
         <particDesc>
           <listPerson type="mentioned">
             <head></head>
             <person></person>
           </listPerson>
           
           <listPerson type="editors">
             <head></head>
             <person>
               <persName></persName>
             </person>
           </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         
         <langUsage>
           <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>

         <handNotes>
           <handNote xml:id="WBA" medium="ink">Anderson, William B.</handNote>
         </handNotes>
         
         <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
             <term>Anderson, William B. (1822-1897)</term>
             <term>Anderson, Mary Louisa ne?? Fischgens (1837-1911)</term>
             <term>Ohio -- Cincinnati</term>
             <term>Kentucky -- Louisville</term>
             <term>Woolslayer, Mary Ann</term>
             <term>McNamer, Mary</term>
             <term>River boats -- United States -- Sources</term>
             <term>United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865</term>
           </keywords>
         </textClass>
         
       </profileDesc>
       
       <revisionDesc>
         <change>
           <date>2006-08-22</date>
           <name>
             H. Lewis Ulman
           </name>
           <label>Manuscripts read aloud by assistant (Catherine A. Ulman) while principal editor 
             checked transcriptions.</label>
         </change>
         
         <change>
           <date>2006-08-10</date>
           <name>
             H. Lewis Ulman
           </name>
           <label>Cross-check against independent transcription by Jamie Danker (principal editor evaluated discrepancies).</label>
         </change>
         
         <change>
           <date>2006-08-08</date>
           <name>
             H. Lewis Ulman
           </name>
           <label>Spot-check corrections</label>
         </change>
         
         <change>
           <date>2006-06-06</date>
           <name>Meghan Elaine Griesemer</name>
           <label>Initial release</label>
         </change>
         
         <!-- Indicate the date on which you completed your XML encoding. -->
         
         <change>
           <date>2006-06-06</date>
           <name>Meghan Elaine Griesemer</name>
           <label>Correction of initial transcription.</label>
           
           <!-- Indicate the date on which you completed the correction of the initial transcription. -->
           
         </change>
         <change>
           <date>2005</date>
           <name>Steve Agricola</name>
           <label>Initial machine-readable transcription.</label>
         </change>
       </revisionDesc>
     </teiHeader>
  
  <!-- SAMPLE FOR CORPUS LETTERS -->
    
  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620616" n="1862-06-16">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his Wife, Louisa, 16 June 1862</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>William B. Anderson writes home to his wife, Louisa, from Cincinnati, Ohio. He is hauling Coal Boat men from Louisville, Kentucky. 
                While in Cincinnati, Anderson visits his mother-in-law, the 'old lady,' as well as family friends. During the dry, dusty, June weather, 
                a fire breaks out near the Ohio River and Third St, destroying several houses. He opens his riverboat up as an improptu shelter for the fire
                victims, even filling the typically unoccupied Ladies' Cabins. Anderson closes the letter by inviting Louisa to accompany him on his next
                trip to Cincinnati.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>ALS, 2pp.</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18620616XXX" corresp="XXX" >
          <pb facs="/0/0fae4c6e-0056-4419-9325-15799bf50925"/>
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><date when="1862-06-16"></date>June 16/62</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear<rs type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            
            <!-- Beginning with the body of the letter, lines in this template have been identified 
               to allow for cross references and numbered to allow for numbered display. IDs must 
               be unique within the document. However, you do not need to report line breaks at all 
               if doing so serves no purpose in your edition. -->
            
            <!-- 
            MODEL FOR NOTES
            <note resp="ed" xml:id="ForestryBld">TEXT OF NOTE
              <bibl><ref target="#UWash">Title</ref></bibl></note>

            -->
            
            <lb n="003"/>I did not write to you 
            <lb n="004"/>from <name type="place" reg=" Louisville, KY">Louisville</name> on account of our 
            <lb n="005"/>short stay there &amp; thought we would 
            <lb n="006"/><sic corr="beat">beet</sic> the Mail up, we will leave 
            <lb n="007"/>here <sic corr="tonight">to night</sic> we had a good trip 
            <lb n="008"/>of Coal boat men up here from <name type="place" reg=" Louisville, KY">Louisville</name>
            <lb n="009"/>but our prospects are poor for a trip 
            <lb n="010"/>of either Freight or <sic corr="passengers">Passenger</sic> up, though 
            <lb n="011"/>upon the whole we make a paying trip  
            <lb n="012"/>I will finish this half sheet just
            <lb n="013"/>before we start &amp; then I can tell you
            <lb n="014"/>more
            
          </p>
          <p>
            
            <lb n="015"/>We have laid over and will leave this 
            <lb n="016"/>Evening we are getting all we want I have 
            <lb n="017"/>just been down to see your <rs type="person" reg="Fischgens, Mary Ann, née Woolslayer">mother</rs><note target="n2">2</note> she is not 
            <lb n="018"/>very well Today sends her respects  <name type="person">Ella</name><note target="n3">3</note> 
            <lb n="000"/>was at school I did not see her. There was 
            <lb n="019"/>a large fire down between Third st and The river 
            <lb n="000"/>yesterday just one <sic corr="square">squear</sic> above the old<sic corr="lady's"> ladys</sic>  
            <lb n="020"/>and burnt a lot of Old Houses &amp; other property 
            <lb n="000"/>we have had all our rooms but 3 in 
            <lb n="021"/>the ladies Cabin full since last night but 
            <lb n="022"/>we have not up <abbr expan="until">till</abbr> this time had a lady 
            <lb n="023"/>passenger on our boat the <name type="person" reg="Woolslayer, Mary Ann">old lady</name> says 
            <lb n="024"/>she would like to have you pay her a 
            <lb n="025"/>visit so if you think you would enjoy 
            
            <pb facs="/6/649db1cc-1689-45f1-95af-1fe636b79e81" n="2"/>    
            
            <lb n="026"/>a trip I will offer you an invitation 
            <lb n="027"/><del type="recoverable" rend="overwritten" hand="WBA">t</del>we will if no accident get up about 
            <lb n="028"/>Saturday &amp; leave again about Tuesday 
            <lb n="029"/><sic corr="today">to day</sic> it is all most suffocatingly hot 
            <lb n="030"/>and the dust is so thick that I cannot 
            <lb n="031"/>scarcely see the buildings along the wharf  
            <lb n="032"/>&amp; I think we must surely have a gust soon  
            <lb n="033"/>I will stop for I expect to spend Sunday 
            <lb n="034"/>with you &amp; the small ones <note target="n4">4</note> 
          </p>
          <p>
            <lb n="035"/>tell <name type="person">Mary McNamee</name><note target="n5">5</note> that WM was over 
            <lb n="000"/>with us last evening and that he is well
            <lb n="036"/>we will leave about 4 or 5 PM this 
            <lb n="038"/>Tuesday <abbr expan="Evening">Eveng</abbr>
          </p>
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Affectionately &amp; <del type="recoverable" rend="overwritten" hand="WBA"></del>Truly Your</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName>WBA</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
        <!-- First, the envelope. -->
        <div type="envelope" xml:id="GS19090706env01" corresp="#GS19090706let01">
          <pb facs="XXX"/>
          <ab type="returnAddress">
            <address>
              <addrLine></addrLine>
              <addrLine></addrLine>
              <addrLine></addrLine>
              <addrLine></addrLine>
            </address>
          </ab>
          <ab type="postalAddress">
            <persName>Mrs. A. T. Stephens</persName>
            <address>
              <addrLine>26 Emerson street</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Newton</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Massachusetts</addrLine>
            </address>
          </ab>
          <ab type="endorsement">
            <handShift new="Unknown"/> 94<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="Endorsements"/>
            <note resp="ed" xml:id="Endorsements">Similar numbers are penciled under the cancelled
              postage stamp on several envelopes in the collection [FIGURE OUT PATTERN]. The second
              number is circled.</note>
          </ab>
          <ab>
            <stamp type="postmark"> SEATTLE, WASH. | JUL 6 | 9 - PM | 1909 </stamp>
            <stamp type="cancellation"> WORLD'S FAIR SEATTLE </stamp>
          </ab>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head>Two-cent U.S. postage stamp.</head>
            <graphic
              url="https://images.asc.ohio-state.edu/is/image/englishdocs07-06-1909_GS_to_ATS_envelope.jpg.jpg?scale=0.4&amp;rgn=920,80,180,180&amp;fmt=png"/>
            <figDesc>U.S. POSTAGE | TWO CENTS [Portrait of Washington; perforated horizontally and
              vertically; Design A139]</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <!-- See http://www.jamesdire.net/W-F.html -->
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="GMS19090706enc01"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>
  

     <TEI xml:id="MyTextNumber1">
         <teiHeader>
             <fileDesc>
                 <titleStmt>
                     <title><!-- ... --></title>
                     <author><!-- ... --></author>
                 </titleStmt>
                 <publicationStmt>
                     <p><!-- ... --></p>
                 </publicationStmt>
                 <sourceDesc>
                     <p><!-- ... --></p>
                 </sourceDesc>
             </fileDesc>
         </teiHeader>
         <text>
             <body>
                 <div>
                     <p><!-- ... --></p>
                 </div>
             </body>
         </text>
     </TEI>
     <TEI xml:id="MyTextNumber2">
         <teiHeader>
             <fileDesc>
                 <titleStmt>
                     <title><!-- ... --></title>
                     <author><!-- ... --></author>
                 </titleStmt>
                 <publicationStmt>
                     <p><!-- ... --></p>
                 </publicationStmt>
                 <sourceDesc>
                     <p><!-- ... --></p>
                 </sourceDesc>
             </fileDesc>
         </teiHeader>
         <text>
             <body>
                 <div>
                     <p><!-- ... --></p>
                 </div>
             </body>
         </text>
     </TEI>
     <!-- More TEI Documents -->
</teiCorpus>
