<?xml-model href="anderson_letters.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?"?>
<teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
     <teiHeader>
         <fileDesc>
           <!-- For each letter, add editor, scanner, and initial markup -->
             <titleStmt>
               <title>William B. Anderson's Civil War correspondence, 1862-1864</title>
               <editor><persName ref="SPF">Sara Pauline Finch</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="MEG">Meghan Elaine Griesemer</persName></editor>
               <editor role="Principal-editor"><persName ref="#HLU">H. Lewis Ulman</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="CMC">Christopher M. Clark</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="JMK">Jenna Marlene Kamrass</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="KS">Kristin Stack</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="ZAH">Zachary A. Hess</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="MEP">Marie E. Pesut</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="KLA">Katie Leigh Adams</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="KLA">Steve W. Sikes-Gilbert</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="KLA">Jeremy A Smith</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="KLA">Kathryn H. Owsley</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="KLA">Sarah Beth Sitzler</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="KLA">Richard (Dickie) J. Selfe</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName ref="KLA">Michelle Leigh Amos</persName></editor>
               
           <respStmt>
             <resp>Creation of digital scans of manuscript pages: </resp>
             <persName>Laura Denning, Ohio State University Libraries</persName>
           </respStmt>
           
           <respStmt>
             <resp>Creation of initial machine-readable transcript: </resp>
             <persName ref="SA">Steve Agricola</persName>
             <persName ref="MEG">Meghan Elaine Griesemer</persName>
             <persName ref="SPF">Sara Pauline Finch</persName>
             <persName ref="CMC">Christopher M. Clark</persName>
             <persName ref="JMK">Jenna Marlene Kamrass</persName>
             <persName ref="KS">Kristin Stack</persName>
             <persName ref="ZAH">Zachary A. Hess</persName>
             <persName ref="KLA">Katie Leigh Adams</persName>
             <persName ref="MEP">Marie E. Pesut</persName>
             <persName ref="KLA">Steve W. Sikes-Gilbert</persName>
             <persName ref="KLA">Jeremy A Smith</persName>
             <persName ref="KLA">Kathryn H. Owsley</persName>
             <persName ref="KLA">Sarah Beth Sitzler</persName>
             <persName ref="KLA">Richard (Dickie) J. Selfe</persName>
             <persName ref="KLA">Jamie Danker</persName>
             <persName ref="KLA">Michelle Leigh Amos</persName>
             
           </respStmt>
           
         </titleStmt>
           
           <editionStmt>
             <p>First Edition</p>
           </editionStmt>
           <!--      Fill this in! -->
           <extent>approx. xxx kilobites</extent>
           
           <publicationStmt>
             
             <publisher>The Ohio State University Library.
               <address>
                 <addrLine n="1">Rare Books and Manuscripts Library</addrLine>
                 <addrLine n="2">327 Main Library</addrLine>
                 <addrLine n="3">1858 Neil Avenue Mall</addrLine>
                 <addrLine n="4">Columbus, OH 43210</addrLine>
               </address>
             </publisher>
             
             <pubPlace>Columbus, OH</pubPlace>
             
             <!-- 
          The <idno> element is only required for documents with a standard id number
          such as a library call number..-->
             
             <idno type="CallNumber">SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
             
             <availability>
               <p>The W. B. Anderson Collection is the property of the Rare Books and Manuscripts
                 Library of The Ohio State University Libraries. Any use of the material should
                 acknowledge such ownership.</p>
               <p xml:id="CreativeCommons">
                 <![CDATA[<a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"><img alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0" src="http://creativecommons.org/images/public/somerights20.png"/></a><br/>This work is licensed under a <a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0  License</a>.
                  This license does not transfer any rights regarding material used in the edition by permission of a third party.]]>
               </p>
             </availability>
             
             <date>2019</date>
           </publicationStmt>
           
           <sourceDesc>
             
	           <biblFull>
	             <titleStmt>
	               <title level="u">Civil War correspondence, 1862-1864</title>
	               <author>Anderson, William B. (b. 1822)</author>
	             </titleStmt>
          <extent>"Includes 21 handwritten letters, 4 documents, and 1 CD-ROM. Letters written by
            William B. Anderson to his wife in Pennsylvania. He writes from his steamboat during the
            Civil War, as he ferries Union troops, ammunition and supplies up and down the river at
            Cincinnati and vicinity. Also contains documents showing his expenses and profits and a
            letter from another person. All letters are digitized and available on a CD, included in
            the collection" (OSU Libraries Catalog).</extent>
	             <publicationStmt>
	               <p>The W. B. Anderson Collection is the property of the Rare Books and Manuscripts
	                 Library of The Ohio State University Libraries. Any use of the material should
	                 acknowledge such ownership. The Ohio State University holds copyright to 
	                 all images of manuscript pages used in the edition.</p>
	             </publicationStmt>
	             <notesStmt>
	               <note type="descriptive">
	                 <p><emph rend="bold">Selection of the Source Text</emph>. This edition contains
	                 the twenty letters written by William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa
	                 Anderson, taking a literal rather than figurative clue from what Anderson calls in one letter the
	                 "distres [sic] that this war has brought on the human family." By contrast, the additional
	                 letter in the collection and the four receipts deal exclusively with Anderson's
	                 shipping business.</p>
	                 
	               </note>
	               <note type="introductory">
	                 <p>
	                   <figure rend="embed" n="250">
	                     <head>Salutation from letter of 27 June 1862</head>
	                     <graphic url="./image_mydearwife.png"/>
	                     <figDesc>
	                       My Dear Wife
	                     </figDesc>
	                   </figure>
	                 </p>
	                 
              <p> In some ways, William B. Anderson's short letter of 27 June 1862 to his wife, Mary
                Louisa, typifies the twenty-one letters from William to Louisa that survive in the
                collection of the Rare Books and Manuscripts Library at The Ohio State University.
                It addresses three of the four broad topics about which he repeatedly writes to his
                wife during the summers of 1862, 1863, and 1864: managing domestic affairs and
                sustaining familial bonds when family members are separated for long periods by
                great distances; the rhetoric and logistics of mid-nineteenth-century
                correspondence; and the economic, logistical, and physical challenges of the
                riverboat business, especially on a waterway as critical as the Ohio River in the
                midst of the American Civil War (in other letters, Anderson also reflects more
                broadly on the uncertainties, vicissitudes, and suffering faced by civilians and
                soldiers alike in wartime).</p>
	                 <p>However, this letter is also unique. All but two of the letters were written from Cincinnati, 
	                   a thriving center of commerce on the Ohio River approximately halfway between its source at 
	                   the confluence of the Allegheny and Monongahela Rivers in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania and its confluence 
	                   with the Mississippi River a mile or so south of Cairo, Illinois. The remaining letter in the collection 
	                   was written from St. Louis, Missouri&#8212;though Anderson mentions writing from Louisville, Kentucky and 
	                   Nashville, Tennessee as well. This letter was written from Pittsburgh, William and Louisa's home town. 
	                   Presumably, he had been visiting his family and had expected to leave Pittsburgh by the Friday in late 
	                   June when he wrote the letter; he writes to inform his wife of a delay.</p>
	                 <p>As the collection in general reveals, delays were common, caused variously by negotiations over freight, 
	                   water levels on the river, mechanical difficulties, and various military complications. 
	                   Arrangements regarding freight seem to have kept Anderson in Pittsburgh overnight on June 27. 
	                   He wants to secure a full load before leaving Pittsburgh because he "cannot depend upon getting 
	                   any freight below here." He takes the opportunity to ask Louisa to send down "the Can of milk and 2 
	                   jars of lard and my clothes and overcoat." The definite article stands out: <emph rend="italic">the</emph> 
	                   Can of milk. 
	                   One wonders whether, in his habitual haste (on which he often blames poor spelling and handwriting), 
	                   he has simply rushed off and forgotten these items, and Louisa has sent him a note asking what she 
	                   should do with them. In any case, in his haste to send her instructions, he crosses out the next 
	                   two lines of his letter and recomposes them. Characteristically, the life of a riverboat captain 
	                   seems frenetic.</p>
	                 <p>It is also worth noting that he arranges to convey a note to his wife via "some one on the Shore at 
	                   Shousetown." While the Andersons clearly handled much of their correspondence through the U.S. 
	                   mail (he mentions post offices several times, and the collection includes one stamped envelope), 
	                   they often convey both messages and goods through intermediaries traveling by rail or river.</p>
	                 <p>Anderson's closing request constitutes something of a refrain in the letters. He asks Louisa to call 
	                   on a Mr. Russell (probably John Russell, a local merchant) in order to collect money owed him, 
	                   noting that he must meet his obligations on the crew's upcoming payday. Aside from suggesting that 
	                   riverboat captains had to watch their cash flow carefully, this request reminds us that Louisa played 
	                   a key role not only in caring for the Anderson household, including their four children (a fifth would 
	                   be born in 1865), but also in tending to their business interests. Though we have only William 
	                   Anderson's side of the correspondence, the letters reveal many details of Louisa's everyday life as well.</p>
	                 <p>It is Louisa, presumably, whom we have to thank for initially preserving the letters, probably for 
	                   the very common, personal reasons to which David Levy alludes in <title level="m">Scrolling Forward: Making Sense of 
	                     Documents in the Digital Age</title>: "In the privacy of our own homes we are likely to hold on to any number 
	                   of treasures: cards, letters, and notes written long ago, photographs, scrapbooks filled with mementoes 
	                   from an earlier era. We can't throw them out, even if we can't say why. We may look at them rarely or 
	                   not at all, yet still it is somehow comforting to know they are there. It's as if something of 
	                   importance is embedded in their very substance. This has less to do with their information content 
	                   per se than with the emotions they evoke and the personal relationships they signify and embody" (96&#8211;97). 
	                   The Rare Books and Manuscripts Library at The Ohio State University purchased the letters in part 
	                   because they fit into a larger goal of acquiring materials that reveal the "common man's view of great 
	                   events," and war letters are one focus of that larger effort (Smith). The collection as a whole, and 
	                   the letter of 27 June 1862 more specifically, should also prove interesting to business historians and 
	                   students of letter writing in American culture (Hewitt). The passing of time has made the everyday 
	                   information in the letters newly valuable, though the letters also retain the power Levy speaks of to 
	                   evoke the emotional fabric of everyday life, especially when it becomes frayed in the course of great 
	                   events.</p>
	               </note>
	             </notesStmt>
	           </biblFull>
             
             <!-- SEE STEPHENS FOR OTHER LIST TYPES -->
             <!-- FOR EACH LETTER, UPDATE LIST OF PLACES -->
             
             <listPlace>
               <head>Places Mentioned in the Text</head>
               <place type="city" xml:id="LouisvilleKY" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Louisville</placeName>
                 <desc>In his letter of June 16, Anderson notes that he did not 
                 write to Louisa during a previous stop in Louisville, KY.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Kentucky</region>
                 <region type="county">Jefferson</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>38.2500 -85.7500</geo>
                 </location>
                 <event type="stop" when="1862-06">
                   <label></label>
                 </event>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="CincinnatiOH" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Cincinnati, OH</placeName>
                 <desc></desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Ohio</region>
                 <region type="county">Hamilton</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>39.1500 -84.4500</geo>
                 </location>
                 <event type="stop" when="1862-06-16">
                   <label></label>
                 </event>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="Shousetown" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Shousetown</placeName>
                 <desc></desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="Pennsylvania"></region>
                 <region type="Allegheny"></region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>40.560833 -80.223200</geo>
                 </location>
                 <event type="stop" notBefore="1862-06-27" notAfter="1862-07-11">
                   <label></label>
                 </event>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="PittsburghPA" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Pittsburgh</placeName>
                 <desc></desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Pennsylvania</region>
                 <region type="county">Allegheny</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>40.4333 -79.9833</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="MaysvilleKY" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Maysville</placeName>
                 <desc></desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="Kentucky"></region>
                 <region type="Mason"></region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>38.6333 -83.7333</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="island" xml:id="Buffington" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Buffington Island</placeName>
                 <desc>In his letter of 10 August 1862, Anderson describes having to lighten his ship's load
                   to navigate around Buffington Island, an island on the Ohio River in Jackson County, West Virginia 
                   north of Pomeroy, Ohio. Nearby in Ohio, the only battle to occur on Ohio soil 
                   during the American Civil War, the Battle of Buffington Island, took place on 
                   July 19, 1863.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Ohio</region>
                 <region type="county">Meigs</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>38.9833 -81.7667</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="island" xml:id="Blennerhassett" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Blennerhassett Island</placeName>
                 <desc>In his letter of 10 August 1862, Anderson describes having to lighten his ship's load
                 to navigate around Blennerhassett Island, near Belpre, Ohio</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">West Virgina</region>
                 <region type="county">Wood</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>39.2667 -81.6167</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="township" xml:id="southbend" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>South Bend</placeName>
                 <desc></desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Pennsylvania</region>
                 <region type="county">Armstrong</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>40.6167 -79.3667</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="gallipolis" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Gallipolis</placeName>
                 <desc>Gallipolis is a city along the Ohio River in Gallia County, Southeast Ohio</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Ohio</region>
                 <region type="county">Gallia</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>38.7833 -82.2000</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="army_camp" xml:id="campPort" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Camp Portsmouth</placeName>
                 <desc>Camp Portsmouth served as a training and organizational camp from 1861-1862 for
                   The 117th Regiment Ohio Volunteer Infantry, the 1st Regiment Ohio Heavy Artillery, and the 18th Regiment Ohio Light Artillery
                 <bibl><ref target="#campPortsmouth"></ref>"Camp Portsmouth"</bibl>.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Ohio</region>
                 <region type="county">Scioto</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>38.7167 -82.9833</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="gramsta" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName notBefore="1837">Graham's Station</placeName>
                 <desc>Graham's Station, Ohio was incorporated in 1841 and was later renamed Racine.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Ohio</region>
                 <region type="county">Meigs</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>38.9667 -81.9000</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="augusta" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Augusta, Kentucky</placeName>
                 <desc>A city in Kentucky along the Ohio River east of Cincinnati, Ohio. In his letter
                 of 28 September 1862, Anderson reports that he has been ordered to take soldiers to Augusta
                 in response to the Battle of Augusta, which took place the previous day.
                 </desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Kentucky</region>
                 <region type="county">Bracken</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>38.7667 -84.0000</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="SLM" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Saint Louis, Missouri</placeName>
                 <desc>Anderson writes from St. Louis on 19 June 1863.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Missouri</region>
                 <region type="county"></region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>38.6167 -90.1833</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="nashville" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Nashville</placeName>
                 <desc>In his letter of 1 July 1863, Anderson he will start for Nashville, Tennessee that evening. Nashville 
                   could be reached from the Ohio River via the Cumberland River, which meets the Ohio at mile 933.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Tennessee</region>
                 <region type="county">Davidson</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>36.1540 -86.7610 </geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="allegheny" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName notBefore="1788" notAfter="1907">Allegheny City</placeName>
                 <desc></desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Pennsylvania</region>
                 <region type="county">Allegheny</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>40.451029 -80.015539</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="lebanon" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>
                 <desc></desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Kentucky</region>
                 <region type="county">Marion</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>37.5667 -85.2500</geo>
                 </location>
                 <event type="battle" when="1863-07-05">
                   <label></label>
                 </event>
               </place>
               <place type="river" xml:id="licking" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Licking River</placeName>
                 <desc>In his letter of 5 July 1863, Anderson mentions navigating a mile
                 up the Licking River to deliver a load of metal.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Kentucky</region>
                 <region type="county">Morgan</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>37.9333 -83.3000</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="lexington" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Lexington</placeName>
                 <desc>In his letter of 5 July 1863, Anderson notes that General Morgan's forces
                 were likely to take Lexington, but in fact they did not.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Kentucky</region>
                 <region type="county">Fayette</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>38.0333 -84.5000</geo>
                 </location>
                 <event type="stop" when="1862-01-01">
                   <label></label>
                 </event>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="richmond" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Richmond</placeName>
                 <desc>The capital of Virgina.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Virginia</region>
                 <region type="county">Henrico</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>37.540304 -77.433150</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="evansville" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Evansville</placeName>
                 <desc>Located on the Ohio River opposite Henderson, Kentucky.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Indiana</region>
                 <region type="county">Vanderburgh</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>37.9667 -87.5500</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="Parkersburg" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Parkersburg, WV</placeName>
                 <desc>In his Letter of 24 August 1864, Anderson speculates about whether
                 water levels will allow him to navigate as far upstream as Parkersburg, WV.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">West Virginia</region>
                 <region type="county">Wood</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>39.2667  -81.5500</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="Racine" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Racine, OH</placeName>
                 <desc>Left freight here when he broke a shaft.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Ohio</region>
                 <region type="county">Meigs</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>38.9667 -81.9000</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               <place type="city" xml:id="Memphis" source="#TGN">
                 <placeName>Memphis, TN</placeName>
                 <desc>Ship Kenton in Memphis trade.</desc>
                 <country>United States</country>
                 <region type="state">Tennessee</region>
                 <region type="county">Shelby</region>
                 <location>
                   <geo>35.1333 -90.0333</geo>
                 </location>
               </place>
               
               
               
               
             </listPlace>
             
             <listOrg>
               <head>List of Organizations Mentioned</head>
               <org xml:id="MCVA" source="WVE">
                 <orgName>Mount de Chantal Visitation Academy</orgName>
                 <state type="school" from="1848" to="2008"></state>
                 <desc>A private catholic women's school in Wheeling, WV established in 1848.</desc>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="LMRR" source="OHC">
                 <orgName>Little Miami Rairoad</orgName>
                 <state type="company"></state>
                 <desc>The Little Miami Railroad 
                   was only the second railroad to be built in Ohio.  
                   The state legislature granted the Little Miami Railroad Company 
                   a charter in March 1836.  The purpose was to connect the city of Cincinnati 
                   to Springfield.  The line was completed between 1837 and 1848</desc>
                 <bibl><ref target="#LMR"></ref>Ohio History Central.</bibl>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="andersonFerry" source="OHC">
                 <orgName>Anderson Ferry</orgName>
                 <state type="company" from="1817"></state>
                 <desc>Ferry service across the Ohio River from Cincinnati, OH to Covington, KY. [NEED CITATION]</desc>
                 <location>
                   <geo>39.085907 -84.622564</geo>
                 </location>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="adams" source="adamsexpress">
                 <orgName>Adams Express Company</orgName>
                 <state type="company" from="1839"></state>
                 <desc>A shipping company that operated through the South, Southwest, and North.</desc>
               </org>
               
             </listOrg>
             
             <!-- FOR EACH LETTER, UPDATE BIBLIOGRAPHY -->
             <listBibl>
               <head>Works Cited in Notes</head>
               <bibl xml:id="HOAC" n="Apfelbaum">
                 Apfelbaum, Charles. <title level="a">Capt. William B. Anderson.</title> <title level="m">History of Allegheny County, Pennsylvania</title>. Chicago: A. Warner &amp; Co., 1889. 298–299. 
                 https://archive.org/details/historyofalleghe01cush/page/298
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hewitt" n="hewitt">
                 Hewitt, Elizabeth.<title level="u"> Lecture to English 569C, Digital Media and English Studies.</title> The Ohio State University. 
                   6 Apr. 2006.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Levy" n="Levy">
                 Levy, David. <title level="m">Scrolling Forward: Making Sense of Documents in the Digital
                   Age</title>. New York: Arcade, 2001.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="SmithG" n="SmithG">
                 Smith, Geoff. <title level="u">Lecture to English 569C, Digital Media and English Studies.</title>. The Ohio State University. 30 Mar. 2006.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="BioRev" n="Biographical">
                 <title level="m">Biographical Review; v. 24, containing life sketches of leading citizens 
                   of Pittsburg and the vicinity, Pennsylvania</title>. Boston: Biographical Review Publishing Co. 1897.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="PittAtlas" n="1876">
                 <title level="a">1876 - Atlas of the Cities of Pittsburgh, Allegheny and Adjoining Boroughs: Plate 41</title>
                 <title level="m">Historic Pittsburgh</title>. http://images.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/maps/showmap.pl?client=maps&amp;image=76v01p41.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="JDE" n="DankerEmail">
                 Danker, Jamie. <title level="u">"Re: Request for permission to reproduce two
                   photos from your  Anderson family site"</title>. Email to H. Lewis Ulman. 20 May 2006.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Green" n="Green">
                 Green, Jerry. <title level="a">Steubenville, Ohio, and the Nineteenth-Century 
                   Steamboat Trade</title>. <title level="m">Ohio History</title> 113 (Winter-Spring 2004): 18-30. http://publications.ohiohistory.org.
               </bibl>               
               <bibl xml:id="Neumeier" n="neumeier">
                 Neumeier, Franz and Carmen Winkler. <title level="m">http://www.steamboats.org/cgi-bin/database.pl</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="WVE" n="May31">
                 <title level="a">May 31, 2008: Mount de Chantal Visitation Academy Graduates Last Class.</title> <title level="m">West Virginia Encyclopedia</title>.
                  https://www.wvpublic.org/post/may-31-2008-mount-de-chantal-visitation-academy-graduates-last-class-0#stream/0.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="LMR" n="LittleMiami">
                 <title level="a">Little Miami Railroad.</title> <title level="m">Ohio History Central</title>. Ohio History Connection. http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/w/Welcome_To_Ohio_History_Central.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="campPortsmouth" n="CampPort"><title level="a">Camp Portsmouth.</title> <title level="m">Ohio Civil War Central</title>. 10 Jun 2019. www.www.ohiocivilwarcentral.com/entry.php?rec=440</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="genealogical" n="Jordan">
                 Jordan, John W., ed. <title level="m">Genealogical and Personal History of Western Pennsylvania</title>. Vol. I. New York: Lewis Historical
                 Publishing Company, 1915.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Brodhead" n="Brodhead">
                 Brodhead, Michael J. <title level="a">Wright, Horatio Gouverneur.</title> <title level="m">American National
                 Biography</title>. https://doi-org.proxy.lib.ohio-state.edu/10.1093/anb/9780198606697.article.0500857.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="histpitt" n="historic">
                 <title level="m">Historic Pittsburgh</title>. University of Pittsburgh Library System. https://historicpittsburgh.org
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="rosenburg" n="rosenburg">
                 Rosenburg, R. B. <title level="a">Morgan, John Hunt.</title> <title level="m">American National Biography</title>. February 2000. https://doi-org.proxy.lib.ohio-state.edu/10.1093/anb/9780198606697.article.0400720
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="regional" n="regional">
                 <title level="m">Regional Cooperation for Water Quality Improvement in Southwestern Pennsylvania</title>. Water Science and Technology Board. Washington,
                 D.C., 2005. https://www.nap.edu/read/11196/chapter/4#36
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="adamsexpress" n="adamsexpress">
                 <title level="m">Adams Express Company Journal</title>. Explore UK. https://exploreuk.uky.edu
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="McBurney" n="Gaines"> Gaines, W. Craig. <title level="m">Encyclopedia of
              Civil War Shipwrecks</title>. LSU Press, 2008.
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="historyof" n="historyof">
                 <title level="m">History of Washington County, Ohio, with illustrations and biographical sketches</title>. Ohio, H. Z. Williams &amp; bro., 1881.
               </bibl>
               
               
               
               
             </listBibl>
             
	        </sourceDesc>
           
         </fileDesc>
       
       <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
           <p>This edition belongs to a series of collaboratively produced electronic editions of
             previously unpublished nineteenth-century American manuscripts held in the Rare Books
             and Manuscripts Library (RBMS) at The Ohio State University Libraries. Other editions
             include "Selected Entries from the Lucius Clark Smith Diaries,
             30 July 1862 to 31 December 1862"; "My Dear Elizabeth," five letters written by Sophia Peabody Hawthorne to her
             sister Elizabeth Palmer Peabody between ca. 1837 and 1868; "Journal of a Tour to Europe," 
             by Samuel Sullivan Cox; and Louisa A. Doane's "Journal
             of Two Ocean Voyages (1852-1853)."</p>
           
           <p>Each text was initially edited in connection with an undergraduate or graduate course
             on electronic textual editing offered by H. Lewis Ulman, Associate Professor of
             English at The Ohio State University. The courses provided students with an
             opportunity to explore issues of textuality and mediation that arise when our
             cultural archives spread from page to screen and from library shelves to networked
             databases. Electronic textual editing served as each class's context for examining
             what happens—and envisioning what might happen—when artifacts in one medium are
             represented in another medium, especially with regard to the interpretive work of
             reading. Electronic textual editions also provided a contact zone that helped
             students reflect on what manuscript, print, and "born digital" artifacts can tell us
             about their unique properties and their relationships to one another.</p>
           
           <p>While the students' work focused on providing reliable textual editions, they also
             explored four threads inextricably woven into the work of electronic textual editing:
             the lives and historical milieu evoked by the texts; the history, characteristics,
             and preservation of physical and digital texts; the editorial processes and decisions
             that shape particular interpretations and presentations texts; and the mediation of
             electronic delivery systems.</p>
           
           <p>These conceptual focuses, along with the time constraints of academic terms and the
             need to train students who had, typically, no prior experience in textual editing or
             the various technologies employed in electronic textual editing, strongly influenced
             the selection of texts in this series. Working with curators in the RBMS, Professor
             Ulman identified previously unpublished manuscript materials that were of potentially
             broad interest and that reflected a curatorial focus of the RBMS collection—for
             example, letters and personal diaries that connect private lives with larger
             historical contexts. Focusing on unique manuscript materials not, in all but one
             case, associated with other copies or later published versions also eliminated the
             need to compare multiple copies or states of the same work, perhaps held in other
             archives, an impractical task in the course of an academic term. Other practical
             matters also informed the choice of materials, including the possibility of scanning
             the source documents before the class so that students could work with both the
             original documents and high-resolutions facsimiles as they transcribed and encoded
             the source texts.</p>
           
           <p>Thus, the editions in this series are documentary editions—interpretations and
             representations of single documents—designed to provide wider exposure and access to
             manuscript materials that might otherwise be overlooked, and to provide users with a
             variety of tools for studying those texts.</p>
           
        <p>While providing a reliable textual edition is a <hi style="font-style:italic;">sine qua non</hi>, the Stephens edition also
          explores ways of telling four stories inextricably woven into our work: the lives and
          historical milieu evoked by the texts, the history of the physical documents, the
          editorial process that gave rise to this particular interpretation of the texts, and the
          mediation of our electronic delivery system. </p>
           
           <p> Over the course of several years following the classes in which students worked on
             the editions, Professor Ulman revised the introductory materials to ensure stylistic
             consistency and proofed the transcription and encoding. He also redesigned the
             structure of the editions to meet the requirements of Ohio State's institutional
             repository, evolving accessibility standards, and feedback from peer reviewers.
             However, he did not undertake a complete retranscription of the source text or
             revision of the students' introductory essays and annotations.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
           <p>
             <emph rend="bold">Scanning</emph>. The manuscript pages were scanned as 24-bit TIFF images
             at 400 dots per inch (dpi), then coverted to 8-bit JPEG images at 400 dpi and full
             quality. All edges were overscanned by at least 1/4 inch. No color correction was used at any stage of image
             preparation, but a scan of a photographer's 18% grey card on the same scanner
             produced RGB values at the center of 91/95/107 after applying a 150% Gaussian Blur in
             Adobe Photoshop to average color values. Thus, a properly configured monitor should
             provide a reasonable approximation of colors on the manuscript pages.. 
           </p>
           
           <p><emph rend="bold">Transcription</emph>. Editing of the Anderson letters emphasizes diplomatic transcription: 
             abbreviations, recoverable cancelations, punctuation, spelling, underlining, additions above and below
             the line or in the margins, capitalization, line breaks, and page breaks 
             have all been transcribed and encoded as they appear in the original manuscripts. The
             representation of those features varies depending on the view of the letter. An explanation of 
             the presentation in each view of the letters can be read via the "About this View" link
             at the top of each view's page.</p>
             
           <p><emph rend="bold">Markup and Annotation</emph>. XML encoding of the Anderson letters follows The
             Text Encoding Initiative's (TEI) <title level="m">P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>,
             as customized for the project using the TEI's ODD ("One Document Does it All") process.
             This editorial introduction and the three "views" of the letters were generated from the main XML file
             using XSL transformations to produce HTML Web pages. Several of the appendices were encoded in HTML separately.
             A more detailed description of the markup can be found via the "Appendices" menu, and all source files
             (XML, XSL, CSS, ODD, RNC) can be viewed and downloaded via the "Source Files" menu.</p>
             
             <p>Introductory material (such as this editorial introduction) as well as annotated lists of people, places, ships, 
               and organizations mentioned in the letters are encoded in the TEI header of the main XML
             document. Other explanatory annotations are linked directly from the text. Separate appendices provide 
             further information about the project (e.g., acknowledgements, editors' bios, and so on). 
             All these ancillary materials can be viewed via the menus at the top of each page.</p>
           
           <p>
             <emph rend="bold">Proofing</emph>. Students who created the original transcriptions proofread their own
             transcription and encoding. In preparation for peer review by NINES and preservation in The Ohio State University's 
             Knowledge Bank, the transcriptions and encoding were once again proofread by Professor Ulman.
           </p>
           <p>
             <emph rend="bold">Peer Review</emph>. Anonymous reviewers for NINES provided peer-reviews for the editions, in response to 
             which they were revised and then reviewed by NINES editors before being listed in the NINES database.
           </p>
           <p>
             <emph rend="bold">Production and Archival Location of Digital Assets</emph>.
             All of the files associated with this edition are accessed via, and archived in, The Ohio State University's
             institutional repository, the Knowledge Bank.
           </p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>          
             <p>
             <emph rend="bold">Encoding Guidelines</emph>. The TEI-compliant transcripts of the source documents follows the 
             P5 version of the Text Encoding Initiative's <title level="m">P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>, 
             as customized using the .ODD file listed under the "Source Files" menu.
           </p>         
         </refsDecl>
         
         <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
             <bibl>
               <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
             </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         
       </encodingDesc>
       
       <profileDesc>
         <creation>
           <date>2006-06-06</date>
         </creation>
         
         <particDesc>
           <listPerson type="mentioned">
             <head>People Mentioned in William B. Anderson's Letters</head>
             <person xml:id="MLA" source="HOAC">
               <persName>Anderson, Mary Louisa, née Fischgens</persName>
               <note type="biographical">Mary Louisa Fischgens (1837-1911) and Capt. William B. Anderson (1822-1897) were married September
                 15, 1853 in Cincinnati, Ohio. They had five children.</note>
               <birth when="1837"><placeName></placeName></birth>
               <death when="1911"><placeName></placeName></death>
               <bibl><ref target="HOAC"><title level="m">History of Allegheny County</title> (298).</ref></bibl>
             </person>
             <person xml:id="MAF" source="XXX">
               <persName>Fischgens, Anna Mary, née Woolslayer</persName>
               <note type="biographical">Mary Louisa Anderson's mother.</note>
               <birth when="1812-07-12"><placeName></placeName></birth>
               <death when="1897-11-25"><placeName></placeName></death>
               <bibl><ref target="HOAC"><title level="m">History of Allegheny County</title></ref>298.</bibl>
             </person>
             <person xml:id="WBA" source="HOAC">
               <persName>Anderson, William B.</persName>
               <note type="biographical"></note>
               <birth when="1822"><placeName></placeName></birth>
               <death when="1897"><placeName></placeName></death>
               <bibl><ref target="HOAC"><title level="m">History of Allegheny County</title> (298).</ref></bibl>
             </person>
             <person xml:id="WYA" source="HOAC">
               <persName>Anderson, William Y.</persName>
               <note type="biographical">Son of William B. Anderson and Mary Louisa Fischgens Anderson. 
                 He Married Nancy C. McKinely. He resided in Shoustown, Pa. He died of typhoid in PA, leaving a widow and 
                 two children. He is buried in Allegheny Cemetery.  He left a widow and two young children.</note>
               <birth when="1855"><placeName></placeName></birth>
               <death when="1890"><placeName></placeName></death>
               <bibl><ref target="HOAC"><title level="m">History
                 of Allegheny County</title></ref>298</bibl>
             </person>
             <person xml:id="JLA" source="HOAC">
               <persName>Anderson, John L.</persName>
               <note type="biographical">John L. Anderson (1859-1922). Son of William B. Anderson and Mary Louisa Fischgens Anderson. 
                 Resided at the homestead. Wounded in Spottsylvania, Va., May 14, 1864, while serving the sixty-second 
                 Pennsylvania volunteers from Antietam to Appomattox. He survived typhoid in 1890. He never married. He is 
                 buried in the Allegheny Cemetery.</note>
               <birth when="1859"><placeName></placeName></birth>
               <death when="1922"><placeName></placeName></death>
               <bibl><ref target="HOAC"><title level="m">History
                 of Allegheny County</title></ref>298</bibl>
             </person>
             <person xml:id="russell" source="BioRev">
               <persName>Russel, John</persName>
               <note type="biographical">John Russel was “a prominent merchant 
                 on Liberty Street for many years.”</note>
               <bibl><ref target="BioRev"><title level="m">Biographical Review</title></ref>205</bibl>
             </person>
             <person xml:id="HGWright" source="Brodhead">
               <persName>Wright, Horatio Gouverneur</persName>
               <note type="biographical">General Wright commanded the Division of Ohio from August 1862 to March 1863.</note>
               <birth when="1820-03-06"><placeName>Clinton, Connecticut</placeName></birth>
               <death when="1899-07-02"><placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName></death>
               <bibl><ref target="ANB">American National Biography</ref>https://doi-org.proxy.lib.ohio-state.edu/10.1093/anb/9780198606697.article.0500857</bibl>
             </person>
             <person xml:id="Morgan" source="TGN">
               <persName>Morgan, John Hunt</persName>
               <note type="biographical">In his letter of 5 July 1863, Anderson refers to the burning
                 of Lebanon, KY during one of General Morgan's raids on Union forces.</note>
               <birth when="1825-06-01"><placeName>Huntsville, Alabama</placeName></birth>
               <death when="1864-09-04"><placeName>Greenville, Tennessee</placeName></death>
               <bibl>Rosenburg, R. B.</bibl>
             </person>
             <person xml:id="hatch" source="States">
               <persName>George Hatch</persName>
               <note type="biographical">George Hatch served as mayor of Cincinnati from 1861-1863.</note>
               <bibl>States at War, Volume 5: A Reference Guide for Ohio in the Civil War. <!--https://books.google.com/books?id=VMFRCgAAQBAJ&pg=PA165&lpg=PA165&dq=George+Hatch+mayor++cincinnati&source=bl&ots=pTmwDOcAR2&sig=ACfU3U16FTG0UkK9YFtEs7SIsWX6ZxQqnw&hl=en&sa=X&ved=2ahUKEwi_97q67_XiAhUBiqwKHb8EA9M4ChDoATAHegQIBxAB#v=onepage&q=George%20Hatch%20mayor%20%20cincinnati&f=false--></bibl>
             </person>
             
             
           </listPerson>
           
           <listPerson type="editors">
             <head></head>
             <person>
               <persName></persName>
             </person>
           </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         
         <langUsage>
           <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>

         <handNotes>
           <handNote xml:id="WBAink" medium="ink">Anderson, William B.</handNote>
           <handNote xml:id="UnknownPencil">Pencilled notes in an unidentified hand.</handNote>
         </handNotes>
         
         <!-- FOR EACH LETTER, UPDATE LCSH KEYWORDS -->
         <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
             <term>Anderson, William B. (1822-1897)</term>
             <term>Anderson, Mary Louisa Fischgens (1837-1911)</term>
             <term>Morris, George</term>
             <term>Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh</term>
             <term>Pennsylvania -- Shousetown</term>
             <term>River boats -- United States</term>
             <term>Ohio -- Cincinnati</term>
             <term>Kentucky -- Louisville</term>
             <term>Woolslayer, Mary Ann</term>
             <term>McNamer, Mary</term>
             <term>River boats -- United States -- Sources</term>
             <term>United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865</term>
             <term>Tennessee -- Nashville</term>
             <term>Pennsylvania -- Parkersburg</term>
             <term>Pennsylvania -- Lumkford Prison</term>
             <term>River boats -- United States</term>
             
           </keywords>
         </textClass>
         
       </profileDesc>
       
       <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-01-01" who="#HLU">Redesign of the edition to match the design approved by NINES peer reviewers;
           editing and proofreading of all files.<roleName>H. Lewis Ulman</roleName></change>
         <change when="2006-08-22" who="#HLU">Manuscripts read aloud by assistant (Catherine A. Ulman) while principal editor 
           checked transcriptions.<roleName>H. Lewis Ulman</roleName></change>
         <change when="2006-08-10" who="#HLU">Cross-check against independent transcription by Jamie Danker (principal editor evaluated discrepancies).
           <roleName>H. Lewis Ulman</roleName></change>
         <change when="2006-08-08" who="#HLU">Spot-check of corrections.<roleName>H. Lewis Ulman</roleName></change>
         <change when="2006-06-06" who="#HLU">Redesign of the edition to match the design approved by NINES peer reviewers;
           editing and proofreading of all files.<roleName>H. Lewis Ulman</roleName></change>
         <change when="2006-06-06" who="#HLU">Initial encoding and editorial work by students in an undergraduate course
           on textual editing.<roleName>The editors</roleName></change>
         <change when="2005" who="#HLU">Initial machine-readable transcription.<roleName>Steve Agricola</roleName></change>
       </revisionDesc>
     </teiHeader>
  
  <!-- INDIVIDUAL LETTERS -->
    
  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620616" n="18620616">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 16 June 1862</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Anderson writes home to Louisa from Cincinnati, Ohio. He is hauling Coal Boat men
                from Louisville, Kentucky. While in Cincinnati, Anderson visits his mother-in-law
                (whom he calls the "old lady") as well as family friends. During the dry, dusty,
                June weather, a fire breaks out near the Ohio River and Third St, destroying several
                houses. Anderson closes the letter by inviting Louisa to accompany him on his next
                trip to Cincinnati.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>William B. Anderson's letter dated June 16, 1862 from Cincinnati and
                addressed to his wife Louisa is written in ink on two sides of a 
                loose sheet of manilla-colored paper measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches 
                tall (19 x 23 cm) and ruled with horizontal blue lines spaced .33 inches 
                (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) unruled top margin. 
                The left edge of the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges 
                are clean, suggesting that the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. 
                The sheet appears to have been folded in half once. A .5-inch by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed 
                printer's mark appears in the upper left- hand corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches
                (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inch (0.6 cm) from the left edge. 
                Although the mark is indistinct, its shape closely matches that of a distinct, 
                similarly sized and positioned printer's mark on a letter dated July 1, 1863,
                which reads "MT HOLLY PAPER CO" over an ornate shield topped by a crown.</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18620616_let">
          <pb facs="Letter01_pg1"/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName> <date when="1862-06-16"></date>June 16/62</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear <rs type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>I did not write to you 
            <lb/>from <placeName ref=" LouisvilleKY">Louisville</placeName> on account of our 
            <lb/>short stay there &amp; thought we would 
            <lb/><choice><corr>beat</corr><sic>beet</sic></choice> the Mail up, we will leave 
            <lb/>here <choice><corr>tonight</corr><sic>to night</sic></choice> we had a good trip 
            <lb/>of Coal boat men up here from <placeName ref=" LouisvilleKY">
              <choice><corr>Louisville</corr><sic>Louisvile</sic></choice></placeName>
            <lb/>but our prospects are poor for a trip 
            <lb/>of either Freight or <choice><corr>passengers</corr><sic>Passenger</sic></choice> up, though 
            <lb/>upon the whole we make a paying trip  
            <lb/>I will finish this half sheet just
            <lb/>before we start &amp; then I can tell you
            <lb/>more
            
          </p>
          <p>
            
            <lb/>We have laid over and will leave this 
            <lb/>Evening we are getting all we want I have 
            <lb/>just been down to see your <rs ref="#MAF">mother</rs><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="mother"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="mother">Mary Louisa Anderson's mother.<bibl><ref target="HOAC"></ref></bibl>.</note> she is not 
            <lb/>very well Today sends her respects  <persName>Ella</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="ella"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="ella">Though unidentified, Ella appears in many letters (context? relations?).</note>
            <lb/>was at school I did not see her. There was 
            <lb/>a large fire down between Third St and The river 
            <lb/>yesterday just one <choice><corr>square</corr><sic>squear</sic></choice> above the old <choice><corr>lady's"</corr><sic>ladys</sic></choice>  
            <lb/>and burnt a lot of Old Houses &amp; other property 
            <lb/>we have had all our rooms but 3 in 
            <lb/>the ladies Cabin full since last night but 
            <lb/>we have not up till this time had a lady 
            <lb/>passenger on our boat the <rs ref="#MAF">old lady</rs> says 
            <lb/>she would like to have you pay her a 
            <lb/>visit so if you think you would enjoy 
            
            <pb facs="Letter01_pg2" n="2"/>    
            
            <lb/>a trip I will offer you an invitation 
            <lb/><del type="recoverable" rend="overwritten" hand="WBA">t</del>we will if no accident get up about 
            <lb/>Saturday &amp; leave again about Tuesday 
            <lb/><choice><corr>today</corr><sic>to day</sic></choice> it is <choice><corr>almost</corr><sic>all most</sic></choice> suffocatingly hot 
            <lb/>and the dust is so thick that I cannot 
            <lb/>scarcely see the buildings along the wharf  
            <lb/>&amp; I think we must surely have a gust soon  
            <lb/>I will stop for I expect to spend Sunday 
            <lb/>with you &amp; the small ones 
          </p>
          <p>
            <lb/>tell <persName>Mary McNamee</persName> that WM was over 
            <lb/>with us last evening and that he is well
            <lb/>we will leave about 4 or 5 PM this 
            <lb/>Tuesday <choice><abbr>Eveng</abbr><expan>Evening</expan></choice>
          </p>
          <closer>
            <salute>Affectionately &amp; <del type="recoverable" rend="overwritten" hand="WBA"></del>Truly Your</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WBA</abbr></choice></persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>
  
  <!-- FINAL PROOFING AGAINST DIPLOMATIC VIEW 8 AUG 2019 -->
  
  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620627" n="18620627">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 27 June 1862.</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Writing from Pittsburgh, Anderson tells Louisa that his boat's departure has been delayed by a day 
                and asks her to send some food and clothes to him at the dock in Shousetown, PA. He also expresses 
                anxiety about whether his trip will be profitable and asks his wife to request 
                some money from a Mr. Russell to help cover an upcoming payday for his crew.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>William B. Anderson's letter dated June 27, 1862 from Pittsburgh and
                addressed to his wife Louisa is written in ink on one side of a 
                loose sheet of manilla-colored paper measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches 
                tall (19 x 23 cm) and ruled with horizontal blue lines spaced .33 inches 
                (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) unruled top margin. 
                The left edge of the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges 
                are clean, suggesting that the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. 
                The sheet appears to have been folded in half once, then again into thirds. 
                A .5-inch by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed 
                printer's mark appears in the upper left- hand corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches
                (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inch (0.6 cm) from the left edge. 
                Although the mark is indistinct, its shape closely matches that of a distinct, 
                similarly sized and positioned printer's mark on a letter dated July 1, 1863,
                which reads "MT HOLLY PAPER CO" over an ornate shield topped by a crown.</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18620627_let">
          <pb facs="Letter03_pg1"/>
          <opener>
          <lb/><add place="margin"> Mr Geo Norris &amp; <unclear>Lady</unclear>
          <lb/>Room # 6 </add><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="Norris"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="Norris">
              This pencilled note appears in the top margin. It was presumably added after
          the letter was composed, but the context is unknown.</note>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#PittsburghPA">Pittsburgh</placeName> <date when="1862-06-27"></date>June 27/62</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>Dear <rs ref="MLA" type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/> I wish to inform you that
            <lb/> we are not able to get out till tom<seg type="softhyphen">
            <lb/>=</seg>orrow we will not leave here till in the
            <lb/> afternoon we are getting a full load
            <lb/> or will have a full load before we <choice><corr>leave</corr><sic>lave</sic></choice>
            <lb/> but Prices are low we are anxious to make 
            <lb/> money and cannot depend upon getting
            <lb/> any freight below here.  You may send
            <lb/> down the Can of milk and 2 Jars of
            <lb/> lard and my clothes and overcoat
            <lb/> <del hand="WBA" rend="overstrike" type="recoverable">I will bring down and hand to</del> 
            <lb/> <del hand="WBA" rend="overstrike" type="recoverable">some one on the shore</del> I will hand
            <lb/> a note for you to some one on the Shore
            <lb/> at <placeName ref="Shousetown" type="place">Shousetown</placeName>.  
            I spoke to <persName ref="#russell">Russell</persName> about
            <lb/> Money and you had better Call on him
            <lb/> as soon in the week as possible as
            <lb/> Saturday is pay day for the hands
            <lb/> and he promised to have some let on
            <lb/> that you are in great need and you Can
            <lb/> fork over to me all you get when I come
            <lb/> home
          </p>
          <!-- TEXT OF THE LETTER between OPENER and CLOSER. ADD NOTES!  -->
            
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Your </salute>
            <signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620711" n="18620711">
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 11 July 1862</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Anderson writes that he hopes his boat will beat riverboat Fanny McBurney to
                Maysville, KY in order to realize more profit on the trip, though he thinks his "prospects are poor" and is concerned
                about delays due to low water. He complains that his sleep has been restless because of mosquitoes,
                and he asks Louisa to write more—and at greater length—about their children and their crops.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>Anderson's letter dated July 11, 1862 from Cincinnati is written in ink on both
                sides of a loose sheet of manilla-colored, unlined paper measuring approximately 7.5
                inches wide by 12.5 inches tall (20 x 32 cm). The left edge of the sheet is slightly
                ragged, while the other three edges are clean, suggesting that the sheet was torn
                from a notepad or bound notebook. It appears originally to have been folded twice
                crosswise and twice lengthwise. At this writing, the ink appears
                brown. A .5-inch by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed
                printer's mark appears in the upper lefthand corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches (1.3
                cm) from the top edge and .25 inches (0.6 cm) from the left edge. Although the mark
                is indistinct, its shape closely matches that of a distinct, similarly sized and
                positioned printer's mark on a letter dated July 18, 1863, which reads "OWEN &amp;
                HURLBUT | SO. LEE | MASS."</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18620711_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter04_pg1"/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName type="city" ref="PittsburghPA"><del type="recoverable" hand="WBA" rend="overstrike">
              Pitts</del></placeName> <placeName type="city" ref="CincinnatiOH">Cin
             </placeName><date when="1862-07-11">July 11/62</date></dateline>
            <lb/><salute>Dear <rs type="recipient" ref="MLA">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/> I have <del type="recoverable" rend="overstrike">on</del>but a moment to
            <lb/> drop you a line we are about to leave
            <lb/>here it is now 1 Oclock and we are
            <lb/>anxious to leave ahead of the <name type="ship">Fanny McBurny</name><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="McBurny"/>
            <note resp="ed" xml:id="McBurny">Presumably the Fanny McBurney (Fanny McBurnie), a Union stern-wheeled steamer built
              at Cincinnati in 1860 <bibl>Gaines 94; History of Washington County 379</bibl>.</note>
            <lb/>for by doing so we Can beat her to Mays<seg type="softhyphen">
            <lb/>=</seg>ville and by so doing will be benefitted
            <lb/>Materially our prospects are poor &amp; we can
            <lb/>not count on making much this trip but
            <lb/>are bound <supplied reason ="omitted">to</supplied> Keep the Boat moving I
            <lb/>Telegraphed t<supplied reason="omitted">o</supplied> <placeName type="city" ref="PittsburghPA">Pitt</placeName> today to see what the 
            <lb/>prospect of water was &amp; have not got an
            <lb/>Answer to my dispatch yet,  I am extremely 
            <lb/>Anxious to get home and will go as soon
            <lb/>as water &amp; other circumstances will permit
            <lb/>last night was the worst night I ever attempted
            <lb/>to put in, I never saw the like of the mosquitoes
            <lb/>I tried to Sleep in my room &amp; Failed and then
            <lb/>failed and tried in the recess at the stern and
            <lb/>failed then also &amp; then on the Boiler deck &amp;
            <lb/>from that to the hurricane deck &amp; still failed
            <lb/>and John &amp; I started up town and got a
            <lb/>good room at the spence house and slept from
            <lb/>1 to 5 oclock which is the best sleep I have
            <lb/>had for a week.  You would not think that
            <lb/>the mosquitoes could be as large and <choice><corr>plentiful</corr><sic>plentifull</sic></choice> as
            <lb/>they are <persName>John</persName> says that they are worse than
            <lb/>they were at California.  Enough of Complaints 
            <lb/>I think you might string out your letters
            <lb/>a little longer as you have a good and cool
            <lb/>place to write and I have not,  give my love
            <lb/>to the children and yourself  I am in a hurry
            <lb/>Excuse bad writing  
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <salute>Your Husband</salute>
            <lb/><signed>
              <persName ref="WBA">WB Anderson</persName>
            </signed> 
           </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
          <postscript>
            <pb facs="Letter04_pg2"/>
            <p>
              <lb/>Write to me and let me know how 
              <lb/>old man <persName>Walsh</persName> is Coming on also what
              <lb/>the prospects of Corn Potatoes &amp;C. are
              <lb/>also what you and <rs type="person">the Maid</rs> have been
              <lb/>doing and how she <choice><corr>turned</corr><sic>tured</sic></choice> out is 
              <persName type="nickname">Willy</persName>
              <lb/>at school &amp; has <persName>John</persName> got stout
              <lb/>I am interrupted by <persName type="person">Jo</persName> &amp; others and must
              <lb/>stop so good <choice><corr>bye</corr><sic>by</sic></choice> 
            </p>
          </postscript>
            <closer>
              <lb/><salute>Your <choice><corr>respectfully</corr><sic>respectfuly</sic></choice></salute>
              <lb/>
              <signed>
                <persName ref="WBA" type="person">WB Anderson</persName>
              </signed>
              <lb/>
            </closer>
          <postscript>
            <p>
              <lb/>PS be sure to write as before
              <lb/>I enclosed an <choice><corr>envelope</corr><sic>Envellop</sic></choice> in Yesterdays
              <lb/>letter
             </p>
            <closer>
               <lb/>
              <signed>
                <persName ref="WBA" type="person">WBA</persName>
              </signed>
            </closer>
          </postscript>
        </div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <!-- FINAL PROOFING AGAINST DIPLOMATIC VIEW 10 AUG 2019 -->

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620728" n="18620728">
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, July 28, 1862</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Anderson discusses details of his trading and shares reflections on the war, including a group of
                prisoners aboard his riverboat and his sense that the war is "far from over."</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>Anderson's letter dated July 28, 1862 from Cincinnati and addressed to his wife
                Louisa is written in ink on two sides of a loose sheet of manilla-colored paper
                measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches tall (19 x 23 cm) and ruled
                with horizontal blue lines spaced .33 inches (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch
                (3.8 cm) unruled top margin. On the second page. William writes a postscript in the
                left margin. The left edge of the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three
                edges are clean, suggesting that the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound
                notebook. It appears originally to have been folded once crosswise and twice
                lengthwise. A .5-inch by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed printer's mark appears in
                the upper lefthand corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge and
                .25 inches (0.6 cm) from the left edge. Although the mark is indistinct, its shape
                closely matches that of a distinct, similarly sized and positioned printer's mark on
                a letter dated July 1, 1863, which reads "MT HOLLY PAPER CO."</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18620728_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter20_pg1"/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName type="city" ref="CincinnatiOH">Cin
            </placeName> <date when="1862-07-28"></date>Monday 28 1862</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>Dear <rs type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/> Yours came safe to hand I was glad
            <lb/> to hear of the welfare of the children and
            <lb/> sorry to hear of your <choice><corr>affliction</corr><sic>affection</sic></choice> though hope 
            <lb/> you will soon be well. We had a very
            <lb/> serious time getting down we got more
            <lb/> frt than we wanted and stuck fast
            <lb/> 36 Hours at the sisters <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="sisters"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="sisters">Andersons is probably referring to the Mount de Chantal Visitation Academy, 
              incorporated as the Wheeling Female Academy
              under the auspices of the Sisters of Visitation in 1848 <bibl><ref target="WVE"></ref>"May 31, 2008: Mount de Chantal Visitation Academy Graduates Last Class"</bibl>.</note>
            above <choice><corr>Wheeling"></corr><sic>Wheeting</sic></choice> &amp; had
            <lb/> to lighten &amp; then stuck again on <choice><corr>Blennerhassett</corr><sic>Blanerh<seg type="softhyphen">
            <lb/> assets</seg></sic></choice> Isld for 12 Hours &amp; had to lighten, &amp; had
            <lb/> fog &amp; consequently did not get here till
            <lb/> this Morning. I have entered into the Cin
            <lb/> &amp; Parkersburg Trade and will leave here
            <lb/> for Parkersburg Tomorrow at 12 Oclock I have 
            <lb/> a full load engaged one item is 100 Beef
            <lb/> Cattle for <choice><corr>Kanawha</corr><sic>Kanatha</sic></choice><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="kanawha"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="kanawha">
              Anderson probably meant to write "Kanawha," referring either to Kanawha City, WV on
              the Kanawha River, which flows into the Ohio at Point Pleasant, OH between Cincinnati and Parkersburg,
              or the Little Kanawha River, which flows into the Ohio at Parkersburg.</note> for a government office
            <lb/> for which I get $300.no/00 and a full load 
            <lb/> of Flour <choice><corr>whiskey</corr><sic>Whisky</sic></choice> &amp;c. we had no accident
            <lb/> to occur on our down trip that will 
            <lb/> <choice><expan>amount</expan><abbr>amt.</abbr></choice> to anything serious though we wet
            <lb/> a few Sacks of Oats. I will not go down 
            <lb/> to see the Old Lady <choice><corr>tonight</corr><sic>to night</sic></choice> as I want
            <lb/> rest and if I feel not <choice><corr>too</corr><sic>to</sic></choice> much fatigued
            <lb/> by morning I will go down while it is 
            <lb/> cool it has been exceedingly hot here
            
            <pb facs="Letter20_pg2"/>
            
            <lb/> today and I have been very <choice><corr>busily</corr><sic>bussily</sic></choice> engaged 
            <lb/> and had scarcely any sleep since I left 
            <lb/> home so I require rest. <persName>Bill Whitacre</persName>
            <lb/> came down to the Boat this evening to
            <lb/> see me he looks very bad has a very 
            <lb/> long Beard. We had a short talk 
            <lb/> and he gives a <choice><corr>doleful</corr><sic>dollfull</sic></choice> account of 
            <lb/> <choice><corr></corr><sic>of</sic></choice> his experience south. 
          </p><p>
            <lb/> There was some of <choice><corr>the</corr><sic>thee</sic></choice> hardest passengers
            <lb/> down with us from Green <choice><expan>township's</expan><abbr>twps</abbr></choice> brig this
            <lb/> time I ever saw among the<del type="recoverable" rend="erased" hand="WBA">e</del> lot was
            <lb/> 2 <choice><corr>prisoners</corr><sic>Prissoners</sic></choice> in Irons on their way to
            <lb/> <choice><corr>Frankfort</corr><sic>Frankford</sic></choice> Prison<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="Frankfort"/>
            <note resp="ed" xml:id="Frankfort">Presumably, Anderson is referring to the Kentucky State Prison in Frankfort, south
              of Cincinnati.</note> one for downing a 
            <lb/> man &amp; the other for <choice><corr>stealing</corr><sic>steeling</sic></choice> sheep
            <lb/> you would think that the very devil 
            <lb/> had broke loose if you would see
            <lb/> and hear all that I do about the 
            <lb/> <choice><corr>Secessionists</corr><sic>Sesseshinists</sic></choice> and others the war is 
            <lb/> far from over I could have had
            <lb/> a good trip to Nashville but did
            <lb/> not like to go on account of the late 
            <lb/> news from down that way and now
            <lb/> I think we are in the right place
            <lb/> and have good prospects and will make
            <lb/> money right fast we made a little on
            <lb/> our down trip I will stop give all the chil<seg type="softhyphen"> 
            <lb/> </seg>dren a kiss for me <choice><corr>tell</corr><sic>till</sic></choice> <choice><expan>William</expan><abbr>Wm</abbr></choice> to be a good boy
            <lb/> and take care of your own <choice><corr>health</corr><sic>healh</sic></choice>
            </p> 
            <closer>
              <lb/><salute>Affectionatle<supplied reason="omitted">y</supplied> your
              <lb/>husband good night </salute><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B. Anderson</expan><abbr type="initials">WBA</abbr></choice></persName></signed>
            </closer>
           <postscript>
             <p>
               <lb/><add place="margin"> Write to me again as soon as you get this and the letter will
               <lb/>be here on our return I feel well though am almost worn out
               <lb/>though think I will have it easier now as we will not
               <lb/>stick so much in the <choice><sic>Parkersbug</sic><corr><placeName ref="#Parkersburg">Parkersburg</placeName></corr></choice> 
                    trade <persName><choice><abbr>WBA</abbr><expan>William B. Anderson</expan></choice></persName> </add>
             </p>
           </postscript>
        </div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>
  
  <!-- PROOFREAD LETTER, CONTENTS, AND MS DESC 12 August 2019 -->

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620810" n="18620810">
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 10 August 1862</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Anderson complains of low water on the river, reports on a visit to Louisa's mother,
              and assures her that he is unlikely to be drafted as long as he is "in part
              in the government employ" transporting soldiers and government freight.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>Anderson's letter dated August 10, 1862 from Cincinnati is written in ink on two
                sides of a loose sheet of lined manilla-colored paper measuring approximately 7.5
                inches wide by 9.0 inches tall (19 x 23 cm) and ruled with horizontal blue lines
                spaced .33 inches (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) unruled top margin. The left edge of
                the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges are clean, suggesting that
                the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. It appears originally to have
                been folded once crosswise and twice lengthwise. A .5-inch by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm)
                embossed printer's mark appears in the upper lefthand corner of the sheet, 0.5
                inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inches (0.6 cm) from the left edge.
                Although the mark is indistinct, its shape closely matches that of a distinct,
                similarly sized and positioned printer's mark on a letter dated July 1, 1863, which
                reads "MT HOLLY PAPER CO."</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18620810_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter05_pg1"/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH">Cin</placeName><date when="1862-08-10"> Aug 10 /62</date></dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear <rs type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>Your of 7 Came to hand    
            <lb/>today on our arrival &amp; I was glad to hear
            <lb/>of your health being better and that of the
            <lb/>Children<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="children"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="children">At the time this letter was written,
              W.B. Anderson and his wife Lousia  had four children: William Y., Anna M., John L., and
              Robert<bibl><ref target="HOAC">298-299</ref></bibl>.</note> being good I have been well since
            <lb/>I wrote to you though have suffered by
            <lb/>heat Considerably we made 2 trips to 
            <lb/><placeName ref="#ParkersburgWV">Parkersburg</placeName> &amp; are bound up tomorrow again
            <lb/>we have had uncommon hard work to
            <lb/>get up have had to lighten at<placeName ref="Buffington"> Buffington</placeName>  
            <lb/>&amp;<placeName ref="Blennerhassett"> Blennerhassetts</placeName> Island &amp; line flats &amp; Barges
            <lb/>and had a good ell of work and anxiety of
            <lb/>mind for a little money we made between
            <lb/>3 and 400 <choice><expan>Dollars</expan><abbr>Dolls</abbr></choice> last week I cannot tell what our  
            <lb/>prospects will be this week yet but I hope
            <lb/>we shall not lose anything</p>
          <p>
            <lb/>I was down to see your mother this evening
            <lb/>she &amp; Ella are well I did not get down
            <lb/>to see her last trip &amp; it was as well for
            <lb/>she had gone down to <placeName type= "township">South Bend</placeName> and
            <lb/>did not get up till Tuesday she says that
            <lb/>she enjoyed the trip and put up a 
            <lb/>large quantity of Blackberries Fruit of all
            <lb/>kinds is very abundant and <choice><corr>watermelons</corr><sic>watter mellons</sic></choice>
            <lb/>are beginning to get plenty we had some
            <lb/>to eat on the boat this evening that
            <lb/>the crew <choice><corr>bought</corr><sic>bot</sic></choice> which were very fine
            <pb facs="Letter05_pg2" n="01"/>
            <lb/>I wrote a letter to <persName ref="russel"> John Russell</persName> and
            <lb/>requested him to pay my taxes I cannot 
            <lb/>tell you when you may look for me
            <lb/>up as it is very uncertain when I can
            <lb/>go up with the Boat &amp; I want to make
            <lb/>all I can out of her I will not leave
            <lb/>her in any bodys hands untill compelled
            <lb/>to by sickness or war I want you to
            <lb/>try to make yourself as happy as <choice><corr></corr><sic>as</sic></choice> you
            <lb/>Can under the circumstances I know how 
            <lb/>you feel about this war matter but you
            <lb/>need not to make yourself uneasy on my
            <lb/>account for you can rest assured that
            <lb/>I will try to keep out of danger as well
            <lb/>as I can I will be less likely to be draf<seg type="softhyphen">
            <lb/>=</seg>ted by being away than I would be if
            <lb/>at home I am at present in part in the
            <lb/>government employ in the way of a transport
            <lb/>that is we carry a great many soldiers and 
            <lb/>large <choice><corr>quantities</corr><sic>quantitys</sic></choice> 
            of <choice><expan>Government</expan><abbr>Gov</abbr></choice> <choice><expan>Freight</expan><abbr>Frt.</abbr></choice> I expect if the
            <lb/>water gets much lower we will not even
            <lb/><supplied reason="omitted">get</supplied> as far up as <placeName ref="parkersburg">Parkersburg</placeName> and may be
            <lb/>employed to Carry <choice><expan>Government</expan><abbr>Gov</abbr></choice> <choice><expan>Freight</expan><abbr>Frt.</abbr></choice> &amp; soldiers up
            <lb/>as far as <placeName ref="gallipolis">Gallipolis</placeName> &amp; if such should be
            <lb/>the case then I will be Free from the draft
            <lb/>I will expect a letter here when I return
            <lb/>which will be on this day week I will drop
            <lb/>you a line tomorrow before we leave and
            <lb/>let you know what our prospects are Kiss
            <lb/>all the children for me and take care of yourself
            <lb/>and them for me</p>
          <closer>
            <salute>Your affectionate husband</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B.</expan><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <!-- PROOFREAD LETTER, CONTENTS, AND MS DESC 12 August 2019 -->

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620816" n="18620816">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to wife Mary Louisa Anderson on August 16, 1862</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>In this letter, Anderson writes to his wife about his daily tasks and his hardships
                while being a riverboat captain. He reports that a shaft has broken on the boat, and
                hopes the new part will arrive soon. Anderson continues his letter and describes how
                he feels about boarding soldiers on his riverboat. His emotions of grief and sadness
                overrun the second half of his letter, and he explains that he feels terrible
                watching families be torn apart. Anderson closes with warm wishes to his family and
                that he hopes to hear from them soon.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>Anderson's letter dated August 16, 1862 from Cincinnati is written in ink on two
                sides of a loose sheet of lined manilla-colored paper measuring approximately 7.5
                inches wide by 9.0 inches tall (19 x 23 cm) and ruled with horizontal blue lines
                spaced .33 inches (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) unruled top margin. The left edge of
                the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges are clean, suggesting that
                the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. It appears originally to have
                been folded once crosswise and twice lengthwise. A .5-inch by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm)
                embossed printer's mark appears in the upper lefthand corner of the sheet, 0.5
                inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inches (0.6 cm) from the left edge.
                Although the mark is indistinct, its shape closely matches that of a distinct,
                similarly sized and positioned printer's mark on a letter dated July 1, 1863, which
                reads "MT HOLLY PAPER CO."</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18620816_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter06_pg1"/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH">Cin </placeName><date when="1862-08-16">Sunday 16th August 1862</date><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="dateError"/>
              <note resp="ed" xml:id="dateError">Anderson records the day as Sunday, but in August 1862, the 16th fell
                on a Saturday.</note></dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear<rs ref="#MLA">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/> As <persName>John</persName> is going home I take 
            <lb/> the opportunity of dropping you a few lines
            <lb/> to inform you that I am well.  we arrived here
            <lb/> at noon today we have had bad luck since
            <lb/> I wrote you last. we broke our shaft on our up 
            <lb/> trip and shall have to lay here for several
            <lb/> days to have it mended or probably a
            <lb/> new one made.  I cannot learn what our
            <lb/> luck will be in getting it <choice><corr>repaired</corr><sic>repared</sic></choice> till Morning
            <lb/> I will probably get time to go up and see
            <lb/> you while the <choice><corr>repairing</corr><sic>reparing</sic></choice> is going on if I can
            <lb/> leave with any kind of propriety.  it was one
            <lb/> of the worst times that an accident could 
            <lb/> happen as the river is low and Government
            <lb/> wants us and at good prices we were pressed
            <lb/> into <choice><expan>Government</expan><abbr>Gov</abbr></choice> Service at <placeName ref="#gallipolis">Gallipolis</placeName> but were released
            <lb/> on account of our broke shaft</p>
          <p>
            <lb/> We brought down part of 3 Companies of 
            <lb/> Soldiers from <placeName ref="#gallipolis">Gallipolis</placeName> to <placeName ref="#campPortsmouth">Camp Portsmouth</placeName>
            <lb/> and it would have made the hardest heart
            <lb/> melt to have heard the <choice><corr>women</corr><sic>woman</sic></choice> and children
            <lb/> weeping on the wharf Boat while the men
            <lb/> were being ordered on board there was at least
            <lb/> 70 women &amp; 100 children there to take perhaps
            <lb/> the last leave of their Husbands Brothers &amp; Sons
            
            <pb facs="Letter06_pg2"/> 
            
            <lb/> who have answered the call for men
            <lb/> to try and restore peace and restore this
            <lb/> once Glorious Country to peace.  You see
            <lb/> or Know nothing about this war or the
            <lb/> effects produced upon families <del type="unrecoverable" rend="overstrike" extent="one word" hand="WBA"/> by it
            <lb/> I am sick and <choice><corr>tired</corr><sic>tiard</sic></choice> of <choice><corr>soldiers</corr><sic>solders</sic></choice> and <choice><corr>soldiering</corr><sic>soldering</sic></choice>
            <lb/> we see nor hear but little else and what
            <lb/> I am most fearfull <add place="supralinear" rend="caret">of</add> is that the end is
            <lb/> not close at hand we carry every trip more
            <lb/> or less sick and wounded men and any amount
            <lb/> of <choice><corr>women</corr><sic>woman</sic></choice> on their way to look up their sons
            <lb/> Husbands or Brothers while I am writing the
            <lb/> wharf is covered from Broadway to Main
            <lb/> street with fresh recruits from <placeName>Indiana</placeName> &amp;
            <lb/> Ohio on their way to the Little Miami <choice><expan>Railroad</expan><abbr>RR</abbr></choice> 
            <lb/> Depot on their way to Camps to be uniformed
            <lb/> I have not been down today to see your <rs ref="#MAF">mother</rs>
            <lb/> but will before I write again or go up
            <lb/> to see you I will not get to more than
            <lb/> just go up one day &amp; return the next
            <lb/> if I do go at <choice><corr>all</corr><sic>al</sic></choice>.  Write to me soon and
            <lb/> give me all the news and take care
            <lb/> of yourself and all the children
            <lb/> you need not be disappointed if I don’t
            <lb/> go up though if I can leave at al<supplied reason="omitted">l</supplied> I will
            <lb/> be sure to write to me as soon as you
            <lb/> get this in care of <orgName>Isham Fisher &amp; Co</orgName> <placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName>
            <lb/> give my love to the children 
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Your affectionate husband</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>
  
  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620824" n="18620824">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to wife Mary Louisa Anderson on August 24, 1862</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>In this letter, Anderson writes to his wife about . . . </p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>REVISE! William B. Anderson's letter dated August 24, 1862 from Cincinnati and
                addressed to his wife Louisa is written in ink on two sides of a 
                loose sheet of paper measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches 
                tall (19 x 23 cm) and ruled with horizontal blue lines spaced .33 inches 
                (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) unruled top margin. 
                All four edges of the letter, 
                are clean, suggesting that the sheet was bought as a package of looseleaf. 
                It appears originally to have been folded once crosswise and twice lengthwise. 
                At this writing, the ink appears brown and the paper off-white (cream). A .5-inch
                by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed printer's mark appears in the upper lefthand 
                corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inches 
                (0.6 cm) from the left edge.</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18620824_let">
          <pb facs="Letter07_pg1"/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><date when="1862-08-24">Sunday Aug 24/62</date></dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My <choice><abbr>Dr</abbr><expan>Dear</expan></choice><rs ref="#MLA"> Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
          <lb/>I arrived here yesterday at 6 in the 
          <lb/>Morning &amp; Found the crew all well and the Boat 
          <lb/>nearly repaired we are all ready for business 
          <lb/>and have a load engaged and will leave here 
          <lb/>tomorrow for <placeName ref="#gallipolis">Gallipolis</placeName> and may if there is water 
          <lb/>go on up as far as <placeName ref="#Parkersburg">Parkersburg</placeName> and take the 
          <lb/>Freight that we left at <placeName>Racine</placeName> the time we 
          <lb/>broke our shaft. I have had various opportunities 
          <lb/>of Chartering or selling our Boat but none that 
          <lb/>I would accept. We will stand a better chance 
          <lb/>on our return to sell or Charter if the river still 
          <lb/>continues to fall. Our expenses for repairs have been 
          <lb/>considerable though not as much as I had anticipated 
          <lb/>I caught the <rs>old lady</rs> &amp; <persName>Ella</persName> in bed yesterday 
          <lb/>morning when I went in to see them. I went in 
          <lb/>and ran upstairs as I usually do and found 
          <lb/>the doors open and the <rs>old lady</rs> laying on the Sofa 
          <lb/>and <persName>Ella</persName> on the floor both sound asleep and the 
          <lb/>bed standing as it has stood since I first went 
          <lb/>down there while the Kenton was in the <placeName>Memphis</placeName> 
          <lb/>Trade. Though I suppose it is their choice of 
          <lb/>cource we have no business to say a word, they are 
          <lb/>both well I promised to go down to day &amp; see them 
          <lb/>and shall this evening. You ought to have seen 
          <lb/>me in <placeName ref="#PittsburghPA">Pittsburgh</placeName> the day I left I had to get 
          <lb/>a pass 
          <pb facs="Letter07_pg2"/>
          to leave the state and give One Thousand 
          <lb/>Dollars Bail that I would return by the 3rd of 
          <lb/>next month if drafted. I don’t fear any 
          <lb/>such thing as being drafted though may 
          <lb/>be for there is no telling what there will be 
          <lb/>to do yet, the eccitement has abated to a great 
          <lb/>extent here since I left though all along the R 
          <lb/>Road the enthusiasm is beyond bounds in the night 
          <lb/>as well as by day all the small stations that the 
          <lb/>Cars would stop at large quantities of recruits would 
          <lb/>flock aboard and an eaqually large quantity of women 
          <lb/>and children would be there to bid Good bye, there is 
          <lb/>no telling the ammount of distres that this war 
          <lb/>has brought on the human family
          </p>
          <p>
          <lb/>I will have to stop for I have no news of 
          <lb/>any importance write about give my love to the 
          <lb/>children and watch <persName>Anna</persName> for I think that she 
          <lb/>is in need of close attention I was in great hopes 
          <lb/>to see the boat but thus far have been unsuccessfull 
          <lb/>I will expect you to write to me on the receipt of 
          <lb/>this. Take good Care of yourself and the children
          </p>
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Your Affectionate Husband</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <postscript>
           <p>
            <lb/>PS the old lady got July letter 
            <lb/><choice><abbr>WBA</abbr><expan>William B. Anderson</expan></choice>
           </p>
          </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>
  
  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620901" n="18620901">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Mary Louisa Anderson, on September 1st, 1862 from Cincinnati, Ohio.</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>In this document, William B. Anderson lists his itinerary and the business conducted at each port of call.  
                He brings oats to Gallipolis, Ohio; retrieves wheat from
                Graham's Station, West Virginia, and brings it to Blennerhasset's Island, West Virginia.  During his travels,
                it was necessary to build a chute and hire oxen in order to bring the wheat to Blennerhasset's Island.  
                In the latter part of the letter, Anderson discusses his hope to sell his boat, as business is stopped 
                now that the previous travels are finished.  He finishes by sending his love to his wife and children.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>This document is a letter from Captain William B. Anderson (1822-1897), to his wife, 
                Mary Louisa (Fischgens) Anderson. He wrote this from Cincinnati, on September 1st, 1862.  
                It is one page long, with no other notes or enclosures. It is written on lined notebook paper, 
                folded in half lengthwise and into thirds after that.  There is no surviving envelope that goes 
                with it, and it is approximately eight inches by ten inches in size.  There is a printer's mark 
                in the upper-left hand corner, in the shape of a shield surrounded by greenery, with a crown on 
                top.  The left edge of the paper is slightly ragged and worn, as if it had been torn from a
                composition book or a pad of paper bound on the left.</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18620901_lett" corresp="XXX" >
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter08_pg1"/>
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice><date when="1862-09-21">Sept 1st   1862,</date></dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear<rs ref="MLA">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>Yours came safe to hand &amp; I was
            <lb/>glad to hear from you though sorry to hear that
            <lb/>all was not well but hope that before this all are
            <lb/>fully recoved.  I have been quite unwell since I left
            <lb/>here but have got better so took a load of Oats
            <lb/>for the Government up to Gallipolis and from there
            <lb/>we went up to take our Wheat that we left
            <lb/>at Grahams Station and and succeeded in getting
            <lb/>up as far as the foot of Blennerhassets Island
            <lb/>and there we dug a <choice><corr>chute</corr><sic>Shute</sic></choice> wide and deep enough
            <lb/>to draw a flat drawing but 13 inches over and at
            <lb/>3 lads got our wheat over and then hired a man
            <lb/>and a team of oxen to haul the flat <choice><corr>off</corr><sic>of</sic></choice> and left
            <lb/>the 2nd clerk there to attend to it  we arrived here
            <lb/>this morning and will leave at noon for Maysville with a
            <lb/>load of Mules and then I don’t know what we will
            <lb/>do though on our return I will write again  I am
            <lb/>quite busy now but will probably have more <del type="recoverable" hand="WBA" rend="overstrike">time</del>
            <lb/>to write about when I come back again  I
            <lb/>may sell the boat I will try to <choice><corr>anyhow</corr><sic>any how</sic></choice>
            <lb/> I hope to be home soon and will most
            <lb/>likely lay up if I don’t sell things are very
            <lb/>checkered and all <choice><corr>business</corr><sic>bussiness</sic></choice> is stopped give my 
            <lb/>love to the children and take care of them
            <lb/>and you		  
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Your affectionate husband</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620917" n="18620917">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>A homesick letter to Mary Louisa Anderson written from Cincinnati on Sept. 17, 1862, by William B. Anderson</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>In this letter, Anderson shows a bit of emotion as he recounts his 
                encounters with the war thus far. Anderson writes of the
                impoverished life he and his fellow shipmates live and becomes nostalgic
                over the simpler pleasures in life like butter and beef. 
                Anderson asks his wife to pay a vist to John Russell in order to collect 
                the money that Russell owes Anderson; Anderson fears that Russell
                will be slow to repay if his wife does not express a strong sense of need. 
                Anderson closes the letter optimistically speaking of great times to 
                come with his wife and children once he returns home. </p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>This letter in written on a single thin piece of blue-lined paper as the writing on the opposite side shows through. 
                The singular, vertical jagged edge on the left side of the paper suggests that the paper was 
                torn from a notebook or journal. The paper is approximately 8 x 9.75 inches in dimension. 
                Anderson wrote the letter in brown ink  and folded the letter three times( once crosswise and
                twice length-wise) to create 
                six equally-sized sections so that the letter could fit into one 
                of his standard envelopes. On the bottom of the first page, several words are smudged perhaps as a result of
                moisture on the captain's hand from the summer heat or from a rapid writing pace that did not allow the ink to dry sufficiently.</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_1862-09-17_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter09_pg1"/>
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><date when="1862-09-17"></date>Sept 17th 1862</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear<rs type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>Yours Came to hand this morning
            <lb/>&amp; I was glad to hear from you and pleased to learn
            <lb/>that the the children were well  I am also well and
            <lb/>am still employed in the same way as a dispatch
            <lb/>Boat and our trips only extend down as far of late
            <lb/>as <orgName>Andersons Ferry</orgName> 8 miles we made but two yesterday
            <lb/>one at noon and one in the night all is quiet here
            <lb/>now and the majority of the stores are open but there
            <lb/>is nothing doing but what appertains to the war it
            <lb/>is thought that there will be a Battle in <placeName>Kentucky</placeName>
            <lb/>someplace soon but as it will not be in the vicinity
            <lb/>of the <rs>River</rs> I will not get a chance of witnessing
            <lb/>it I have heard so much of war and been so much
            <lb/>among soldiers that I have lost all horrors that I
            <lb/>used to entertain about war I would as soon go
            <lb/>to war as not if I were stout and had no family
            <lb/>for it has almost became a fashion to go all that
            <lb/>are left out of the military ranks are old and
            <lb/>decripped, and it seems as that it has became a 
            <lb/>necessity to turn out.  I will never go unless compelled
            <lb/>to and that in defence of my own property and for
            <lb/>the preservation of the Union  I am sure that the South will
            <lb/>be completely broken up and the north greatly in
            <lb/>debt though the debt will be amongst the north
            <lb/>and the money will be left in the country and all
            <lb/>will be benefitted more or less with it. 
            <lb/>over 
            
            <pb facs="Letter09_pg2" n="2"></pb>
            
            <lb/>I have not seen <rs ref="#MAF">your mother</rs> since I last wrote
            <lb/>to you as I have to stay on the Boat<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="glide"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="glide">Anderson built
              the Glide, a river steamer which he eventually sold to the U.S. government.<bibl><ref target="#genealogical">Jordan</ref>506</bibl>.</note> I have no
            <lb/>opportunity of seeing any body or any thing only soldiers
            <lb/>guns and Cannons.  We are almost <choice><corr>tired</corr><sic>tiard</sic></choice> of this kind 
            <lb/>of work we live almost <choice><corr>miserably</corr><sic>misserably</sic></choice> poor I have not
            <lb/>tasted any Butter for 4 weeks that I could stand and
            <lb/>as for sauce we never have any thing of the kind we
            <lb/>have Beef poor at that and Bakers <choice><corr>bread</corr><sic>Bred</sic></choice> and the poorest
            <lb/>Kind of <choice><corr>vegetables</corr><sic>vegatibles</sic></choice> I ever saw all kinds of marketting is dur
            <lb/>and poor the Country is as dry as a chip for all we have
            <lb/>showers frequenty yesterday and last night and today
            <lb/>is as warm a time as we have had this summer and the
            <lb/>Mosquitoes are the worst I ever saw.  I wish you would
            <lb/>Call on <persName ref="#russell">John Russell</persName> and tell him you want some
            <lb/>Money and keep all that you know to be good such
            <lb/>as U.S. and all Pittsburgh Banks I fear that I shall
            <lb/>fail to get all out of him if I don’t make frequent calls
            <lb/>you must let on to him that you are in need or he will
            <lb/>put you off.  Tell all the children that I am not
            <lb/>in war nor do I intend to go that I will come home when
            <lb/>the river raises and that I have some things for them
            <lb/>I have a fine lot of Peach stones and <choice><corr>watermelon</corr><sic>wattermellon</sic></choice> seeds
            <lb/>saved and I will go up town some of those days after
            <lb/><choice><corr>business</corr><sic>bussiness</sic></choice> resumes more fully and buy each of them some
            <lb/>thing that will please them. I have thought frequently
            <lb/>about <del type="overstrike">about</del> our whereabouts and pleasures nine years
            <lb/>ago, and how as you thought what may our position
            <lb/>be nine year from now.  I hope that we may have no
            <lb/>more to mar our happiness than we have had and
            <lb/>that we may both live and our children live many nine
            <lb/>years to come.  I will stop as my paper is full I will
            <lb/>look for a letter from you on receipt of this and hope to
            <lb/>hear of you and the little ones enjoying good health and happiness
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Ever Truly your husband </salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18620928" n="18620928">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B Anderson to his wife, Louisa, dated
            September 28, 1862.</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>William B Anderson tells his wife how he must take soldiers to Augusta, Kentucky.  Anderson reports that 
                he is doing well and that he is happy to hear that his wife's mother is also doing well.  He wants his wife to take care 
                of herself and the children.  He describes when he thinks he may be home and for his wife to take 
                care of the house and the work that needs to be done.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>This document is letter number 10 from a man named William B. Anderson 
                that he wrote to his wife, Louisa in September of 1862 from Cincinnati.  In 
                all, there were 26 letters written to Louisa from 1862 to 1864.  This particular
                letter is 2 pages long and is written on loose paper measuring approximately
                7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches tall, lined with blue horizontal lines.  The first page
                of the letter is in pretty good condition.  However, there are numerous brown stains
                that could possibly be dirt.  The second page of the letter is in slightly better condition,
                with only a few smudges.  Both pages seem to have been folded, twice long ways
                and once shorts ways.  While the ink is black and legible throughout, there are still
                errors both in spelling and with ink smudges.  The paper William used is a cream 
                color.</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18620928_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter10_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName> <date when="1862-09-28"></date>Sunday Sept 28/62</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear<rs type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/> I am ordered to take up 
            <lb/>a lot of Soldiers to <placeName ref="#augusta">Augusta</placeName> Ky as the
            <lb/>Rebels have taken that place and Burned
            <lb/>it we are to take up a lot of men and 
            <lb/>land them Below to attract and whip
            <lb/>the Rebels if they can I will land
            <lb/>a good piece Below too as I don’t want
            <lb/>shot.  I will write a full <choice><expan>account</expan><abbr>acct</abbr></choice> on our
            <lb/>return  I have no time to write much now,
            <lb/><rs ref="#MAF">your Mother</rs> was here yesterday and is well
            <lb/> I am well &amp; Hope you and all the children
            <lb/>are well take good care of your Health
            <lb/>and that of the children. I wrote you
            <lb/>  a long letter a few days ago  I <choice><expan>received</expan><abbr>recd.</abbr></choice>
            <lb/>yours yesterday and am sorry that <persName type="nickname" ref="#WYA">Willie</persName>
            <lb/>is not well but hope he will soon recover
            <lb/>give my respects to all and write 
            <lb/>often and longer I yesterday learned what 
            <lb/>we are to get for our Boat and my
            <lb/>Portions is forty Dollars clear each day
            <lb/>say nothing about it I hope to stay here
            <lb/>Some time yet  
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Ever Yours truly</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
          <postscript>
            <p>
              <lb/>P.S. We got our Coal found us and one
              <lb/>Hundred &amp; Fifty <choice><expan>Dollars</expan><abbr>Dolls</abbr></choice> per Day for the whole Boat 
              
              <pb facs="Letter10_pg2" n="2"/>
              
              <lb/>as we have not got steam up I will
              <lb/>write on.  in your Letter you said that the
              <lb/>man was there to assess the Buggy I suppose 
              <lb/> the calculation is to lay a heavy tax on
              <lb/> it as we Keep it for our own use all
              <lb/> right I will get it with interest back out
              <lb/> of Uncle Sam while I am here if all goes
              <lb/> well. I suppose Mr Walsh  might as well
              <lb/> Hole what potatoes you <del rend="overstrike" resp="WBA">want</del> <add place="supralinear">dont</add> want
              <lb/>in the Cellar down in the field where they
              <lb/>are and secure them by a fence around there  
              <lb/>and Keep the Cows from there where he pastures
              <lb/> the Stalks.  You can manage things the best
              <lb/>way you think till I come I cannot tell
              <lb/>when I will be back home now but may
              <lb/>accidentally get home sooner that I look
              <lb/>for <del rend="overstrike" resp="WBA">I will</del> it has the appearance of rain this
              <lb/> morning and if water comes to let larger Boats
              <lb/> run there we are done here and home I will go
              <lb/>you cannot <choice><corr>censure</corr><sic>Sensure</sic></choice> me for being so indifferent
              <lb/> as appearing so indifferent about home when
              <lb/> you know what I am to get for staying away
              <lb/>if I can only get what I now get and have
              <lb/>health I would like to stay here a good
              <lb/>while and then when I go home to stay there
              <lb/>the <choice><expan>balance</expan><abbr>Bal</abbr></choice> of my days I will stop so good
              <lb/> <choice><corr>bye</corr><sic>Bie</sic></choice> write soon and give all the news
              <lb/>and Kiss the children</p>  
            <closer>
              <lb/><salute>Yours ever</salute>
              <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WBA</abbr></choice></persName></signed>
              <lb/>Excuse all ever as I am in haste
            </closer>
          </postscript>
        </div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18621007" n="18621007">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>October 7, 1862 Letter from William B. Anderson Pertaining to Everyday Life During the Civil War</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>
                In this letter, Anderson reports hearing shooting along the river.  He references two captains
                who were put in jail for cowardice.  He expresses concern that he does not know what his orders will be from
                one day to the next.  He speaks of a funeral of a friend's son in Maysville, and worries that his wife 
                is sick or mad because he has not heard from her.  This letter was written in October, making it one of the latest
                in the season, possibly indicating unseasonably warm weather or extenuating circumstances.
              </p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>This document is a transcript of a letter written by William B. Anderson to his wife Louisa Fischgens
                in 1862.  It includes one sheet of paper, front and back.  It is written on unlined paper that is approximately 20 cm wide by 32 cm tall.  .  
                This is the first publication of this letter. </p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18621007_let" corresp="#WBA_18621007-env">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter11_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName> <date when="1862-10-07"></date>>Oct 7th 1862</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear<rs type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>As I have found out what we
            <lb/>are to do for a little while I let you know
            <lb/>this morning we were ordered to go below the Bridge
            <lb/>and go in one old trade that is to go in the dispatch
            <lb/><choice><corr>business</corr><sic>bussiness</sic></choice> and we still carry our Gun Squad of
            <lb/>Eleven Men we have just made a trip down to the 
            <lb/> J B Gurly at Andersons ferry &amp; back &amp; found all well 
            <lb/>on board though a little excitement down that way
            <lb/>Some shooting was heard back in the country and
            <lb/>a dispatcher sent out to <choice><corr>ascertain</corr><sic>asscertain</sic></choice>
            the cause and
            <lb/>I look for an answer back such as has occurred
            <lb/>lots of times before that there was a review and shoo<seg type="softhyphen">
              <lb/>"<supplied>t</supplied>ing</seg> of Blank cartridges by way of stimulating the Men
            <lb/>at hearing the cracks &amp;c. I have good reason to
            <lb/>expect that we will be soon discharge as I have
            <lb/>heard that all Boats in <choice><corr>Government</corr><abbr>Gov</abbr></choice> service will be dismiss<seg type="softhyphen">
            <lb/>"</seg>ed this week unless there should be an attack
            <lb/>made by the rebels I find that the <rs type="title">Comadore</rs> is
            <lb/>dissatisfied at some of the boats engaged in the
            <lb/>flottilla and the intention is to call all in and
            <lb/>dismiss all, and such as are absolutely needed he
            <lb/>will engage again.  I feel safe that we shall
            <lb/>fare well and if there is any money to be got out
            <lb/>of the chartering <choice><corr>business</corr><sic>bussiness</sic></choice> we will fare to. You
            <lb/>may think that this is a strange sort of life  
            
            <!-- Page 2 -->
            <pb facs="Letter11_pg2" n="2"/>
            <lb/>and so do I!  I cannot tell today what
            <lb/>I shall do tomorrow nor can a I find out by
            <lb/>enquiry as the <choice><corr>Commodore</corr><sic><rs type="title">Comadore</rs></sic></choice> of the fleet is subject to
            <lb/>the orders of <persName ref="#HGWright">Gen Wright</persName> I suppose you heard
            <lb/>by the papers of the cowardice of <persName>Capt Adams</persName>
            <lb/>and the <rs type="title">Capt</rs> of the <name type="ship">Florence Miller</name> who are both in
            <lb/>Jail and likely to be Kept there I don’t Know
            <lb/>what will be their doom yet.
          </p>
          <p> 
            <lb/>I have no news of any interest to write to
            <lb/>you I have not seen your <rs ref="#MAF">mother</rs> since last
            <lb/>Saturday week she was well  I have not
            <lb/>had any letter from you for over a week
            <lb/> and it worries me are you sick or are you
            <lb/>mad or are any of the children sick let me
            <lb/>hear from you often.  I witnessed a funeral
            <lb/><choice><corr>procession</corr><sic>persession</sic></choice> on last Saturday of one of <persName>James Loves</persName>
            <lb/>children at Maysville and it struck me sorely
            <lb/>to see it as he and us were both married on the
            <lb/>Same day and have had the same number of child<seg type="softhyphen">
            <lb/>"</seg>ren and they lack but a little of being of the same
            <lb/>ages and he lost the youngest one a boy of the same
            <lb/>size and near the same age of <persName>Eddie</persName> it made me
            <lb/>feel very queer indeed as I had not heard from
            <lb/>you when at <choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice> last  I wish you was here or I
            <lb/>Could go up and stay at home a while but that
            <lb/>is out of the question.  Kiss all the children for
            <lb/>me and tell them to be good that I will soon
            <lb/>Come home take good care of yourself good
            <lb/>bye
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Your affectionate husband,</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WBA</abbr></choice></persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
        <!-- First, the envelope. -->
        <div type="envelope" xml:id="WBA_18621007-env" corresp="WBA_18621007-let">
          <pb facs="Envelope02_front"/>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head><emph>Envelope</emph></head>
            <graphic url="./Envelope02_front.jpg"></graphic>
            <figDesc>Envelope for letter of 7 October 1862</figDesc>
          </figure>
            <ab type="postalAddress">
              <persName>Mrs Louisa anderson</persName>
              <address>
                <addrLine>Shousetown</addrLine>
                <addrLine>Allegheny County</addrLine>
                <addrLine>Pennsylvania</addrLine>
              </address>
            </ab>
            <ab>
              <stamp type="postmark">CINCINNATI | OCT | 7</stamp>
              <stamp type="postage">3 U.S. POSTAGE 3 | [Profile image of George Washington] | 3 U.S. POSTAGE 3 </stamp>
            </ab>
        </div>
        
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>
  
  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18621016" n="18621016">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 16 October 1862.</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Anderson tells his wife that his boat's departure has been delayed by a day 
                and asks her to send some food and clothes to him at the dock. He also expresses 
                anxiety about whether his trip will be profitable and asks his wife to request 
                some money from [John?] Russell to help cover an upcoming payday for his crew.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>William B. Anderson's letter dated June 27, 1862 from Pittsburgh and
                addressed to his wife Louisa is written in ink on one side of a 
                loose sheet of paper measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches 
                tall (19 x 23 cm) and ruled with horizontal blue lines spaced .33 inches 
                (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) unruled top margin. 
                The left edge of the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges 
                are clean, suggesting that the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. 
                It appears originally to have been folded once crosswise and twice lengthwise. 
                At this writing, the ink appears brown and the paper off-white (cream). A .5-inch
                by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed printer's mark appears in the upper lefthand 
                corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inches 
                (0.6 cm) from the left edge. Although the mark is indistinct, its shape 
                closely matches that of a distinct, similarly sized and positioned printer's 
                mark on a letter dated July 1, 1863, which reads "MT HOLLY PAPER CO." 
                (see illustrations). Texture? Stiffness? Watermarks? I will have to visit 
                the RBML.</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18621016_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter12_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><date when="1862-06-16"></date>June 16/62</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My <choice><expan>Dear</expan><abbr>Dr</abbr></choice><rs type="recipient" ref="#MLA"> Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>Yours Mailed 13th I got on my 
            <lb/>arrival to the City this afternoon &amp; was glad 
            <lb/>to hear from you.  I have been absent from 
            <lb/>the City for a few days on a trip to Maysville 
            <lb/>we are sill in Gov employ and I suppose we 
            <lb/>will continue some time yet as there is no prospect 
            <lb/>of water.  I will have to be <choice><corr>disappointed</corr><sic>dissapointed</sic></choice> in 
            <lb/>my prospects of going home for while and 
            <lb/>if you can come down I will be glad to 
            <lb/>see you any time you can come you had better 
            <lb/>not attempt to bring the children as they will 
            <lb/>be <choice><corr>too</corr><sic>to</sic></choice> great a charge for you, although I should 
            <lb/>be very happy to see them but you could not be 
            <lb/>at liberty to go any place you might wish with 
            <lb/>them and there is no reason why you could not 
            <lb/>leave them in care of Mary McNamee and Julia 
            <lb/>Porter for that time.  You can make your own 
            <lb/>arrangements about the children as I leave the 
            <lb/>care of them altogether to you I think if you 
            <lb/>will come down 
            <del type="recoverable" rend="overstrike" hand="WBA"> you had better come down</del> you
            <lb/>had better not wait as long as next month 
            <lb/>for fear the river will raise or if it <choice><corr>don't</corr><sic>dont</sic></choice> 
            <lb/>raise &amp; should continue to fall we might be sent 
            <lb/>down below. this <del type="recoverable" rend="overstrike" hand="WBA">is</del> 
            my <choice><corr>advice</corr><sic>advise</sic></choice> to you will be 
            <lb/>for you to come by the Steubenville route and 
            
            <pb facs="Letter12_pg2" n="2"/>
            
            <lb/>leave Pittsburgh at one Oclock or there abouts 
            <lb/>and when you get on board you tell the 
            <lb/>Conductor that you want to take the <choice><corr>sleeping</corr><sic>sheeping</sic></choice> 
            <lb/>Car which they take in tow at Steubenville 
            <lb/>and that will cost you 50 cts extra that train 
            <lb/>arrives at the Dayton &amp; Hamilton Depot at about 
            <lb/>5 or 6 oclock A.M. the ticket office is on 
            <lb/>Liberty Street near the Canal on the left hand 
            <lb/>side of the street it might be that John 
            <lb/>will come down with you and that would 
            <lb/>be better as I think he has acted very foolish 
            <lb/>for I have to pay 5$ each per day for Pilots 
            <lb/>and he might just as well had 200$ dollars 
            <lb/>while he has been at home as not if you should 
            <lb/>come down or have any chance to send me 
            <lb/>that pair of Blue pants &amp; belt down I would 
            <lb/>like to have them as my Pants are getting thin 
            <lb/>and I don’t want to spend any money I can 
            <lb/>help.  I have not seen your mother for 
            <lb/>2 or three weeks I may see her in a few 
            <lb/>days if you come let me know a few days 
            <lb/>before you come when to be on the look out 
            <lb/>for you. 
          </p>
          <p>
            
            <lb/>Tell Old Man Walsh that I will take 12 
            <lb/><choice><expan>dollars</expan><abbr>dolls</abbr></choice> for that Heifer &amp; for him to sell the Hay 
            <lb/>and divide the money I think hay will be very 
            <lb/>High in the spring but I suppose he wants his 
            <lb/>share of the money he can do as he thinks 
            <lb/>best about it.  That Bank notice you spoke 
            
            <pb facs="Letter12_pg3" n="3"/>
            
            <lb/>about I made arrangements with Holmes 
            <lb/>&amp; Sons Brokers to pay all my notes that will 
            <lb/>fall due I told Mr Wright to use what Money 
            <lb/>was deposited at Holmes &amp; Sons belonging to the Boat 
            <lb/>to Pay Notes &amp; when that ran out to use what 
            <lb/>I had there which is sufficient to pay all claims 
            <lb/>that may fall due for a while I will look 
            <lb/>for a letter from you soon and will be 
            <lb/>pleased to hear of you making satisfa<seg type="softhyphen">
              <lb/>=</seg>ctory arrangements to come and see me 
            <lb/>as it seems utterly impossibly for me to 
            <lb/>leave for the present I am to settle up 
            <lb/>our business here up till the 15 of this <choice><expan>Month</expan><abbr>Mo</abbr></choice> 
            <lb/>this or next week and then I will find out 
            <lb/>what I am making but one thing I do 
            <lb/>know is this that I am doing as well as I 
            <lb/>want to with a boat my share of the <choice><corr>profits</corr><sic>proffits</sic></choice> 
            <lb/>and wages is at least 40 <choice><expan>dollars</expan><abbr>>dolls</abbr></choice> per day and that 
            <lb/>is not bad but keep it to yourself. I will stop 
            <lb/>as the mail Closes at 8 Oclock this evening I 
            <lb/>will write soon again but write immediately 
            <lb/>and give me all the news and take good 
            <lb/>Care of yourself and the children and kiss 
            <lb/>all of them for me and tell them to be good 
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Your Affectionate Husband</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>Anderson</expan><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice></persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <lb/>Excuse Haste &amp; Bad writing as there is a constant
            <lb/>ta<del type="recoverable" rend="overwritten" hand="WBA">k</del>lking and fun in the Hall           
          </p>
          <closer>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B. Anderson</expan><abbr>WBA</abbr></choice></persName></signed>
          </closer>
        </postscript>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18630619" n="18630619">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>My Dear Wife: A Riverboat Captain's Missive to His Love</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>On June 19th, 1863, riverboat captain William B. Anderson penned a letter to his wife 
                from St. Louis, Missouri, in which he informs his spouse of matters concerning river
                travel, his salary, and a bout of illness that left him bedridden.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>The single folded sheet, yellowed with age, has
                writing on both the front and back in black ink, as well as a printer's mark in the upper left hand corner.
                William B. Anderson's letter dated June 19th, 1863 from St. Louis, Missouri, is
                addressed to his wife Louisa and is written in ink on both sides of a 
                loose sheet of off-white paper measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches 
                tall (19 x 23 cm).  The paper is ruled with horizontal lines of a blue color that are spaced .33 
                inches (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) top margin that is unruled. 
                The sheet's left edge is not a clean line like the remaining three, suggesting that it was
                most likely  torn from a notepad of some sort.  Written in black ink, the letter appears to 
                have originally been folded once horizontally and twice vertically. 
                A .5-inch by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed printer's mark appears in the upper left 
                corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge of the paper and .25 inches 
                (0.6 cm) from the left edge. Although the exact origins of the mark is inconclusive, it
                resembles a similarly sized and placed printer's mark on a letter dated July 1, 1863, that
                reads: "MT HOLLY PAPER CO."</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18630619_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter02_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline>St Louis <date when="1863-06-19"></date>Saturday June 19th 63</dateline><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="June19"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="June19">June 19, 1863 fell on a Friday, not Saturday.</note>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear<rs type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>I will commence a letter to you 
            <lb/>this afternoon &amp; Finish it tomorrow we arrived
            <lb/>here last night about Midnight we had
            <lb/>a fair trip around &amp; if we get as good a one
            <lb/>back we will make a little money times are very
            <lb/>dull &amp; and prices poor we had all the freight we could 
            <lb/>carry on the water I have several small lots engaged
            <lb/>to go back to  <placeName ref="#LouisvilleKY">Louisville</placeName> &amp; <choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin.</abbr></choice> &amp; I think by Monday
            <lb/>night we shall have all we can carry I had thought
            <lb/>somebody would be here and offer to buy the boat but
            <lb/>the Boat fervor has subsided greatly I had a visit
            <lb/>from <persName>Capt. R. C. Gray</persName> today &amp; he says that he thinks that
            <lb/>the upper <placeName>Mississippi river</placeName> trade would pay us better
            <lb/>than the <placeName ref="#SLM">St Louis</placeName> and <placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin.</abbr></choice></placeName> trade but I dont wish to go up 
            <lb/>there for the present. I had an offer at <placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin.</abbr></choice></placeName> to sell &amp; I will
            <lb/>know what I can do when I return if the party accepts my
            <lb/>offer I will be home Shortly.</p>
          <p>
            <lb/>Sunday Evening I have been rather under the weather
            <lb/>since I left <placeName ref="#LouisvilleKY">Louisville</placeName> &amp; had today to have a 
            <lb/>Doctor &amp; he gave me a lot of <choice><corr>Medicine</corr><sic>Medacin</sic></choice> and as
            <lb/>Soon as I took of it got better he says I would 
            <lb/>have had the ague or a bad attack of Billious 
            <lb/>fever if I had not had relief soon I thought
            <lb/>it was the Neuralgia I had, for one side of
            <pb facs="Letter02_pg2" n="2"/>
            <lb/>of my face &amp; jaw pained me constantly
            <lb/>and my teeth ached &amp; I had one of them 
            <lb/>pulled and it did not do any good and
            <lb/>for 48 hours, I had not eaten one bite nor
            <lb/>slept one minute.  I was not well one minute
            <lb/>at a time until I took the medicine and it
            <lb/>acted like a charm I am of course weak
            <lb/>but feel well and tomorrow I want to go 
            <lb/>and see <persName>Belle Ferguson</persName> I have not been out
            <lb/>of my room nor in fact out of bed all
            <lb/>day till this Evening. I would not have
            <lb/>believed that a few doses of medicine would
            <lb/>do so much in so short a time.  I will
            <lb/>send you a paper or two tomorrow I
            <lb/>hope you are well give my love to 
            <lb/>the children excuse this poor letter
            <lb/>for I can assure you that I have had 
            <lb/>better to say – I will leave here for
            <lb/>Cin Tomorrow night without I get
            <lb/>disappointed. I have been unable to go 
            <lb/>up Town to see how it looks but will
            <lb/>Tomorrow if nothing happens &amp; my 
            <lb/>health improves I <choice><corr>feel</corr><sic>feell</sic></choice> sure I will
            <lb/>be all right again in a day or two
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Yours Affectionately</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <postscript>
           <p>
            <lb/>P.S. I will write again Tomorrow any how
           </p>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B. Anderson</expan><abbr type="initials">WBA</abbr></choice></persName></signed>
          </postscript>
           <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18630701" n="18630701">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>A letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Mary Louisa, from July 1, 1863 written in Cincinnati</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>In this letter, from July 1, 1863, William B. Anderson writes to his wife, Mary Louisa, from
                Cincinnati.  Anderson tells his wife about the Government cargo he is shipping, and the hard
                work that goes along with handling the cargo in the summer heat.  Anderson also gives Mary Louisa
                advice pertaining to family and financial affairs back home in Pittsburgh.  He ends the letter 
                as he does most, with affection for his wife and telling her to kiss "the little ones" for him.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>William B. Anderson's letter dated July 1, 1863 from Cincinnati and
                addressed to his wife Louisa is written in ink on one side of a 
                loose sheet of paper measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches 
                tall (19 x 23 cm) and ruled with horizontal blue lines spaced .33 inches 
                (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) unruled top margin. 
                The left edge of the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges 
                are clean, suggesting that the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. 
                It appears originally to have been folded once crosswise and twice lengthwise. 
                At this writing, the ink appears brown and the paper off-white (cream). A .5-inch
                by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed printer's mark appears in the upper lefthand 
                corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inches 
                (0.6 cm) from the left edge. It reads "MT HOLLY PAPER CO" 
                (see illustration).</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18630701_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter13_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName><date when="1863-07-01"></date> July 1st 1863</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My <choice><expan>Dear</expan><abbr>Dr</abbr></choice><rs ref="#MLA">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>As  I have an opportunity of sending
            <lb/>you a letter by <persName>Mr Wm Russell</persName> I thought I
            <lb/>would embrace the opportunity.  I am well and hope
            <lb/>you are also. we start this evening for <placeName ref="#nashville">Nashville</placeName>
            <lb/>Our cargo is principally <choice><expan>Government</expan><abbr>Gov.</abbr></choice> <choice><expan>Freight</expan><abbr>Frt</abbr></choice> we have for 
            <lb/>one item 1000 Barrels Potatoes there is lots of <choice><expan>Freight</expan><abbr>frt</abbr></choice>
            <lb/>to Go to <placeName ref="#nashville">Nashville</placeName>  I had the offer of 280
            <lb/>six Horses <choice><corr>Wagons</corr><sic>Waggons</sic></choice> 150 ambulances and Horses for
            <lb/>June and 450 tons clothing.  I take 100 tons or
            <lb/>one thousand Barrels Potatoes and as many
            <lb/>boxes of Clothing As I can carry on the water
            <lb/>which will <choice><expan>amount</expan><abbr>amt</abbr></choice> to in all about 1500$ <choice><expan>Dollars</expan><abbr>Dolls</abbr></choice>
            <lb/>for Potatoes and about 12 to 1500$ for the <choice><expan>Balance</expan><abbr>Bal</abbr></choice>
            <lb/>which is in all about a three thousand <choice><expan>Dollar</expan><abbr>Dlr</abbr></choice> Trip
            <lb/>&amp; if we get safe there &amp; back we will make
            <lb/>a good trip it is excessively Hot today I can
            <lb/>scarcely stand it but I hope we will have it
            <lb/>Cooler when we get underway. I have been very
            <lb/>buissily engaged all day have had a good ell
            <lb/>of work to do to get our trip secured there is a
            <lb/>good many way of dodging.  I can not tell
            <lb/>you when I will be home I had some hope of
            <lb/>selling but now all chances have escaped
            <lb/>I will make this trip and I can<add place="supralinear">not</add> tell you
            
            <!-- Page 2 -->
            <pb facs="Letter13_pg2" n="2"/>
            
            <lb/>what I will do next If I cannot make it pay 
            <lb/>&amp; I don’t sell I will lay up till Cool weather
            <lb/>it is murdering ones self by degrees to Boat
            <lb/>such times as those.  I suppose you have best
            <lb/>get a Barrell of N.O. Sugar at <placeName ref="#PittsburghPA"><choice><expan>Pittsburgh</expan><abbr>Pitt</abbr></choice></placeName> either
            <lb/>from  Holmes &amp; Co Market St <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="holmes"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="holmes">A lot labeled "Holmes" appears
              at 15 Market Street on an 1872 map of Pittsburg. <bibl> Historic Pittsburgh, https://historicpittsburgh.org/islandora/object/pitt%3A1872p015/viewer</bibl>.</note> or from Mirer and  
            <lb/>Robinson <placeName>Allegheny</placeName> I would send you the
            <lb/>Money but I suppose you can get it from
            <lb/><persName>Russell</persName> it will cost about 35 or 40 <choice><expan>Dollars</expan><abbr>Dolls</abbr></choice>
            <lb/>you can get <persName>Russell</persName> to get it for you and
            <lb/>let him charge it.  I will send him a 
            <lb/>note by Bill and he can get it and have it
            <lb/>sent to his store have him get it over
            <lb/>the River &amp; all.
          </p>
          <p>
            <lb/>I have no news to write about but to
            <lb/>say your letter the first one came yesterday
            <lb/>and I was pleased to hear from you
            <lb/>give my love to all the little ones
            <lb/>and Kiss them for me
          </p>
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Ever your affectionate Husband</salute>
            <lb/>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <postscript>
           <p><lb/>P.S.
              <lb/>I am interupted all the time or
              <lb/>I would write more
              <lb/>good bye for a while
           </p>
              <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B. Anderson</expan><abbr type="initials">WBA</abbr></choice></persName></signed>
          </postscript>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18630705" n="18630705">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>W.B. Anderson During The Burning of Lebanon During the Cival War</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>In this letter W.B. Anderson gives us a description of the difficulty he has unloading
                a shipment because of the civil war. More importantly though Anderson gives us an insight
                in this letter to the burning of Lebanon during the civil war, from the stand point of
                a civilian in public enterprise during this time. Some of the impact that we are given 
                insight to includes the organization of local troops and how it is holding back Anderson 
                and his shipment.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>This three page long letter written by W.B. Anderson on July fifth 1863 is written with a 
                brown/black ink on a loose piece of off-white, blue lined paper, approximately 7.5inches 
                wide by 10 inches long. The letter in its current state is appears as if it was folded twice
                vertically and once horizontally. The document was written front and back on 2 sheets of 
                paper for a total of 3 pages in length. The page also contains a printer’s mark in the upper
                right hand corner of the page which is now indistinguishable. This printer’s mark closely 
                resembles other printers marks found on several of Anderson’s letters including the letter 
                of 27 June 1862 and the letter of 1 July 1863. On these other letters you can more clearly 
                read "MT HOLLY PAPER CO."</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18630705_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter17_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName><date when="1862-07-05"></date> Sunday Afternoon</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>Dear<rs facs="#MLA">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>I take my pen to let you know
            <lb/> that I am well.  we  arrived here on Friday
            <lb/>Morning and had to go over to the other side
            <lb/>of the river and about a mile up <placeName ref="#licking">Licking</placeName>
            <lb/>to put out our Metal and had a terrible 
            <lb/>time getting unloaded the Irish in this town
            <lb/>are all on a rioting spree and wont work
            <lb/>nor let any body else work we made a
            <lb/>Contract with a party to put our load off
            <lb/>for 15 <choice><expan>cents</expan><abbr>cts</abbr></choice> per ton and when we got to the
            <lb/>place to unload refused to work and then
            <lb/>all our Deck hands but 2 quit and would
            <lb/>not work so we sent over to <placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName>. for more
            <lb/>men and the Irish would not let them
            <lb/>cross on the ferry Boat so we had a good time
            <lb/>to get our load out but finally succeeded
            <lb/>and got back out of <placeName ref="#licking">Licking</placeName> and to the
            <lb/>Wharf here about 10 Oclock at night and
            <lb/>yesterday took all the <choice><expan>freight</expan><abbr>Frt.</abbr></choice> we could get for
            <lb/><placeName ref="#PittsburghPA">Pitt</placeName> and will I think by tomorrow Evening
            <lb/>have a load we have now on and insight
            <lb/>half enough.  but the devil has broke loose
            <lb/>over in <placeName>Kentucky</placeName> again last night the <rs>Mayor</rs>
            <lb/>Received a dispatch to send all the Forces
          </p>
          
          
          <!-- Page 2 -->
          <pb facs="Letter17_pg2"/>
          <p>
            <lb/>that could be got over to go out to <placeName ref="#lexington">Lexington</placeName>
            <lb/>as <persName ref="#Morgan">Morgan</persName> and 3000 men had Burned down
            <lb/> <placeName ref="#lebanon">Lebanon</placeName>and were likely to take <placeName ref="#lexington">Lexington</placeName>
            <lb/>and the city was all one uproar last
            <lb/>night and to day the <rs ref="#hatch">Mayor</rs> then ordered
            <lb/>all the Police 200 in number to start at
            <lb/>2 Oclock with as many more citizens as
            <lb/>can be procured to go out on a special train
            <lb/>I was up to a meeting on the public square
            <lb/>on 5th street and could not get to hear one
            <lb/>word in ten that was spoken while I was
            <lb/>there there was a dispatch arrived to <unclear>Morgan
            <lb/>Hatch</unclear> to send our men and arms to save
            <lb/>the city as <placeName ref="#lexington">Lexington<placeName/> was in <choice><corr>imminent</corr><sic>iminent</sic></choice> danger
            <lb/>as for <placeName ref="#LouisvilleKY">Louisville</placeName> they had enough to do
            <lb/> to take care of it them selves and <placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName>.
            <lb/>Must save <placeName ref="#lexington">Lexington</placeName>  I think I never saw
            <lb/>as wild a people as all in <placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName>. are today
            <lb/>I don’t think that the danger is as great
            <lb/>as is anticipated  I think that all this is
            <lb/>done to get recruits and then they will march
            <lb/>them on to <placeName ref="#richmond">Richmond</placeName> but be it as it may if
            <lb/>they played the very mischief with business in
            <lb/>the city for a few days.  I was down to see the
            <lb/>old Lady to day and <persName>Ella</persName> came up with me
            <lb/>and is on the Boat now and is well the old
            <lb/>lady is well I have some Pears the <rs ref="#MAF">old lady</rs> 
            <lb/>sent you.  I will take <persName>Ella</persName> and put her
          </placeName>
          <pb facs="Letter17_pg3"/>            
            <lb/>on the street cars and send her down home and
            <lb/>Mail this if nothing more happens than I know
            <lb/>if at this time  we will be up about Friday
            <lb/>or Saturday our trip will not be as good
            <lb/>as the last on account of our down trip
            <lb/>being so poor  tell <persName>Mary <choice><corr>"McNamee"</corr><sic>McName</sic></choice></persName> that <name>Wm</name>
            <lb/>is now on the boat on a visit and is well
            <lb/>I will buy a Half Barrel of white sugar and
            <lb/> <del type="unrecoverable" rend="overwritten" hand="WBA"></del>put off as we go up <choice><corr>if</corr><sic>is</sic></choice> I can get it right
            <lb/>everything is high and money scarce gold and
            <lb/>Silver is from 10 to 15 per <choice><expan>cent</expan><abbr>ct</abbr></choice> better than paper
            <lb/>money here  I will go up on 5th st tomorrow
            <lb/> and see <persName> Sue <choice><corr>Whitaker</corr><sic>Whitake</sic></choice></persName> as I have to pass where
            <lb/>she is on my way to the Lead factory on 9th
            <lb/> <choice><expan>street</expan><abbr>st</abbr></choice>  I have engaged 60 tons of Lead and but
            <lb/>about half of it is down yet &amp; I have to see the
            <lb/>shipper tomorrow to let him know definitely about
            <lb/>our time of leaving I will stop as I have no
            <lb/>more news to write about<lb/>
          </p>
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Your affectionate husband</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B.</expan><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
        </div>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18630718" n="18630718">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 18 July 1863</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Anderson shares with his wife the status of his crew and currently what cargo he is carrying, though he does
                not share with her his destination, he promises to write to her from either Evansville or Nashville. He also tells
                her that he has prepared the finances and taxes for Russell and for her to get any sugar she would like from him.
                He asks her to kiss his children for him and wishes them well while he is gone. He also apologizes for mistakes
                in spelling and other errors.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>William B. Anderson's letter dated June 18, 1863 from Cincinnati and
                addressed to his wife Louisa is written in ink on one side of a 
                loose sheet of paper measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches 
                tall (19 x 23 cm).
                The left edge of the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges 
                are clean, suggesting that the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. 
                It appears originally to have been folded once crosswise and twice lengthwise. 
                At this writing, the ink appears brown and the paper off-white (cream). A .5-inch
                by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed printer's mark appears in the upper lefthand 
                corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inches 
                (0.6 cm) from the left edge. There is no image, only the text "OWEN &amp; HURLEBUT So Lee MASS."
                (see illustrations).</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18630718_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter14_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName> <date when="1863-07-18"></date>July 18/63</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear<rs ref="#MLA">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>We are on the eve of
            <lb/>leaving for <placeName ref="#nashville">Nashville</placeName> “prospects good”
            <lb/>I have not read any letter from you since
            <lb/>I wrote and am disappointed! <persName>Ella</persName> was here
            <lb/>yesterday &amp; today <rs ref="#MAF">your mother</rs> is well as
            <lb/>usual <persName>Elias</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="Elias"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="Elias">Unidentified but often mentioned.</note> is sick and I could not leave
            <lb/>the boat long enough to see your mother
            <lb/>Our Cargo Consists of Sutlers goods<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="sutlers"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="sutlers">Sutlers goods were 
              the everyday necessities such as food and tools made available to the soldiers in the war.<bibl>Dictionary</bibl>.</note> and              
            <lb/>as they are in so many small <choice><expan>packages</expan><abbr>pkgs</abbr></choice> it
            <lb/>Kept <persName>Joe</persName> &amp; I both <choice><corr>busily</corr><sic>bussily</sic></choice> engaged all the
            <lb/>time on the wharf till late at night
            <lb/>we have no Passengers but are full of <choice><expan>Freight</expan><abbr>Frt</abbr></choice>
            <lb/>&amp; if we are successful will make a good
            <lb/>trip. I have been very well &amp; all on
            <lb/>board are well except <persName>Elias</persName> I got <persName>Dr Dave
            <lb/>Indkins</persName> to See him and I think he will get well
            <lb/>the water appears to <choice><corr>disagree</corr><sic>dissagree</sic></choice> with him
            <lb/>I think he is mending now I will
            <lb/>write you from <placeName ref="#evansville">Evansville</placeName> or <placeName ref="#nashville">Nashville</placeName>
            <lb/>again Kiss all the <rs>children</rs> and tell them
            <lb/>to be good I wrote to <persName ref="#russell">Russell</persName><seg><note target="n8">8</note></seg> to day
            <lb/>&amp; Sent him a statement of My income
            <lb/>Tax to Pay it?  I am in a great hurry
            <lb/>and have not time to write long
            <lb/>get what sugar you want from <persName ref="#russell">Russell</persName>
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Ever your affectionate Husband</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B.</expan><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
          <postscript>
            <p>
              <lb/>PS Excuse all Errors Write often
            </p>
          </postscript>
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18630731" n="18630731">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from riverboat captain William B. Anderson to his wife at home in Pittsburgh, dated July 31, 1863, from Cincinnati.</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Anderson informs his wife that the sickly Elias will bring her some money when he
                returns to Pittsburgh. Anderson then describes his current employment transporting
                goods for the government. He hopes to make enough money over the summer so that he
                can stay at home for the winter. While apologizing for an apparent scarcity of
                letters, Anderson claims that he has written frequently, and speculates that the
                Morgan raid may have interfered with mail delivery.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>William B. Anderson's letter dated July 31, 1863, from Cincinnati and
                addressed to his wife Mary Louisa is written in dark ink on both sides of a 
                loose sheet of paper measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 10.0 inches 
                tall (19.5 x 25 cm) and ruled with horizontal blue lines spaced .33 inches 
                (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) unruled top margin on the front 
                of the sheet and a 0.9-inch (2 cm) unruled top margin on the back of the sheet. 
                The left edge of the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges 
                are straight, suggesting that the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. 
                It appears to have been folded once crosswise and twice lengthwise. 
                At this writing, the ink appears very dark brown and the paper off-white (cream). A .5-inch
                by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed printer's mark appears in the upper lefthand 
                corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inches 
                (0.6 cm) from the left edge. Although the mark is hard to see, its shape 
                closely matches that of a distinct, similarly sized and positioned printer's 
                mark on a letter dated July 1, 1863, which reads "MT HOLLY PAPER CO." 
                (see illustrations), so it is likely this letter was of the same paper supply.  
                The Ohio State University Library's Rare Books and Manuscripts Library
                is currently inaccessible due to its relocation in preparation for renovation, so
                no further information about the original letter is currently available.</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18630731_lett">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter15_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName><date when="1863-07-31"> Friday July 31st 1863</date><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName></dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My <choice><expan>Dear</expan><abbr>Dr</abbr></choice><rs ref="#MLA">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/> Your of 26 came in due time &amp; I
            <lb/> was pleased to hear from you &amp; hope you &amp; all the
            <lb/> little ones are well<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="typhoid"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="typhoid">According 
              to information from Anderson descendent Jamie Danker, at the time of this letter the Andersons had four young children: William Y. 
              (Young?), age seven or eight; Anna Margaret, age six; John L., age four; and Robert Edward, 
              age two.  A fifth child, Harry C., would be born in January 1865.  Tragically, William Y., 
              Robert Edward, and Harry C. would all die of typhoid fever in 1890 (Robert Edward and Harry C. just a day 
              apart), while Anna Margaret and John L. survived the disease that year.  
              In a 2005 report, the Water Science and Technology Board states that Pittsburgh had the highest 
              national typhoid death rate for large cities in the years 1873-1907; before the establishment of an 
              effective water filtration system in 1907, the city drew its drinking water directly from the polluted 
              Allegheny River.<bibl>Danker; <title level="m">Regional Cooperation</title>, 36–37.</bibl></note> I send with <persName ref="#Elias">Elias</persName><note target="note004">4</note> 60$ <choice><expan>dollars</expan><abbr>Dolls</abbr></choice>
            <lb/> as he is going home to stop off till his health
            <lb/> gets better I will see your <rs ref="#MAF">Mother</rs> this
            <lb/> Evening I have been very <choice><corr>busily</corr><sic>buissily</sic></choice> engaged
            <lb/> all day &amp; have not had one moment to
            <lb/> myself I &amp; the boat are pressed in <choice><expan>government</expan><abbr>Gov.</abbr></choice>
            <lb/> service or rather chartered at 150$ one
            <lb/> hundred &amp; Fifty <choice><expan>Dollars</expan><abbr>Dolls</abbr></choice> per day &amp; our fuel
            <lb/> furnished which is as good or better than
            <lb/> I could do out of the service our trip
            <lb/> around was rather poor having only
            <lb/> picked <del type="recoverable" rend="overstrike">put</del> but little by the way we
            <lb/> have made in all since the boat came
            <lb/> out six thousand clear cash though that
            <lb/> is not bad in less than two months I hope
            <lb/> to be able to make enough by the setting in
            <lb/> of winter to remain at home &amp; enjoy the com<seg type="softhyphen">
              <lb/></seg>forts of our own fireside though things change often
            <lb/> I had almost despaired when we arrived here and
            <lb/> all of a sudden I happened to strike a <choice><corr>lucky</corr><sic>luckey</sic></choice>
            <lb/> lick &amp; get wind of this <choice><corr>operation</corr><sic>opperation</sic></choice> that I now
            <lb/> am engaged in we will leave tomorrow
            <pb facs="Letter15_pg2"/>
            <lb/> Evening for <placeName ref="#nashville">Nashville</placeName> with 220 Mules and
            <lb/> about 40 tons of soldier clothing &amp; 40 tons of oats
            <lb/> It will take us probably 15 to twenty days to
            <lb/> make the trip &amp; by that time we shall probably
            <lb/> hear of orders to go some place else or it may
            <lb/> be that we shall not be permitted to come
            <lb/> back here again as we are at the Command
            <lb/> of the Military authorities though one thing certain
            <lb/> we are not at our own risk if the boat is
            <lb/> lost we hold the Government for it and the
            <lb/> way it was before if she was lost it would
            <lb/> have been our own risk.  I am astonished
            <lb/> to hear of you not receiving more letters
            <lb/> from me for I have written to you very
            <lb/> often 2 the last time I was here and one from
            <lb/> <placeName ref="#nashville">Nashville</placeName> and so on all the time I am sure
            <lb/> I have written at the very least 2 letters per
            <lb/> week Ever since I left home I hope you
            <lb/> will get them more regularly as I have
            <lb/> written &amp; do still intend writing but there
            <lb/> has been so much trouble about the mails
            <lb/> on account of the <persName ref="#Morgan">Morgan</persName> raid that I suppose
            <lb/> may account for failure of the mails
            <lb/> I have but little news to write about
            <lb/> Kiss all the little ones for me &amp; tell them to
            <lb/> be good till I come good by till tomorrow I
            <lb/> will drop you a line before we leave
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute><!-- From salute --></salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><abbr type="initials">WBA</abbr></choice></persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18630801" n="18630801">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>W. B. Anderson Letter--8/1/1863--A busy moment for family and business.</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Anderson shoots off a short letter announcing a dinner with his wife's mother and Ella 
                (as yet an unknown relative or friend mentioned in several of Anderson's letters). 
                He suggests that the boat (Glide II) will leave that afternoon from Cincinnati for Nashville with 200 mules 
                aboard. He sends by Adams Express $3600 for business-related expenses (Adams Express was a very profitable 
                delivery company started in the 1850s and had parallel systems of delivery in the south during the war (Pixley, 2002).
                and reminds his wife that he sent $60 for family expenses with the previous letter.</p>
              <p>In this one-page, hurried letter to his wife--which followed  a longer letter just the day  
                before--Anderson suggests many things about the times and activities on the riverboat. He mentions the transport of 
                animals (200 mules) along with personal commitments: Anderson met
                his wife's mother and Ella (an unknown relative or friend) on the boat (Glide II) and was about to leave for dinner. 
                Before the afternoon departure, he was also intent upon sending business funds to his wife and money for family expenses: 
                All this in one page on lined notebook paper with little punctuation and a postscript anticipating 
                a subsequent letter from Nashville.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>one page on lined notebook paper </p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18630801_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter16_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName><date when="1863-08-01">Aug 1st 1863</date></dateline>
            <lb/><salute>Dear<rs type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/> As we leave this Evening
            <lb/> I <choice><corr>thought</corr><sic>thot</sic></choice> I would drop you a line
            <lb/> to let you know that I have seen 
            <lb/> your <rs ref="#MAF">mother</rs> she &amp; <persName ref="#ella">Ella</persName> 
              are on the <name type="ship" ref="#glide">Boat</name>
            <lb/> now &amp; have been for an hour I have
            <lb/> to go up <rs ref="#CincinnatiOH">town</rs> and they are waiting till 
            <lb/> I get ready we are to have 200 mules
            <lb/> down after dinner &amp; shall get out by
            <lb/> 4 or 5 oclock I have no news to 
            <lb/> write about I send by Adams Express<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="adamsex"/><note resp="ed" xml:id="adamsex">During the Civil War,he 
              Adams Express Company shipped goods to and from Union troops.<bibl>Adams Express Company Journal</bibl>.</note>
            <lb/> to <placeName ref="#PittsburghPA">Pitt</placeName> today 
            (3600.<del type="unrecoverable" rend="overstrike" hand="WBA">[deleted numbers]</del> Three thousand six hundred
                <lb/> <choice><expan>Dollars</expan><abbr>Dolls</abbr></choice> to pay our 1st notes give my respects 
            <lb/> to all I am in a hurry and have not
            <lb/> time write or think of any thing that
            <lb/> will interest you give my respects to 
            <lb/> all I sent a letter last night by <persName ref="#Elias">Elias</persName> 
            <lb/> and $60.00 in cash for you Kiss all the small 
            <lb/> ones for me good bye
          </p>
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Yours affectionately</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B.</expan><abbr>WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
          <postscript>
           <p>
             <lb/>P.S. I will write from <placeName ref="#nashville">Nashville</placeName>
             <lb/>again 
             <lb/><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B. Anderson</expan><abbr type="initials">WBA</abbr></choice></persName> 
           </p> 
          </postscript>
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18640810" n="18640810">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 10 August 1864.</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Summary here!</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>CHECK! William B. Anderson's letter dated June 27, 1862 from Pittsburgh and
                addressed to his wife Louisa is written in ink on one side of a 
                loose sheet of paper measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches 
                tall (19 x 23 cm) and ruled with horizontal blue lines spaced .33 inches 
                (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) unruled top margin. 
                The left edge of the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges 
                are clean, suggesting that the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. 
                It appears originally to have been folded once crosswise and twice lengthwise. 
                At this writing, the ink appears brown and the paper off-white (cream). A .5-inch
                by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed printer's mark appears in the upper lefthand 
                corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inches 
                (0.6 cm) from the left edge. Although the mark is indistinct, its shape 
                closely matches that of a distinct, similarly sized and positioned printer's 
                mark on a letter dated July 1, 1863, which reads "MT HOLLY PAPER CO." 
                (see illustrations). Texture? Stiffness? Watermarks? I will have to visit 
                the RBML.</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18640810_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter21_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName> <date when="1864-08-10">Aug 10 /64</date></dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear<rs ref="#MLA">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>We arrived here on Monday 
            <lb/>at 3 P.M. we had but Little trouble in 
            <lb/>getting down but Picked up nothing we 
            <lb/>were <choice><corr>detained</corr><sic>detaned</sic></choice> by the Navy department 
            <lb/>with a view of making a Gun Boat 
            <lb/>of us until this morning &amp; then 
            <lb/>rejected on <unclear>ap</unclear> of me not agreeing 
            <lb/>with them on terms &amp;c. now I have 
            <lb/>no alternative but to take a load to 
            <lb/>Louisville at low prices &amp; then am 
            <lb/>required to report to the commissary 
            <lb/>department &amp; expect to be sent to 
            <lb/>Tennesee River though have a hope 
            <lb/>of getting to come back to Cin on 
            <lb/>my own account if we are sent 
            <lb/>below I will write from <placeName ref="#LouisvilleKY"><choice><corr>Louisville</corr><sic>Louisvill</sic></choice></placeName> 
            <lb/>if not will write from here on my 
            <lb/>return I am well though very much 
            <lb/>out of heart not from any defects in 
            <lb/>the boat for she does well in every 
            <lb/>respect I would have written before 
            <lb/>now but wanted to wait till I knew 
            <lb/>our destination. I have not heard 
            <lb/>of the old Lady yet. 
          </p>
          
          <pb facs="Letter21_pg2"/>
          
          <p>  
            <lb/>It has been excessively hot ever since 
            <lb/>I left home and the mosquitoes are 
            <lb/>very bad I have not had any offer 
            <lb/>to sell the boat I will sell if any 
            <lb/>good Chance offers. I stopped at <corr>Gallipolis</corr><sic>Gall<seg type="softhyphen">
              <lb/>=</seg>ipoli</sic> on our downward trip and proposed 
            <lb/>to put her in the <placeName ref="#gallipolis"><choice><corr>Gallipolis</corr><sic>Gallipols</sic></choice></placeName> &amp; Pitt trade 
            <lb/>in the fall &amp; got the promise of all 
            <lb/>the patronage there which will be I 
            <lb/>think what I will do if I don’t sell 
            <lb/>I hope to hear from you on my return 
            <lb/>here.  I have nothing of intrest to write 
            <lb/>about we will leave here tomorrow 
            <lb/>try &amp; take good care of yourself and 
            <lb/>the children &amp; get a girl as soon as 
            <lb/>you can for I know you need one 
            <lb/>I will close for my mind is not in 
            <lb/>tune to write long so good night 
            <lb/>for a while. 
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>affectionately your <rs ref="#WBA">Husband</rs></salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B.</expan><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
          <postscript>
            <p>
              <lb/>5.P.M.
              <lb/>P.S. Since writing the above Capt Good
              <lb/>orders me out this <choice><corr>evening</corr><sic>evenig</sic></choice>
              <lb/>Your <persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B. Anderson</expan><abbr type="initials">WBA</abbr></choice></persName>
            </p>
          </postscript>
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>

  <TEI xml:id="WBA_18640814" n="18640814">
    <!-- FIRST COPY THIS TEI ELEMENT!! -->
    <!-- FILL IN THE VALUES ABOVE -->
    <!-- ADD EDITOR'S NAME TO LIST -->
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 14 August 1864.</title>
          <author>Anderson, William B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p><!-- ... --></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <country>USA</country>
              <settlement>Columbus, OH</settlement>
              <repository>Rare Books and Manuscripts, The Ohio State University</repository>
              <collection>William B. Anderson Collection</collection>
              <idno>SPEC.RARE.CMS.0309</idno>
            </msIdentifier>
            <msContents>
              <p>Anderson informs his wife that he has arrived in Louisville, KY. He reports that a canal was closed and tells his wife that he was forced to
                hire men to keep some tobacco safe and slept with it on a subsequent night incase it rained.  Anderson reports the local weather and asks her to send him pictures of their children.
                He also advises her of a new address to send letters to.</p>
            </msContents>
            <physDesc>
              <p>William B. Anderson's letter dated August 14, 1864 from Cincinatti and addressed to
                his wife Louisa is written in ink on two sides of a loose sheet of paper measuring
                approximately 7.5 inches wide by 10 inches tall (19.5 x ? 25cm) and is unruled. The
                left edge of the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges are clean,
                suggesting that the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. It appears
                originally to have been folded once crosswise and twice lengthwise. At this writing,
                the ink appears brown and the paper off-white (cream).</p>
              <accMat></accMat>
            </physDesc>
            <additional>
              <adminInfo>
                <!-- Info from the finding aid -->
                <note></note>
              </adminInfo>
            </additional>
          </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter" xml:id="WBA_18640814_let">
          <!-- REVISE THE VALUES ABOVE -->
          <pb facs="Letter22_pg1"/>
          <!-- MAKE SURE TO REVISE THE FACS VALUE! -->
          <head type="letterhead"></head>
          <figure rend="link">
            <head></head>
            <graphic url=""></graphic>
            <figDesc></figDesc>
          </figure>
          <lb/>
          <opener>
            <lb/><dateline><placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH"><choice><expan>Cincinnati</expan><abbr>Cin</abbr></choice></placeName> <date when="1864-08-14"></date>Sunday Aug 14 /64</dateline>
            <lb/><salute>My Dear<rs type="recipient">Wife</rs></salute>
          </opener>
          <p>
            <lb/>Yours of <date when="1864-08-09">9th</date> Came safe to hand
            <lb/>I was pleased to hear from you.  We arrived
            <lb/>from <placeName ref="#LouisvilleKY">Louisville</placeName> on Friday Evening made a
            <lb/>quick trip but very little Money when we got
            <lb/>to <placeName ref="#LouisvilleKY">Louisville</placeName> the Canal was closed to repare
            <lb/>and we came back with but  1/4 of a load
            <lb/>on account of the R Road here having Teleg<seg type="softhyphen">
              <lb/>=</seg>raphed down to not ship up any more Frt
            <lb/>as they were blocked full of Frt &amp; could not
            <lb/>take it in the Depots consequently could not
            <lb/>take it off the wharf  I put our Tobacco off
            <lb/>Yesterday &amp; Last night had to hire men &amp;
            <lb/>put it onboard the Boat today to Keep it safe
            <lb/>for fear of rain now I have to lay here with it in
            <lb/>the Boat till Tuesday &amp; then I am to commence to
            <lb/>load again for <placeName ref="#LouisvilleKY">Louisville</placeName> I have a  little better
            <lb/>prospect than before.  I left you that <placeName ref="#PittsburghPA"><choice><expan>Pittsburgh</expan><abbr>Pittsbg</abbr></choice></placeName>
            <lb/>Money &amp; put it in that Big Pocket Book I Took
            <lb/>the Gov money &amp; Pd <persName>Mr Hamilton</persName> the 168$ to pay
            <lb/>the Taxes with. I have not seen the <rs ref="#MAF">Old Lady</rs>
            <lb/>yet it has been Excessively hot today &amp; has rained
            <lb/>a little &amp; is Cloudy with prospects of rain.  I have 
            <lb/>been Tollerable well since I wrote last.  I have
            <lb/>no news of any importance to write about
            <lb/>I would like you to send me one of Each
            <lb/>of the Likenesses of You &amp; the children to look 
            
            <pb facs="Letter22_pg2" n="2"/>
            
            <lb/>at occasionally   I may go below from
            <lb/><placeName ref="#LouisvilleKY">Louisville</placeName> this trip if the Canal is open
            <lb/>though it is very uncertain
          </p>
          <p>
            <lb/>Direct your letters to me in Care
            <lb/>of <orgName>Harry Davidson and co</orgName>  <placeName ref="#CincinnatiOH">Cincinnati Ohio</placeName>
            <lb/>instead of <orgName>Barker Hart &amp; Cook</orgName> &amp; I will 
            <lb/>get them in the night as well as day
            <lb/>for they keep a man to sleep in the store
            <lb/>Kiss all the little ones and tell them
            <lb/>to be good</p>
          <p> <lb/>let me hear often from you &amp; tell
            <lb/>me how the crops look &amp;c. &amp;c. get
            <lb/>a girl soon as you can &amp; take
            <lb/>care of your own health &amp; that of the
            <lb/>children
          </p> 
          <closer>
            <lb/><salute>Your affectionate Husband</salute>
            <lb/><signed><persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B.</expan><abbr type="initials">WB</abbr></choice> Anderson</persName></signed>
          </closer>
          <!-- If there were a <postscript>, we have a tag for that. -->
          <postscript>
            <p>
              <lb/>P.S.  I will drop you a line again
              <lb/>when I leave here
              <lb/>Yours <persName ref="#WBA"><choice><expan>William B. Anderson</expan><abbr type="initials">WBA</abbr></choice></persName>
            </p>
          </postscript>
        </div>
        <!-- Or an enclosure: <div type="enclosure" xml:id="WBA_18600101enc"></div> -->
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>
  
  <!-- More TEI Documents? -->
</teiCorpus>
