<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/teip4/schema/dtd/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.prose 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.linking 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.figures 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.analysis 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.transcr 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML 'INCLUDE'>

<!-- If necessary, identify the files containing extensions of the TEI DTD
by removing the commenting around the following declarations and
editing the filenames.

<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM 'XXXXXX.ent' >
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM 'XXXXXX.dtd' >

 -->

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-lat1.ent'>
%ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-lat2.ent'>
%ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-num.ent'>
%ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-pub.ent'>
%ISOpub;
<!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED>
<!ATTLIST pb mmid CDATA #IMPLIED>
]>

<TEI.2 id="WBA_18620928">

   
   <teiHeader type="AACR2">
      <!--The type attribute in teiHeader element above indicates that the header provides 
      enough information to create a bibliographic record that complies with the 
      Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules, 2nd ed. (1978; rev. 1988).-->
      
      <fileDesc>
         <!--The  file description tagged <fileDesc>, contains "a full bibliographical description 
         of the computer file itself, from which a user of the text could derive a proper bibliographic 
         citation, or which a librarian or archivist could use in creating a catalogue entry recording 
         its presence within a library or archive" (TEI P4X, ch. 5).-->
         
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from William B Anderson to his wife, Louisa, dated
            September 28, 1862.</title>
           
            
            <editor>Zack Hess</editor>
          
            
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of initial machine-readable transcript: </resp>
               <name type="person">Zachary Hess</name>
               <resp>Creation of digital images: </resp>
               <name type="person">Laura Denning</name>
               <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: </resp>
               <name type="person">Zachary A. Hess</name>
               <!-- Your full name (first middle last). -->
               
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         
         <editionStmt>
            <p>1st Edition.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         
         <extent>ca. 64 kilobytes </extent>
         
         <publicationStmt>
            <!-- one of (address authority availability date distributor idno p pubPlace publisher) -->
            <!-- Use the following for the Valentine Peers papers. Otherwise you can simply
            indicate your own address. -->
            
            <publisher>The Ohio State University Library. <address>
                  <addrLine n="1">Rare Books and Manuscripts Library</addrLine>
                  <addrLine n="2">327 Main Library</addrLine>
                  <addrLine n="3">1858 Neil Avenue Mall</addrLine>
                  <addrLine n="4">Columbus, OH 43210</addrLine>
               </address>
            </publisher>
            
            <pubPlace>Columbus, OH</pubPlace>
            
            <idno type="CallNumber_Box_Folder_Item">XX_XX_XX_XX</idno>
            <!-- The <idno> element is only required for documents with a standard id number
            such as a library call number. The Anderson papers did not have a call number at the
            beginning of our course, but we will check before we finish.-->
            
            <availability>
               <p>The W. B. Anderson Collection is the property of the Rare Books and Manuscripts
                  Library of The Ohio State University Libraries. Any use of the material should
                  acknowledge such ownership.</p>
               <p id="CreativeCommons">
                  <!--Creative Commons License-->
                  <![CDATA[<a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"><img 
                     alt="Creative Commons License" border="0" src="http://creativecommons.org/images/public/somerights20.png"/></a><br/>This work is licensed under a <a 
                        rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/">Creative
                        Commons Attribution-NoDerivs 2.5 License</a>.]]> This license does not transfer 
                  any rights regarding material used in the edition by permission of a third
                  party. <!--/Creative Commons License--><!--
                           <rdf:RDF xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc
                           /elements/1.1/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
                     <Work rdf:about="">
                     <license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/" />
                     <dc:title>William B. Anderson</dc:title>
                     <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
                     <dc:description>This is a letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa,
                           on September 28, 1862.</dc:description>
                     <dc:creator><Agent><dc:title>Zachary Hess</dc:title></Agent></dc:creator>
                     <dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text" />
                     </Work>
                     <License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"><permits
                           rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction"/><permits rdf
                           :resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution"/><requires rdf:resource=
                           "http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice"/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org
                           /cc/Attribution"/></License></rdf:RDF> -->
               </p>
            </availability>
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            <date>2006-06-01</date>
            
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               
               <titleStmt>
                  
                  <title level="u">Anderson</title>
                  <!--The "level" attribute "indicates whether this is the title of an article, book, journal, 
                  series, or unpublished material, indicated as a, b, j, s, or u" (TEI P4X, ch. 5.2.1).
                     Write "no title" if your document has no title. -->
                  
                  <author>William B Anderson</author>
                  <!-- First middle last -->
                  
               </titleStmt>
               
               <extent>2 Pages</extent>
               <!-- The size of your source document, in whatever units are appropriate (usually pages;
               for example, 2 pp.) -->
               
               <publicationStmt>
                  <p>Pulbication statement from the library.</p>
               </publicationStmt>
               
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>This document is letter number 10 from a man named William B. Anderson 
                        that he wrote to his wife, Louisa in September of 1862 from Cincinnati.  In 
                        all, there were 26 letters written to Louisa from 1862 to 1864.  This particular
                        letter is 2 pages long and is written on loose paper measuring approximately
                        7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches tall, lined with blue horizontal lines.  The first page
                        of the letter is in pretty good condition.  However, there are numerous brown stains
                        that could possibly be dirt.  The second page of the letter is in slightly better condition,
                        with only a few smudges.  Both pages seem to have been folded, twice long ways
                        and once shorts ways.  While the ink is black and legible throughout, there are still
                        errors both in spelling and with ink smudges.  The paper William used is a cream 
                        color.</p>
              
                     
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
               
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
         
      </fileDesc>
      
      <encodingDesc>
         <!--The encoding description, tagged <encodingDesc>, describes "the relationship 
         between an electronic text and its source or sources" (TEI P4X, ch. 5).-->
         
         
         
         
         
         
         <projectDesc>
            
            <p><figure rend="embedImg">
               <head>Dateline from MS</head>
               <figDesc>
                  <xref url="https://images.asc.ohio-state.edu/is/image/mediamanager/6/6421e60e-db07-496e-b9e2-13e4e6b888d2.jpg?scale=0.4&amp;rgn=600,120,800,120&amp;fmt=png&amp;layer=1&amp;size=800,120&amp;text=\vertalc\cf1\qc\fs20\%20&amp;pos=-520,-540"></xref>									
               </figDesc>
            </figure></p>
            
           <p>William B. Anderson, in this letter dated September 28, 1862, 
            continues his conversations with his wife Louisa as he has been
            doing since his first letter in June of 1862.  In all, his 26 letters were written
            over a span of 3 years, all of these letters being housed in The Rare Books
            and Manuscripts Library at The Ohio State University.  In this letter, William 
            addresses his wife with the typical things that he has been conversing with her
            in the past few months.  He speaks about the battles occurring during this hard time of the American Civil War.  
              With only one main reference to the war, the rest of his letter 
            addresses domestic problems and affairs as well as economic affairs.  He 
            continues to ask how his wife and children are doing as well as his wife's 
            mother.  This is something that is important to William and shows his dedication
            to his family life.  As far as economic matters, William tell his wife of money that
            is to be made by himself as well as how she should assess and take care of
            certain economic situations at home while he is away.  He ends with his longing
            to come home and join Louisa and the children, and tries to assure her that he
              will be back soon.</p>
            <p>This letter, written in 1862 in the city of Cincinnati (Cin), shows where Anderson
               was based most of the time, as almost
               all of the 26 letters are inscribed with Cincinnati in the dateline.  This letter does not
               have any special notes as far as location.  We know that there is fighting in the area,
               and that he is writing to his wife back home in Pittsburgh. </p>
            <p>This letter continues to show how Anderson longs to be home with his
            wife and children, yet knows that he has no control over it at times.  However, he 
            does seem to want to stay around because he is getting paid very well.  He tells
            Louisa at the end of the letter, "if I can only get what I now get and have health I 
            would like to stay here a good while."  He wants to make as much money as he 
            so that when he goes home finally, he will have enough money to support his 
               wife and kids without worry.  </p>
            <p>It is important to note that, although there do seem to be a few spelling errors
            and text that is difficult to read, William only crosses out one word.  It does not seem 
            as if he is in much of a hurry at this point in the letters.  While we know that he would 
            go on to write 16 more letters after his letter, he may have not known how long he 
            was going to be away from his wife and children.  As stated earlier, he is talking of
            coming home already, so at this point he may be writing as if he will see Louisa 
               very soon.</p>
            <p>While we can look at many factors regarding the actual letters and how they came
            about and are still in good condition in the Ohio State Rare Books and Manuscripts 
             Library in Columbus, Ohio, we must, at some point, take the time to give thanks and
             credit to William B. Anderson himself writing these wonderful letters to his wife and for
             his wife for keeping them.  In <title level="m">Scrolling Forward: Making Sense of 
                Documents in the Digital Age</title>, David M. Levy writes, "(A letter) carries a message 
              from one individual to another; it addresses a highly personal subject; and in its hand-produced
              marks it expresses some of the drama and the pathos of the situation in which it is embedded" 
               (80-81).  William Anderson did not have to write these letters to his wife during the war and
              Louisa did not have to save them and preserve them through time.  They both did their part, 
              however, and people who view these letters today are now a part of their lives and can at least 
              have a glimpse into what it was like to live when they did and how they did.</p>
            
            <p><hi rend="bold">Works Cited</hi></p>
            <p>Levy, David M. <title level="m">Scrolling Forward: Making Sense of Documents in the Digital
               Age</title>. New York: Arcade, 2001.</p>
            
            
 
           
            
         </projectDesc>
         
         <editorialDecl>
            
            <p>Encoding of the Anderson letters emphasizes diplomatic transcription, with supplemental
               information allowing for semi-modernized, corrected, regularized, or expanded views included as 
               the values of attributes associated with various elements. Accordingly, abbreviations, recoverable
               cancelations, punctuation, spelling, underscoring, capitalization, line breaks, and page breaks 
               have all been transcribed or tagged as they appear in the original manuscripts. Regularized
               versions of all names and referring strings have been encoded as the values of "reg"
               attributes. Standard format values for all dates have been encoded in "value" attributes.</p>
            <p>Corrections and emendations in Anderson's hand have been encoded as cancelations and interlinear 
               or marginal additions. In a few cases, omitted text has been supplied by the editors for the sake 
               of clarity and encoded with the TEI &lt;supplied&gt; element.</p>
            <p>The following structural elements of the letters are also encoded: opener (including salutation
               and dateline), body, lines, paragraphs, pages, and closers (including salutation and 
               signature). Notes and postscripts are identified as such.</p>
            <p>The critical apparatus used in particular views of the letters is explained at the bottom of each view.</p>
            <p>To view the project's complete markup guidelines, 
               <xref url="http://people.cohums.ohio-state.edu/ulman1/Anderson_Letters/Markup.htm">click here</xref>.</p>
            <p>At the time of publication (6 June 2006), the XML and XSL files related to this
               edition were stored in an XML publishing system operated by Humanities
               Information Systems (HIS), College of Humanities, The Ohio State University. For
               more information about HIS, see <xref url="http://his.osu.edu/">http://his.osu.edu/</xref>. 
               Most image, audio, and video 
               files linked to, or embedded in, this edition via &lt;figure&gt; elements were 
               stored in the Media Manager system maintained by the Colleges of Arts and 
               Sciences of The Ohio State University. For more information about the Media Manager,
               see <xref url="https://mediamanager.osu.edu/">https://mediamanager.osu.edu/</xref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         
         <refsDecl>
            <p>The XML files that constitute this edition of the William B. Anderson letters
               are named according the letters' dates of composition, using the following naming
               convention: WBA_YYYYMMDD.xml. Dates of composition were determined from
               various sources of evidence: the datelines inscribed in the letters, internal
               evidence in the body of the letters, and perpetual calendars. If the year,
               month, or date on which a letter was written could not be determined, the 
               appropriate part of the filename is rendered with 0s. XSL style
               sheet documents are named with the prefix "WBA" followed by an underscore
               and a descriptive phrase (e.g., "WBA_diplomatic.xsl).</p>
            <p>In general, this edition follows the Text Encoding Initiative's Guidelines
               for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange, XML-compatible edition P4.
               For more information about TEI P4, see <xref url="http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/">http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/</xref>.
               To facilitate embedding or linking to image, audio, and video files, this edition
               supplements the Text Encoding Initiative's DTD by adding a URL attribute to 
               the &lt;xref&gt; element and an MMID (i.e., Media Manager ID) attribute to the 
               &lt;pb&gt; element. The values of the MMID attribute in &lt;pb&gt; elements and
               the file IDs in the URL attribute of &lt;xref&gt; elements that link to, or embed, 
               image, audio, and video files contained in the Media Manager are generated 
               by the Media Manager application.</p>
            
            <!--  TAKE NOTE: This information helps your readers understand the encoded XML document:
               
               •	Explain any revisions to the TEI DTD.
               •	Explain any special naming conventions used in your encoding (for example, the ID
                  attributes of page break elements).
               
                  You can use more than one paragraph (tagged <p> </p>).
            -->
            
         </refsDecl>
         
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         
      </encodingDesc>
      
      <profileDesc>
         <!--The text profile, tagged <profileDesc>, contains "classificatory and contextual information 
         about the text, such as its subject matter, the situation in which it was produced, the 
         individuals described by or participating in producing it, and so forth" (TEI P4X, ch. 5).-->
         
         <creation>
            <date>2006-05-15</date>
         </creation>
         
         <langUsage>
            <!-- Note any languages that appear in your document. -->
            <language id="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         
         <handList>
            <!-- Identify any hands (i.e., individuals' handwriting) that appear in your document. -->
            <hand id="WBA" scribe="Anderson, William B." first="yes"/>
            <hand id="UNK" scribe="Unknown"/>
         </handList>
         
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <!-- Supply a list of keywords for your document. -->
               <term>Anderson, William B. (1822-1897)</term>
               <term>Anderson, Mary Louisa neé Fischgens (1837-1911)</term>
               <term>Ohio -- Cincinnati</term>
               <term></term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         
      </profileDesc>
      
      <revisionDesc>
         
         <!--The revision history, tagged <revisionDesc>, allows "the encoder to provide a history of 
            changes made during the development of the electronic text" (TEI P4X, ch. 5).-->
         
         <!-- Add additional changes at the top of the list. -->
         <change>
            <date>2006-08-13</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Principal Editor</resp>
               <name>H. Lewis Ulman</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Cross-check against independent transcription by Jamie Danker (principal editor evaluated discrepancies).</item>
         </change>
         
         <change>
            <date>2006-08-03</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Principal Editor</resp>
               <name>H. Lewis Ulman</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Spot-check corrections.</item>
         </change>
                 
         <change>
            <date>2006-06-00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <name>Zachary Hess</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Completion of initial TEI-compliant encoding.</item>
         </change>
         
         <!-- Indicate the date on which you completed your XML encoding. -->
         
         <change>
            <date>2006-04-00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <name>Zachary Hess</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Correction of initial transcription.</item>
            
            <!-- Indicate the date on which you completed the correction of the initial transcription. -->
            
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <name>Steve Agricola</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Initial machine-readable transcription.</item>
         </change>
         
      </revisionDesc>
      
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 n="1" type="abstract">
            
            <!-- This template uses divisions to distinguish parts of the front, body, and
            back of the electronic document. You do not have to use divisions. -->
            
            <head>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Letter of September 28, 1862</title>
                  <!-- This title should be the same as the one you supply in fileDesc/titleStmt/title. -->
                  
                  <date>1862-09-28</date>
                  <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                  <!-- "ALS" means "autograph letter signed." -->
                  <extent>2 Pages.</extent>
                  <idno rend="suppress">XXXXXXXXXX</idno>
                  <!-- For the Anderson letters, we will assign ID numbers that reflect the date. -->
               </bibl>               
            </head>
            
            <p>William B Anderson tells his wife how he must take soldiers to Augusta, Kentucky.  Anderson reports that 
               he is doing well and that he is happy to hear that his wife's mother is also doing well.  He wants his wife to take care 
               of herself and the children.  He describes when he thinks he may be home and for his wife to take 
               care of the house and the work that needs to be done.</p>
           
            <p>Previous letter <xref type="prev" url="WBA_18620917">17 September 1862</xref>
               Next letter <xref type="next" url="WBA_18621007"> 07 October 1862</xref></p>
            
            
         </div1>         
      </front>
      
      <body>
         <div1 n="1" type="[Letter]">
            <!--Transcription of the body of the document begins here. If you use the div tag,
            the type attribute should reflect the nature of your document (e.g., "letter"). -->
            
            <head/>
            <!-- Note that the head can be entered as an empty element. Compare to the 
            div element in the front of the document. -->
            
            <pb mmid="/6/6421e60e-db07-496e-b9e2-13e4e6b888d2" n="1"/>
           
            <!-- In order to build links to images of each page, we will use the Media Manager Item ID
            as the value of the "id" attribute of each <pb> element. The "n" attribute should contain
            a sequential page number within the letter (in the case of the Anderson letters, 1, 2, or 3).  -->
            
            <opener>
       <!-- The opener element contains any dateline and salutation appearing at the head of the letter.
       You may omit this element if your document does not contain similar material.
       Note that dates and names are tagged with standard versions in order to improve searching. -->          
               
               <lb n="001"/> <dateline><address><name type="city" reg="Cincinnati, OH">Cin <seg><note
                  target="n1">1</note></seg></name></address>
                  <date value="1862-09-28">Sunday Sept 28/62</date></dateline> 
               
               <lb n="002"/><salute>My Dear<rs type="recipient"> 
                  <rs key="MLA" reg="Anderson, Mary Louisa, née Fischgens (1837-1911)" type="person"
                     >Wife</rs></rs></salute><name type="recipient">
                     <name key="XNM" reg="REGULARIZED NAME" type="person"></name></name>
                  <seg>
                     <note target="n2">2</note>
                  </seg>
               
            </opener>
            
            <p>
        
        <!-- Beginning with the body of the letter, lines in this template have been identified 
               to allow for cross references and numbered to allow for numbered display. IDs must 
               be unique within the document. However, you do not need to report line breaks at all 
               if doing so serves no purpose in your edition. -->
               
               <lb n="003"/> I am ordered to take up 
               <lb n="004"/>a lot of Soldiers to <name type="place" reg="Augusta, KY">Augusta <seg><note
                  target="n3">3</note></seg></name> Ky as the
               <lb n="005"/>Rebels have taken that place and Burned
               <lb n="006"/>it we are to take up a lot of men and 
               <lb n="007"/>land them Below to attract and whip
               <lb n="008"/>the Rebels if they can I will land
               <lb n="009"/>a good piece Below too as I don’t want
               <lb n="010"/>shot.  I will write a full <abbr expan="account">acct</abbr> on our
               <lb n="011"/>return  I have no time to write much now,
               <lb n="012"/><rs type="person" reg="Fischgens, Ann Mary, née Woolslayer">your Mother</rs> <seg><note target="n4">4</note></seg> was here yesterday and is well
               <lb n="013"/> I am well &amp; Hope you and all the children <seg><note target="n5">5
               </note></seg>
               <lb n="014"/>are well take good care of your Health
               <lb n="015"/>and that of the children. I wrote you
               <lb n="016"/>  a long letter a few days ago  I <abbr expan="received">recd.</abbr>
               <lb n="017"/>yours yesterday and am sorry that <name type="person" reg="Anderson, William Y. (18??-????)">Willie</name> <seg><note target="n6">6</note></seg>
               <lb n="018"/>is not well but hope he will soon recover
               <lb n="019"/>  give my respects to all and write
               <lb n="020"/> often and longer  I yesterday learned what
               <lb n="021"/>we are to get for our Boat and my
               <lb n="022"/>Portions is forty Dollars clear each day
               <lb n="023"/>say nothing about it I hope to stay here
               <lb n="024"/>Some time yet  
              
             </p> 
               
           
            
         <!-- Closer begins here, for letters. -->
            
            <closer> 
               <lb n="025"/><salute>Ever Yours truly </salute>
             
               
             <signed>
                  <name reg="Anderson, William B. (1822-1897)" type="person">WB Anderson</name>
             </signed>
            </closer> 

         </div1>
         
         <div1 n="2" type="note">
            <!-- Note how this template provides for a second top-level division, in this
            case a note. If your document does not have a second top-level division, delete
            this <div1> tag and its contents.-->
            
            <head/>
            <opener/>
            
            <p>
               <lb n="026"/>P.S. We got our Coal found us and one
               <lb n="027"/>Hundred &amp; Fifty <sic corr="Dollars">Dolls</sic> per Day for the whole Boat 
               
                <pb mmid="/4/422e8a2e-72c2-40d5-9b01-b62a15b3b4f7" n="2"/>
             
               <lb n="028"/>as we have not got steam up I will
               <lb n="029"/>write on.  in your Letter you said that the
               <lb n="030"/>man was there to assess the Buggy I suppose 
               <lb n="031"/> the calculation is to lay a heavy tax on
               <lb n="032"/> it as we Keep it for our own use all
               <lb n="033"/> right I will get it with interest back out
               <lb n="034"/> of Uncle Sam while I am here if all goes
               <lb n="035"/> well.  I suppose Mr <name type="person">Walsh</name> <seg><note target="n7">7</note></seg> might as well
               <lb n="036"/> Hole what potatoes you <del rend="overstrike" resp="WBA">want</del> <add place="supralinear">dont</add> want
               <lb n="037"/>in the Cellar down in the field where they
               <lb n="038"/>are and secure them by a fence around there  
               <lb n="039"/>and Keep the Cows from there where he pastures
               <lb n="040"/> the Stalks.  You can manage things the best
               <lb n="041"/>way you think till I come I cannot tell
               <lb n="042"/>when I will be back home now but may
               <lb n="043"/>accidentally get home sooner that I look
               <lb n="044"/>for <del rend="overstrike" resp="WBA">I will</del> it has the appearance of rain this
               <lb n="045"/> morning and if water comes to let larger Boats
               <lb n="046"/> run there we are done here and home I will go
               <lb n="047"/>you cannot <sic corr="censure">Sensure</sic> me for being  so indifferent
               <lb n="048"/> as appearing so indifferent about home when
               <lb n="049"/> you know what I am to get for staying away
               <lb n="050"/>if I can only get what I now get and have
               <lb n="051"/>health I would like to stay here a good
               <lb n="052"/>while and then when I go home to stay there
               <lb n="053"/>the <abbr expan="balance">Bal</abbr> of my days I will stop so good
               <lb n="054"/> <sic corr="bye">Bie</sic> write soon and give all the news
               <lb n="055"/>and Kiss the children</p>  
            
            <closer><salute>Yours ever</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name reg="Anderson, William B. (1822-1897)" type="person">WBA</name>
               </signed>
               <lb n="056"/>Excuse all ever as I am in haste
            </closer> 
            
         </div1>
         
         <div1 n="3" type="Envelope">
            <!-- Third top-level division starts here, in this case an envelope division. 
            If your document does not have a third top-level division, delete
            this <div1> tag and its contents. -->
            
            <head/>
            <opener/>
            
            <p>
              
               
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name key="X1X" reg="Regularized Name" type="person"></name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine></addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name key="WRM" reg="Regularized Name" type="place"></name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               

            </p>
            
            <closer/>
            
         </div1>
      </body>
      
      <back>
         <div1 type="Annotations" n="1">
            <!-- Annotations begin here. -->
            
            <head>Notes</head>
            
            <note id="n1">1. Cincinnati is a city in the extreme SW of Ohio. It was incorporated
               as a state in 1819 and is on the Ohio River bordering Kentucky.       <bibl><title level="m">
                  Enclyclopedia.com
               </title></bibl>
               </note>
               
               <note id="n2">2. William Anderson married his wife, Mary Louisa Fischgens in Cincinnati
                  in 1853.  She was born in Pittsburg and had 5 children with William.     <bibl><title level=
                     "m">History
                     of Allegheny County </title></bibl>
                 </note>
               
               <note id="n3">3.  Augusta is a city in Bracken County, Kentucky, along the Ohio River.
                  <bibl><title level="m">Wikipedia.com </title></bibl>
                  
                  
               </note>
               
               <note id="n4">4.  Louisa (Fischgens) Anderson's mother is named Ann (Woolslayer)
                  Fischgens, born in Pittsburgh.   <bibl><title level="m">History
                     of Allegheny County </title></bibl>
                  
                  
                  
                  
          
             </note>
               
               
               <note id="n5">5.  William B. Anderson and his wife Louisa, had 5 children: William Y, Anna 
                  M, John L, Robert, and Harry C.   <bibl><title level="m">History
                     of Allegheny County </title></bibl>
                  
                  
              
               </note>
               
               <note id="n6">6.                
                  While the name Willie is an undetermined person in Anderson's life, it
                  could possibly be short for William Y, who was William's son, born in 1855, and who 
                  could have possibly been sick at the time of this letter.   <bibl><title level="m">History
                     of Allegheny County </title></bibl>      
                  
                  
                  
                  <note id="n7">7.    Walsh is an undetermined person in Anderson's life.         </note>
               
               
               
               
               
               
               
  
               
               <bibl>
                  <title></title></bibl>
            </note>
            
         </div1>
         
         <div1 type="Citations" n="3">
            <!--List of Works Cited begins here-->
            
            <listBibl>
               <head>Works Cited in Notes</head>
               
               <bibl id="HOAC">
                  <title level="m">History of Allegheny county, Pennsylvania: Including its early settlement and 
                     progress to the present time; a description of its historic and interesting localities; 
                     its cities, towns and villages; religious, educational, social and military history; mining, 
                     manufacturing and commercial interests, improvements, resources, statistics, etc.; also, 
                     biographies of many of its representative citizens</title>
                  <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>A. Warner &amp; Co.</publisher>
                  <date>1889</date>
               </bibl> 
               
               <bibl id="Cincinnati">
                  <title level="m">Encyclopedia online artice on the history of Cincinnati</title>
                  <publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
                  <date>2006</date>
                  http://www.enclyclopedia.com/html/C/cincinna.asp
               </bibl>
               
               
               <bibl id="Augusta">
                  <title level="m">Wikipedia article on Augusta, KY</title>
                  <publisher>Wikipedia Foundation, Inc.</publisher>
                  <date>29 May 2006</date>
                  http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augusta,_KY
               </bibl>
             
               
            </listBibl>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
