<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/teip4/schema/dtd/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.prose 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.linking 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.figures 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.analysis 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.transcr 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML 'INCLUDE'>

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-lat1.ent'>
%ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-lat2.ent'>
%ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-num.ent'>
%ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-pub.ent'>
%ISOpub;
<!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED>
<!ATTLIST pb mmid CDATA #IMPLIED>
]>

<TEI.2 id="WBA_18620901">
   
   <teiHeader type="AACR2">
     
      <fileDesc>
         
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Mary Louisa Anderson, on September 1st, 1862 from Cincinnati, Ohio.</title>
        
            <editor>Jenna Marlene Kamrass</editor>
           
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of initial machine-readable transcript: </resp>
               <name type="person">Jenna Marlene Kamrass</name>
               <resp>Creation of digital images: </resp>
               <name type="person">Laura Denning</name>
               <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: </resp>
               <name type="person">Jenna Marlene Kamrass</name>
               
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         
         <editionStmt>
            <p>1st Edition.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         
         <extent>ca. 18 kilobytes </extent>
         
         <publicationStmt>
           
            <publisher>The Ohio State University Library. <address>
                  <addrLine n="1">Rare Books and Manuscripts Library</addrLine>
                  <addrLine n="2">327 Main Library</addrLine>
                  <addrLine n="3">1858 Neil Avenue Mall</addrLine>
                  <addrLine n="4">Columbus, OH 43210</addrLine>
               </address>
            </publisher>
            
            <pubPlace>Columbus, OH</pubPlace>
            
            <idno type="CallNumber_Box_Folder_Item">XX_XX_XX_XX</idno>
            
            <availability>
               <p>The W. B. Anderson Collection is the property of the Rare Books and Manuscripts
                  Library of The Ohio State University Libraries. Any use of the material should
                  acknowledge such ownership.</p>
            </availability>
            
            <date>2006-06-01</date>
            
         </publicationStmt>
         
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               
               <titleStmt>
                  
                  <title level="u">No Title</title>
                 
                  
                  <author>William B. Anderson</author>
                   
               </titleStmt>
               
               <extent>1 pp.</extent>
               
               <publicationStmt>
                  <p>Publication statement from the library.</p>
               </publicationStmt>
               
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>This document is a letter from Captain William B. Anderson (1822-1897), to his wife, 
                        Mary Louisa (Fischgens) Anderson. He wrote this from Cincinnati, on September 1st, 1862.  
                        It is one page long, with no other notes or enclosures. It is written on lined notebook paper, 
                        folded in half lengthwise and into thirds after that.  There is no surviving envelope that goes 
                        with it, and it is approximately eight inches by ten inches in size.  There is a printer's mark 
                        in the upper-left hand corner, in the shape of a shield surrounded by greenery, with a crown on 
                        top.  The left edge of the paper is slightly ragged and worn, as if it had been torn from a
                        composition book or a pad of paper bound on the left.  
                     </p>
                     
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
               
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
         
      </fileDesc>
      
      <encodingDesc>
         
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This very short letter, written by William B. Anderson to his wife, Mary Louisa, in September of 1862,
               is the 1862 edition of what we do on cell phones or by e-mail every day: discussing his day to day life, 
               even when it seems mundane.  It addresses his happiness at the way business is going at the time of the 
               letter, his concern at the way matters at home are going, and the various challenges that a riverboat 
               captain on the Ohio River in the Civil War era might face.  His spelling is less than perfect, and his
               grammar might leave much to be desired&mdash;much like the email or phone conversations that we might 
               have with our distant relatives in 2006.</p>
            <p>This letter resembles the other letters from William to Louisa that are in the collection in The 
               Ohio State University Rare Books and Manuscripts Library.  It was written in Cincinnati, one of the 
               many thriving ports that Anderson visited on the Ohio River, as were all but two of the letters in 
               the collection.  The issues in the letter, which included family life, business, and day to day discussion,
               are common themes throughout the collection. His poor grammar and spelling are also regular occurrences,
               and in some of the letters, Anderson frequently apologizes for the mistakes that occur because of the 
               speed with which he had to write.  These are some of the threads that tie the entire collection together.</p>
            <p>However, this letter stands out from the others for a variety of reasons.  In many of the other letters 
               in the collection, Anderson's cross&ndash;outs and spelling mistakes are numerous.  In this particular letter, there
               are only a few glaring mistakes: the word "chute" is spelled "Shute" and
               the word "business" has an extra 's'.  In addition, in this particular letter, business is actually going
               quite well, whereas in most of the letters, it is not.  Anderson even references the bad business in
               the last few lines of the letter.</p>
            <p>Though this letter is an example of correspondence in an earlier time, it is interesting to note the
               similarities to our correspondence today.  Obviously, there was not instant communication in 1862, but 
               the topics of conversation were not so different from our own.  Hopefully, this collection will be a link
               to the past, but also, a reminder that things might not have changed so very much, after all.</p>
            
            
      </projectDesc>
         
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>In this collection, the Anderson letters are transcribed diplomatically, meaning that
               the words on the page are what is described.  Abbreivations, misspellings, capitalization,
               punctuation, and all other elements found in these letters appear exactly as they do in the
               original collection.  All names and places are encoded with a "value" tag, and all dates appear
               in a standard format.</p>
            
            <p>To view the project's complete markup guidelines, 
               <xref url="http://people.cohums.ohio-state.edu/ulman1/Anderson_Letters/Markup.htm">click here</xref>.</p>
            <p>At the time of publication (6 June 2006), the XML and XSL files related to this
               edition were stored in an XML publishing system operated by Humanities
               Information Systems (HIS), College of Humanities, The Ohio State University. For
               more information about HIS, see <xref url="http://his.osu.edu/">http://his.osu.edu/</xref>. 
               The image in this particular transcription is stored in the Media Manager system maintained 
               by the Colleges of Arts and Sciences of The Ohio State University, found here<xref url="https://mediamanager.osu.edu/">https://mediamanager.osu.edu/</xref>.</p>
            
         </editorialDecl>
         
         <refsDecl>
            <p>The XML files that constitute this edition of the William B. Anderson letters
               are named according the letters' dates of composition, using the following naming
               convention: WBA_YYYYMMDD.xml. Dates of composition were determined from
               various sources of evidence: the datelines inscribed in the letters, internal
               evidence in the body of the letters, and perpetual calendars. If the year,
               month, or date on which a letter was written could not be determined, the 
               appropriate part of the filename is rendered with 0s. XSL style
               sheet documents are named with the prefix "WBA" followed by an underscore
               and a descriptive phrase (e.g., "WBA_diplomatic.xsl).</p>
            <p>In general, this edition follows the Text Encoding Initiative's Guidelines
               for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange, XML-compatible edition P4.
               For more information about TEI P4, see <xref url="http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/">http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/</xref>.
               To facilitate embedding or linking to image, audio, and video files, this edition
               supplements the Text Encoding Initiative's DTD by adding a URL attribute to 
               the &lt;xref&gt; element and an MMID (i.e., Media Manager ID) attribute to the 
               &lt;pb&gt; element. The values of the MMID attribute in &lt;pb&gt; elements and
               the file IDs in the URL attribute of &lt;xref&gt; elements that link to, or embed, 
               image, audio, and video files contained in the Media Manager are generated 
               by the Media Manager application.</p>
           
         </refsDecl>
         
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         
      </encodingDesc>
      
      <profileDesc>

         
         <creation>
            <date>2006-07-28</date>
         </creation>
         
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         
         <handList>
            <hand id="WBA" scribe="William B. Anderson"/>
         </handList>
         
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>William B. Anderson</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         
      </profileDesc>
      
      <revisionDesc>
        
         <change>
            <date>2006-08-11</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Principal Editor</resp>
               <name>H. Lewis Ulman</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Cross-check against independent transcription by Jamie Danker (principal editor evaluated discrepancies).</item>
         </change>
         
         <change>
            <date>2006-08-08</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Principal Editor</resp>
               <name>H. Lewis Ulman</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Spot-check corrections.</item>
         </change>
         
         <change>
            <date>2006-07-28</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <name>Jenna Kamrass</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Completion of initial TEI-compliant encoding.</item>
         </change>
         
         <change>
            <date>2006-04-16</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <name>Jenna Kamrass</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Correction of initial transcription.</item>
            
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <name>Steve Agricola</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Initial machine-readable transcription.</item>
         </change>
         
      </revisionDesc>
      
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 n="1" type="abstract">
    
            
            
      <head>
         <bibl>
            <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Mary Louisa Anderson, on September 1st, 1862 from Cincinnati, Ohio</title>
                  
            <date>1862-09-01</date>
               <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                  <extent>1 pp.</extent>
                  <idno rend="suppress">18620901</idno>
           </bibl>               
       </head> 
       
            
            <p>In this document, William B. Anderson lists his itinerary and the business conducted at each port of call.  
               He brings oats to Gallipolis, Ohio; retrieves wheat from
               Graham's Station, West Virginia, and brings it to Blennerhasset's Island, West Virginia.  During his travels,
               it was necessary to build a chute and hire oxen in order to bring the wheat to Blennerhasset's Island.  
               In the latter part of the letter, Anderson discusses his hope to sell his boat, as business is stopped 
               now that the previous travels are finished.  He finishes by sending his love to his wife and children.
            </p>
            <p>Previous letter <xref type="prev">[not yet edited]</xref> 
               Next letter <xref type="next" url="WBA_18620917">17 September 1862</xref></p>
         </div1>
         </front>
                 

      
      <body>
         <div1 n="1" type="Letter">
                  <figure rend="embedImg">
                  <head>[Dateline]</head>
                  <figDesc>
                     <xref url="https://images.asc.ohio-state.edu/is/image/mediamanager/5/54bee70e-bdcc-4dd8-ab05-87aeb7b07aa0.jpg?scale=0.5&amp;rgn=825,125,625,100&amp;fmt=png"></xref>
                    
                  </figDesc>
               </figure>
            
            <pb mmid="/5/54bee70e-bdcc-4dd8-ab05-87aeb7b07aa0" n="1"/>

            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <lb n="001"/><date value="1862-09-21">Cin   Sept 1st   1862,</date>
                </dateline>
               
               <lb n="002"/><salute>My Dear <name type="person" reg="Mary Louisa Anderson">Wife<seg><note target="n1">1</note></seg></name> </salute>
               
            </opener>
            
            <p>
               <lb n="003"/>Yours came safe to hand &amp; I was
               <lb n="004"/>glad to hear from you though sorry to hear that
               <lb n="005"/>all was not well but hope that before this all are
               <lb n="006"/>fully recoved.  I have been quite unwell since I left
               <lb n="007"/>here but have got better so took a load of Oats
               <lb n="008"/>for the Government up to <name type="place" reg="Gallipolis, OH">Gallipolis</name><seg><note target="n2">2</note></seg> and from there
               <lb n="009"/>we went up to take our Wheat that we left
               <lb n="010"/>at <name type="place" reg="Grahams Station, WV">Grahams Station</name><seg><note target="n3">3</note></seg> and and succeeded in getting
               <lb n="011"/>up as far as the foot of <name type="place" reg="Blennerhasset's Island, WV">Blennerhassets Island</name><seg><note target="n4">4</note></seg>
               <lb n="012"/>and there we dug a <sic corr="chute">Shute</sic> wide and deep enough
               <lb n="013"/>to draw a flat drawing but 13 inches over and at
               <lb n="014"/>3 lads got our wheat over and then hired a man
               <lb n="015"/>and a team of oxen to haul the flat <sic corr="off">of</sic> and left
               <lb n="016"/>the 2nd clerk there to attend to it  we arrived here
               <lb n="017"/>this morning and will leave at noon for <name type="place" reg="Maysville, KY">Maysville</name><seg><note target="n5">5</note></seg> with a
               <lb n="018"/>load of Mules and then I don’t know what we will
               <lb n="019"/>do though on our return I will write again  I am
               <lb n="020"/>quite busy now but will probably have more <del type="recoverable" hand="WBA" rend="overstrike">time</del>
               <lb n="021"/>to write about when I come back again  I
               <lb n="022"/>may sell the boat I will try to <sic corr="anyhow">any how</sic>
               <lb n="023"/> I hope to be home soon and will most
               <lb n="024"/>likely lay up if I don’t sell things are very
               <lb n="025"/>checkered and all <sic corr="business">bussiness</sic> is stopped give my 
               <lb n="026"/>love to the children and take care of them
               <lb n="027"/>and you		  
          </p>
            
            <closer>
               <salute>Your affectionate husband</salute>
               <lb n="028"/>PS. Write as before
               <signed>
                  <name reg="Anderson, William (1822-1897)" type="person">WB Anderson</name>
               </signed>        
               
            </closer>          

         </div1>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         </body>
         <back>
            <div1 type="Annotations" n="1">
              
               <head>Notes</head>
               
               <note id="n1">1. Mary Louisa Fischgens married William B. Anderson on September 15th, 1853.
                  <bibl>
                     <title>The Anderson Family</title>, 1 
                  </bibl>
               </note>
              
               <note id="n2">2. Gallipolis, Ohio is located in Gallia county, in the southeastern tip of Ohio. 
                  It is a port city on the Ohio River. 
                  <bibl>
                     <title>"Gallipolis, Ohio." Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia.</title>
                  </bibl></note>
               <note id="n3">3. Graham's Station, West Virgina is now known as Bluefield, West Virigina.  
                  It was a port city on the Ohio River.
                  <bibl>
                     <title>"Bluefield, WV."  Wikipedia, the free enclyclopedia.</title>
                  </bibl></note>
               <note id="n4">4. Blennerhasset's Island, West Virginia is an island in the Ohio River, and was originally a slave plantation.
               <bibl>
                  <title>"Blennerhasset Island Historical State Park."</title>
               </bibl></note>
               <note id="n5">5. Maysville, Kentucky is located on the Ohio River, in the northeast corner of the state.
               <bibl>
                  <title>"Maysville, KY." Wikipedia, the free online encyclopedia."</title>
               </bibl></note>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="Citations" n="2">
               
               <listBibl>
                  <head>Works Cited in Notes</head>
                  
                  
                  <bibl id="BISP">
                     <title level="m">Blennerhasset's Island State Park</title>
                     <pubPlace>WWW publication: 
                         <figure rend="link">
                          <figDesc>
                             <xref url="http://www.blennerhassettislandstatepark.com">http://www.blennerhassettislandstatepark.com/</xref>.
                          </figDesc>
                         </figure>
                    </pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Blennerhasset's Island State Park Website</publisher>
                  </bibl>

                  <bibl id="GOW">
                     <title level="m">Gallipolis, Ohio</title>
                     <pubPlace>WWW publication: 
                        <figure rend="link">
                           <figDesc><xref url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gallipolis%2C_Ohio">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gallipolis%2C_Ohio</xref>.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                     </pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Wikipedia, the free online encyclopedia</publisher>
                     <date>May 18, 2006</date>
                  </bibl>
                  
                  <bibl id="HOAC">
                     <title level="m">History of Allegheny county, Pennsylvania: Including its early settlement and 
                     progress to the present time; a description of its historic and interesting localities; 
                     its cities, towns and villages; religious, educational, social and military history; mining, 
                     manufacturing and commercial interests, improvements, resources, statistics, etc.; also, 
                     biographies of many of its representative citizens</title>
                     <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>A. Warner &amp; Co.</publisher>
                     <date>1889</date>
                  </bibl>

                  <bibl id="MKW">
                     <title level="m">Maysville, Kentucky</title>
                     <pubPlace>WWW publication: 
                        <figure rend="link">
                           <figDesc><xref url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maysville%2C_Kentucky">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maysville%2C_Kentucky</xref>.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                     </pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Wikipedia, the free online encyclopedia</publisher>
                     <date>May 18, 2006</date>
                   </bibl>
                  
               </listBibl>
            </div1>
         </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
