<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/teip4/schema/dtd/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.prose 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.linking 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.figures 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.analysis 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.transcr 'INCLUDE'>
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML 'INCLUDE'>

<!-- If necessary, identify the files containing extensions of the TEI DTD
by removing the commenting around the following declarations and
editing the filenames.

<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM 'XXXXXX.ent' >
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM 'XXXXXX.dtd' >

 -->

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-lat1.ent'>
%ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-lat2.ent'>
%ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-num.ent'>
%ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/Entity_Sets/Unicode/iso-pub.ent'>
%ISOpub;

<!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED> 
<!ATTLIST pb mmid CDATA #IMPLIED>]>

<TEI.2 id="WBA_18620627">
   
   <teiHeader type="AACR2">
      <!--The type attribute in teiHeader element above indicates that the header provides 
      enough information to create a bibliographic record that complies with the 
      Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules, 2nd ed. (1978; rev. 1988).-->
      
      <fileDesc>
         <!--The  file description tagged <fileDesc>, contains "a full bibliographical description 
         of the computer file itself, from which a user of the text could derive a proper bibliographic 
         citation, or which a librarian or archivist could use in creating a catalogue entry recording 
         its presence within a library or archive" (TEI P4X, ch. 5).-->
        
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 27 June 1862.</title>
            <editor>H. Lewis Ulman</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable transcript: </resp>
               <name type="person">H. Lewis Ulman</name>
               <resp>Creation of digital scans of manuscript pages: </resp>
               <name type="person">Laura Denning</name>
               <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup: </resp>
               <name type="person">H. Lewis Ulman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         
         <editionStmt>
            <p>1st Edition.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         
         <extent>ca. 64 kilobytes </extent>
         
         <publicationStmt>
            <!-- one of (address authority availability date distributor idno p pubPlace publisher) -->
            
            <publisher>The Ohio State University Library. <address>
                  <addrLine n="1">Rare Books and Manuscripts Library</addrLine>
                  <addrLine n="2">327 Main Library</addrLine>
                  <addrLine n="3">1858 Neil Avenue Mall</addrLine>
                  <addrLine n="4">Columbus, OH 43210</addrLine>
               </address>
            </publisher>
            
            <pubPlace>Columbus, OH</pubPlace>
            
            <availability>
               <p>The William B. Anderson Collection is the property of the Rare Books and Manuscripts
                  Library of The Ohio State University Libraries. Any use of the material should
                  acknowledge such ownership.</p>
               <p id="CreativeCommons">
                  <!--Creative Commons License-->
                 <![CDATA[<a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/">
                     <img alt="Creative Commons License" border="0" src="http://creativecommons.org/images/public/somerights20.png"/></a>
                  <br/>This work is licensed under a 
                  <a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/">
                     Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 2.5 License</a>.]]> This license
                  does not transfer any rights regarding material used in the edition by permission of a
                  third party.&gt;
                  <!--/Creative Commons License-->
                  <!-- <rdf:RDF xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
                     <Work rdf:about="">
                     <license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/" />
                     <dc:title>Edition of Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 27 June 1862</dc:title>
                     <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
                     <dc:description>XML-encoded transcription and annotation of a manuscript letter held in, and owned by, the Rare Books and Manuscripts Library of The Ohio State University.</dc:description>
                     <dc:creator><Agent><dc:title>H. Lewis Ulman</dc:title></Agent></dc:creator>
                     <dc:rights><Agent><dc:title>H. Lewis Ulman</dc:title></Agent></dc:rights>
                     <dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text" />
                     </Work>
                     <License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/">
                     <permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction"/>
                     <permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution"/>
                     <requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice"/>
                     <requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution"/>
                     <prohibits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/CommercialUse"/>
                     <permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks"/>
                     <requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/ShareAlike"/>
                     </License>
                     </rdf:RDF> -->
               </p>
            </availability>
            
            <date>2006</date>
            
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               
               <titleStmt>
                  <title level="u">No title</title>
                  <!--The "level" attribute "indicates whether this is the title of an article, monograph (book), journal, 
                  series, or unpublished material, indicated as a, m, j, s, or u" (TEI P4X, ch. 5.2.1).-->
                  <author>William B. Anderson</author>
               </titleStmt>
               
               <extent>1 p.</extent>
               
               <publicationStmt>
                  <p>Pulbication statement from the library.</p>
               </publicationStmt>
               
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <!-- 
                        Note about the document. The entire header should answer the following
                        questions; add anything here that is not provided elsewhere.
                        1. What is the document (letter, will, etc.)?
                        2. What does it say about itself (titles, descriptive notes,etc.)?
                        3. What does it contain (no. of pages/sheets, enclosures, etc.)?
                        4. How is it put together (folded sheets, binding, etc.)?
                        5. What is it made of (paper, vellum, etc.)?
                        6. How is it packaged/contained (binding, envelope, folder, box, etc.)?
                        7. How is it related to other versions (original, copy, print history)?
                        
                        For an example of how archivists describe paper, 
                        see [http://abacus.bates.edu/Faculty/wmarchive/FORM_descriptions.html].
                     -->
                     <figure rend="embedImg">
                        <head>Letter of 1 July 1863</head>
                        <figDesc>
                           <xref url="https://images.asc.ohio-state.edu/is/image/mediamanager/E/e06062da-d7e0-424c-b850-fdcd54e05aca.jpg?scale=0.5&amp;rgn=80,100,150,160&amp;op_brightness=-50&amp;op_contrast=25&amp;fmt=png"/>
                        </figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     
                     <figure rend="embedImg">
                        <head>Letter of 27 June 1862</head>
                        <figDesc>
                           <xref url="https://images.asc.ohio-state.edu/is/image/mediamanager/C/cc918f45-896e-4226-a419-9261be2361ac.jpg?scale=0.5&amp;rgn=80,120,150,160&amp;op_brightness=-50&amp;op_contrast=25&amp;fmt=png"/>
                        </figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     William B. Anderson's letter dated June 27, 1862 from Pittsburgh and
                     addressed to his wife Louisa is written in ink on one side of a 
                     loose sheet of paper measuring approximately 7.5 inches wide by 9.0 inches 
                     tall (19 x 23 cm) and ruled with horizontal blue lines spaced .33 inches 
                     (0.8 cm) apart, except for a 1.5-inch (3.8 cm) unruled top margin. 
                     The left edge of the sheet is slightly ragged, while the other three edges 
                     are clean, suggesting that the sheet was torn from a notepad or bound notebook. 
                     It appears originally to have been folded once crosswise and twice lengthwise. 
                     At this writing, the ink appears brown and the paper off-white (cream). A .5-inch
                     by .5-inch (1.3 x 1.3 cm) embossed printer's mark appears in the upper lefthand 
                     corner of the sheet, 0.5 inches (1.3 cm) from the top edge and .25 inches 
                     (0.6 cm) from the left edge. Although the mark is indistinct, its shape 
                     closely matches that of a distinct, similarly sized and positioned printer's 
                     mark on a letter dated July 1, 1863, which reads "MT HOLLY PAPER CO." 
                     (see illustrations). Texture? Stiffness? Watermarks? I will have to visit 
                     the RBML.
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
               
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
         
      </fileDesc>
      
      <encodingDesc>
         <!--The encoding description, tagged <encodingDesc>, describes "the relationship 
         between an electronic text and its source or sources" (TEI P4X, ch. 5).-->
         
         <projectDesc>
            <p><figure rend="embedImg">
               <head>Salutation from letter of 27 June 1862</head>
               <figDesc>
                  <xref url="https://images.asc.ohio-state.edu/is/image/mediamanager/C/cc918f45-896e-4226-a419-9261be2361ac.jpg?scale=0.3&amp;rgn=80,189,234,95&amp;fmt=png"/>
               </figDesc>
            </figure>
               In some ways, William B. Anderson's short letter of 27 June 1862 to his wife, Mary Louisa, 
               typifies the twenty-one letters from William to Louisa that survive in the collection of the 
               Rare Books and Manuscripts Library at The Ohio State University. It addresses three of the 
               four broad topics about which he repeatedly writes to his wife during the summers of 1862, 1863, 
               and 1864: managing domestic affairs and sustaining familial bonds when family members are 
               separated for long periods by great distances; the rhetoric and logistics of mid-nineteenth-century 
               correspondence; and the economic, logistical, and physical challenges of the riverboat business, 
               especially on a waterway as critical as the Ohio River in the midst of the American Civil War 
               (in other letters, Anderson also reflects more broadly on the uncertainties, vicissitudes, and 
               suffering faced by civilians and soldiers alike in wartime).</p>
            <p>However, this letter is also unique. All but two of the letters were written from Cincinnati, 
               a thriving center of commerce on the Ohio River approximately halfway between its source at 
               the confluence of the Allegheny and Monongahela Rivers in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania and its confluence 
               with the Mississippi River a mile or so south of Cairo, Illinois. The remaining letter in the collection 
               was written from St. Louis, Missouri&mdash;though Anderson mentions writing from Louisville, Kentucky and 
               Nashville, Tennessee as well. This letter was written from Pittsburgh, William and Louisa's home town. 
               Presumably, he had been visiting his family and had expected to leave Pittsburgh by the Friday in late 
               June when he wrote the letter; he writes to inform his wife of a delay.</p>
            <p>As the collection in general reveals, delays were common, caused variously by negotiations over freight, 
               water levels on the river, mechanical difficulties, and various military complications. 
               Arrangements regarding freight seem to have kept Anderson in Pittsburgh overnight on June 27. 
               He wants to secure a full load before leaving Pittsburgh because he "cannot depend upon getting 
               any freight below here." He takes the opportunity to ask Louisa to send down "the Can of milk and 2 
               jars of lard and my clothes and overcoat." The definite article stands out: <hi rend="italics">the</hi> 
               Can of milk. 
               One wonders whether, in his habitual haste (on which he often blames poor spelling and handwriting), 
               he has simply rushed off and forgotten these items, and Louisa has sent him a note asking what she 
               should do with them. In any case, in his haste to send her instructions, he crosses out the next 
               two lines of his letter and recomposes them. Characteristically, the life of a riverboat captain 
               seems frenetic.</p>
            <p>It is also worth noting that he arranges to convey a note to his wife via "some one on the Shore at 
               Shousetown." While the Andersons clearly handled much of their correspondence through the U.S. 
               mail (he mentions post offices several times, and the collection includes one stamped envelope), 
               they often convey both messages and goods through intermediaries traveling by rail or river.</p>
            <p>Anderson's closing request constitutes something of a refrain in the letters. He asks Louisa to call 
               on a Mr. Russell (probably John Russell, a local merchant) in order to collect money owed him, 
               noting that he must meet his obligations on the crew's upcoming payday. Aside from suggesting that 
               riverboat captains had to watch their cash flow carefully, this request reminds us that Louisa played 
               a key role not only in caring for the Anderson household, including their four children (a fifth would 
               be born in 1865), but also in tending to their business interests. Though we have only William 
               Anderson's side of the correspondence, the letters reveal many details of Louisa's everyday life as well.</p>
            <p>It is Louisa, presumably, whom we have to thank for initially preserving the letters, probably for 
               the very common, personal reasons to which David Levy alludes in <title level="m">Scrolling Forward: Making Sense of 
               Documents in the Digital Age</title>: "In the privacy of our own homes we are likely to hold on to any number 
               of treasures: cards, letters, and notes written long ago, photographs, scrapbooks filled with mementoes 
               from an earlier era. We can't throw them out, even if we can't say why. We may look at them rarely or 
               not at all, yet still it is somehow comforting to know they are there. It's as if something of 
               importance is embedded in their very substance. This has less to do with their information content 
               per se than with the emotions they evoke and the personal relationships they signify and embody" (96–97). 
               The Rare Books and Manuscripts Library at The Ohio State University purchased the letters in part 
               because they fit into a larger goal of acquiring materials that reveal the "common man's view of great 
               events," and war letters are one focus of that larger effort (Smith). The collection as a whole, and 
               the letter of 27 June 1862 more specifically, should also prove interesting to business historians and 
               students of letter writing in American culture (Hewitt). The passing of time has made the everyday 
               information in the letters newly valuable, though the letters also retain the power Levy speaks of to 
               evoke the emotional fabric of everyday life, especially when it becomes frayed in the course of great 
               events.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Works Cited</hi></p>
            <p>Hewitt, Elizabeth. Lecture to English 569C, Digital Media and English Studies. The Ohio State University. 
               6 Apr. 2006.</p>
            <p>Levy, David M. <title level="m">Scrolling Forward: Making Sense of Documents in the Digital
               Age</title>. New York: Arcade, 2001.</p>
            <p>Smith, Geoffrey. Lecture to English 569C, Digital Media and English Studies. 
               Rare Books and Manuscripts Library, The Ohio State University. 30 Mar. 2006.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         
         <editorialDecl>
            <!--In addition to prose description, the Editorial Practices Declaration may contain 
            specialized elements concerned with correction, normalization, quotation, hyphenation, 
            segmentation, date and number format, and interpretive apparatus (TEI P4X, ch. 5.3.3).-->
            <p>Encoding of the Anderson letters emphasizes diplomatic transcription, with supplemental
               information allowing for semi-modernized, corrected, regularized, or expanded views included as 
               the values of attributes associated with various elements. Accordingly, abbreviations, recoverable
               cancelations, punctuation, spelling, underscoring, capitalization, line breaks, and page breaks 
               have all been transcribed or tagged as they appear in the original manuscripts. Regularized
               versions of all names and referring strings have been encoded as the values of "reg"
               attributes. Standard format values for all dates have been encoded in "value" attributes.</p>
            <p>Corrections and emendations in Anderson's hand have been encoded as cancelations and interlinear 
               or marginal additions. In a few cases, omitted text has been supplied by the editors for the sake 
               of clarity and encoded with the TEI &lt;supplied&gt; element.</p>
            <p>The following structural elements of the letters are also encoded: opener (including salutation
               and dateline), body, lines, paragraphs, pages, and closers (including salutation and 
               signature). Notes and postscripts are identified as such.</p>
            <p>The critical apparatus used in particular views of the letters is explained at the bottom of each view.</p>
            <p>To view the project's complete markup guidelines, 
               <xref url="http://people.cohums.ohio-state.edu/ulman1/WBAnderson_Letters/AndersonLettersMarkup.cfm">click here</xref>.</p>
            <p>At the time of publication (6 June 2006), the XML and XSL files related to this
               edition were stored in an XML publishing system operated by Humanities
               Information Systems (HIS), College of Humanities, The Ohio State University. For
               more information about HIS, see <xref url="http://his.osu.edu/">http://his.osu.edu/</xref>. 
               Most image, audio, and video 
               files linked to, or embedded in, this edition via &lt;figure&gt; elements were 
               stored in the Media Manager system maintained by the Colleges of Arts and 
               Sciences of The Ohio State University. For more information about the Media Manager,
               see <xref url="https://mediamanager.osu.edu/">https://mediamanager.osu.edu/</xref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         
         <refsDecl>
            <p>The XML files that constitute this edition of the William B. Anderson letters
               are named according the letters' dates of composition, using the following naming
               convention: WBA_YYYYMMDD.xml. Dates of composition were determined from
               various sources of evidence: the datelines inscribed in the letters, internal
               evidence in the body of the letters, and perpetual calendars. If the year,
               month, or date on which a letter was written could not be determined, the 
               appropriate part of the filename is rendered with 0s. XSL style
               sheet documents are named with the prefix "WBA" followed by an underscore
               and a descriptive phrase (e.g., "WBA_diplomatic.xsl).</p>
            <p>In general, this edition follows the Text Encoding Initiative's Guidelines
               for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange, XML-compatible edition P4.
               For more information about TEI P4, see <xref url="http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/">http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/</xref>.
               To facilitate embedding or linking to image, audio, and video files, this edition
               supplements the Text Encoding Initiative's DTD by adding a URL attribute to 
               the &lt;xref&gt; element and an MMID (i.e., Media Manager ID) attribute to the 
               &lt;pb&gt; element. The values of the MMID attribute in &lt;pb&gt; elements and
               the file IDs in the URL attribute of &lt;xref&gt; elements that link to, or embed, 
               image, audio, and video files contained in the Media Manager are generated 
               by the Media Manager application.</p>
         </refsDecl>
         
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         
      </encodingDesc>
      
      <profileDesc>
         <!--The text profile, tagged <profileDesc>, contains "classificatory and contextual information 
         about the text, such as its subject matter, the situation in which it was produced, the 
         individuals described by or participating in producing it, and so forth" (TEI P4X, ch. 5).-->
         
         <creation>
            <date>2006-06-06</date>
         </creation>
         
         <langUsage>
            <!-- NOTE ANY LANGUAGES THAT APPEAR IN YOUR DOCUMENT -->
            <language id="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         
         <handList>
            <!-- IDENTIFY ANY HANDS THAT APPEAR IN A HANDWRITTEN OR ANNOTATED DOCUMENT-->
            <hand first="yes" id="WBA" scribe="Anderson, William B. (1822-1897)"/>
            <hand first="no" id="UNK" scribe="Unknown"/>
         </handList>
         
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <!-- SUPPLY A LIST OF KEYWORDS FOR YOUR DOCUMENT -->
               <term>Anderson, William B. (1822-1897)</term>
               <term>Anderson, Mary Louisa neé Fischgens (1837-1911)</term>
               <term>Morris, George</term>
               <term>Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh</term>
               <term>Pennsylvania -- Shousetown</term>
               <term>River boats -- United States</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         
      </profileDesc>
      
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--The revision history, tagged <revisionDesc>, allows "the encoder to provide a history of 
         changes made during the development of the electronic text" (TEI P4X, ch. 5).-->
         <!-- USE THE FIRST ENTRY IN THE LIST OF CHANGES TO RECORD YOUR
         INITIAL PUBLICATION OF THE DOCUMENT. Add additional changes at the top of the list. -->
         
         <change>
            <date>2006-08-10</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Principal Editor</resp>
               <name>H. Lewis Ulman</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Cross-check against independent transcription by Jamie Danker (principal editor evaluated discrepancies).</item>
         </change>
         
         <change>
            <date>2006-06-06</date>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <name>H. Lewis Ulman</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Initial release.</item>
         </change>
         
      </revisionDesc>
      
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 n="1" type="abstract">
            
            <!-- This template uses divisions to distinguish parts of the front, body, and
            back of the electronic document. You do not have to use divisions. -->
            <head>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Letter from William B. Anderson to his wife, Louisa, 27 June 1862.</title>
                  <date>1862-06-27</date>
                  <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                  <!-- "ALS" MEANS AUTOGRAPH LETTER SIGNED. ASK ME ABOUT OTHER
                  ABBREVIATIONS -->
                  <extent>1 pp.</extent>
                  <idno rend="suppress" type="CallNumber">XXXXXXXXXX</idno>
               </bibl>
            </head>
            <p>Anderson tells his wife that his boat's departure has been delayed by a day 
               and asks her to send some food and clothes to him at the dock. He also expresses 
               anxiety about whether his trip will be profitable and asks his wife to request 
               some money from [John?] Russell to help cover an upcoming payday for his crew.</p>
            <p>Previous letter <xref type="prev" url="WBA_18620616">16 June 1862</xref>
               Next letter <xref type="next" url="WBA_18620711">11 July 1862.</xref></p>
         </div1>         
      </front>
      
      <body>
         
         <div1 n="1" type="Letter">
            <!--Transcription of the body of the document begins here. If you use the div tag,
            the type attribute should reflect the nature of your document (e.g., "letter"). -->
            
            <head/>
            <!-- Note that the head can be entered as an empty element. Compare to the 
            div element in the front of the document. -->
            
            
       <!-- 
            The opener element contains any dateline and salutation appearing at the head of the letter.
            You may omit this element if your document does not contain similar material.
            Note that dates and names are tagged with standard versions in order to improve searching. 
       -->
            
       <!--   
               Beginning with the opener of the letter, lines in this template have been identified 
               to allow for cross references and numbered to allow for numbered display. IDs must 
               be unique within the document. However, you do not need to report line breaks at all 
               if doing so serves no purpose in your edition. 
       -->
            <pb mmid="/0/0a310868-4a89-4c8a-a1f1-0adfe7c9232a" n="1"/>
            
            <opener>
               <lb n="001"/><dateline><address><name reg="Cincinnati, OH" type="place"><abbr expan="Cincinnati">Cin</abbr></name></address>
                  <date value="1862-10-16">Oct 16th 1862</date></dateline>
               <lb n="002"/><salute>My Dr <rs type="recipient">
                     <rs reg="Anderson, Mary Louisa, née Fischgens (1837-1911)" type="person">Wife</rs></rs>
                  <seg>
                     <note target="n2">2</note>
                  </seg>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            
            <p>
               <lb n="003"/>Yours Mailed 13th I got on my 
               <lb n="004"/>arrival to the City this afternoon &amp; was glad 
               <lb n="005"/>to hear from you.  I have been absent from 
               <lb n="006"/>the City for a few days on a trip to Maysville 
               <lb n="007"/>we are sill in Gov employ and I suppose we 
               <lb n="008"/>will continue some time yet as there is no prospect 
               <lb n="009"/>of water.  I will have to be <sic corr="disappointed">dissapointed</sic> in 
               <lb n="010"/>my prospects of going home for while and 
               <lb n="011"/>if you can come down I will be glad to 
               <lb n="012"/>see you any time you can come you had better 
               <lb n="013"/>not attempt to bring the children as they will 
               <lb n="014"/>be <sic corr="too">to</sic> great a charge for you, although I should 
               <lb n="015"/>be very happy to see them but you could not be 
               <lb n="016"/>at liberty to go any place you might wish with 
               <lb n="017"/>them and there is no reason why you could not 
               <lb n="018"/>leave them in care of Mary McNamee and Julia 
               <lb n="019"/>Porter for that time.  You can make your own 
               <lb n="020"/>arrangements about the children as I leave the 
               <lb n="021"/>care of them altogether to you I think if you 
               <lb n="022"/>will come down 
               <del type="recoverable" rend="overstrike" hand="WBA"> you had better come down</del> you
               <lb n="023"/>had better not wait as long as next month 
               <lb n="024"/>for fear the river will raise or if it <sic corr="don't">dont</sic> 
               <lb n="025"/>raise &amp; should continue to fall we might be sent 
               <lb n="026"/>down below. this <del type="recoverable" rend="overstrike" hand="WBA">is</del> 
               my <sic corr="advice">advise</sic> to you will be 
               <lb n="027"/>for you to come by the Steubenville route and 
               
               <pb mmid="/5/5aa5bc88-89c1-48c1-bc3e-c2d2be754dba" n="2"/>
               
               <lb n="028"/>leave Pittsburgh at one Oclock or there abouts 
               <lb n="029"/>and when you get on board you tell the 
               <lb n="030"/>Conductor that you want to take the <sic corr="sleeping">sheeping</sic> 
               <lb n="031"/>Car which they take in tow at Steubenville 
               <lb n="032"/>and that will cost you 50 cts extra that train 
               <lb n="033"/>arrives at the Dayton &amp; Hamilton Depot at about 
               <lb n="034"/>5 or 6 oclock A.M. the ticket office is on 
               <lb n="035"/>Liberty Street near the Canal on the left hand 
               <lb n="036"/>side of the street it might be that John 
               <lb n="037"/>will come down with you and that would 
               <lb n="038"/>be better as I think he has acted very foolish 
               <lb n="039"/>for I have to pay 5$ each per day for Pilots 
               <lb n="040"/>and he might just as well had 200$ dollars 
               <lb n="041"/>while he has been at home as not if you should 
               <lb n="042"/>come down or have any chance to send me 
               <lb n="043"/>that pair of Blue pants &amp; belt down I would 
               <lb n="044"/>like to have them as my Pants are getting thin 
               <lb n="045"/>and I don’t want to spend any money I can 
               <lb n="046"/>help.  I have not seen your mother for 
               <lb n="047"/>2 or three weeks I may see her in a few 
               <lb n="048"/>days if you come let me know a few days 
               <lb n="049"/>before you come when to be on the look out 
               <lb n="050"/>for you. 
            </p>
            <p>
               
               <lb n="051"/>Tell Old Man Walsh that I will take 12 
               <lb n="052"/><abbr expan="dollars">dolls</abbr> for that Heifer &amp; for him to sell the Hay 
               <lb n="053"/>and divide the money I think hay will be very 
               <lb n="054"/>High in the spring but I suppose he wants his 
               <lb n="055"/>share of the money he can do as he thinks 
               <lb n="056"/>best about it.  That Bank notice you spoke 
               
               <pb mmid="/D/d9efdc52-501d-44fd-ac88-c104eb8132ed" n="3"/>
               
               <lb n="057"/>about I made arrangements with Holmes 
               <lb n="058"/>&amp; Sons Brokers to pay all my notes that will 
               <lb n="059"/>fall due I told Mr Wright to use what Money 
               <lb n="060"/>was deposited at Holmes &amp; Sons belonging to the Boat 
               <lb n="061"/>to Pay Notes &amp; when that ran out to use what 
               <lb n="062"/>I had there which is sufficient to pay all claims 
               <lb n="063"/>that may fall due for a while I will look 
               <lb n="064"/>for a letter from you soon and will be 
               <lb n="065"/>pleased to hear of you making satisfa<seg type="softhyphen">
               <lb n="066"/>=</seg>ctory arrangements to come and see me 
               <lb n="067"/>as it seems utterly impossibly for me to 
               <lb n="068"/>leave for the present I am to settle up 
               <lb n="069"/>our business here up till the 15 of this <abbr expan="month">Mo</abbr> 
               <lb n="070"/>this or next week and then I will find out 
               <lb n="071"/>what I am making but one thing I do 
               <lb n="072"/>know is this that I am doing as well as I 
               <lb n="073"/>want to with a boat my share of the <sic corr="profits">proffits</sic> 
               <lb n="074"/>and wages is at least 40 <abbr expan="dollars">dolls</abbr> per day and that 
               <lb n="075"/>is not bad but keep it to yourself. I will stop 
               <lb n="076"/>as the mail Closes at 8 Oclock this evening I 
               <lb n="077"/>will write soon again but write immediately 
               <lb n="078"/>and give me all the news and take good 
               <lb n="079"/>Care of yourself and the children and kiss 
               <lb n="080"/>all of them for me and tell them to be good 
            </p>            
                                         
            <!-- Closer begins here, for letters. -->
            
            <closer>
               <lb n="081"/><salute>Your Affectionate Husband</salute>
               <lb n="082"/><signed>
                  <name reg="Anderson, William B. (1822-1897)" type="person">WB Anderson</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>          
         </div1>
         <div1 type="postscript" n="2">
            <head/>
            <p>
               <lb n="083"/>Excuse Haste &amp; Bad writing as there is a constant
               <lb n="084"/>ta<del type="recoverable" rend="overwritten" hand="WBA">k</del>lking and fun in the Hall
            </p>
            <closer>
               <lb n="085"/><signed><name type="person" reg="Anderson, William B. (1822-1897)">WBA</name></signed>
            </closer>
         </div1>
      </body>
      
      <back>
         <div1 n="1" type="Annotations">
            <!-- Annotations begin here. -->
            
            <head>Notes</head>
            
            <note id="n1">1. This penciled note appears to have been partially erased
               <figure rend="link">
                  <head>Detail from letter dated 27 June 1862</head>
                  <figDesc>
                     <xref url="https://images.asc.ohio-state.edu/is/image/mediamanager/C/cc918f45-896e-4226-a419-9261be2361ac.jpg?crop=1600,150,1500,450&amp;scale=.5&amp;op_brightness=-25&amp;op_contrast=15&amp;fmt=png">
                      Click to view a detailed image
                     </xref>
               </figDesc>
               </figure>
               George Morris is unidentified.</note>
            <note id="n2">2. Mary Louisa Fischgens (1837-1911) and William B. Anderson were married September
            15, 1853 in Cincinnati, Ohio. They had five children. <bibl><title level="m">History
               of Allegheny County </title>298</bibl>.</note>
            <note id="n3">3. Shousetown, Pennsylvania was located along the Ohio River in western Allegheny
               County, approximately six miles downstream from the confluence of the Allegheny and 
               Monongahela Rivers in Pittsburgh.
               To view an 1876 map of Shousetown, <xref url="http://images.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/maps/showmap.pl?client=maps&amp;image=76v01p41&amp;levels=5&amp;originx=0&amp;originy=0&amp;lastlevel=4&amp;fullheight=4818&amp;fullwidth=3912&amp;level=1&amp;size=1&amp;image.x=60&amp;image.y=252">click here</xref>.
            <bibl><title level="m">Historic Pittsburgh</title>.</bibl></note>
            <note id="n4">4. Perhaps the John Russell referred to in the <title>Biographical Review</title> as 
               “a prominent merchant on Liberty Street [in Pittsburgh] for many years” (205).</note>
            
         </div1>
         
         <div1 n="2" type="Citations">
            <!--List of Works Cited begins here-->
            
            <listBibl>
               <head>Works Cited in Notes</head>
               
               <bibl id="BR">
                  <title level="m">Biographical review; v. 24, containing life sketches of leading citizens 
                     of Pittsburg and the vicinity, Pennsylvania</title>
                  <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Biographical Review Publishing Co.</publisher>
                  <date>1897</date>
               </bibl>
               <bibl id="HP">
                  <title level="a">1876 - Atlas of the Cities of Pittsburgh, Allegheny and Adjoining Boroughs: Plate 41</title>
                  <title level="m">Historic Pittsburgh</title>
                  <biblScope type="URL">http://images.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/maps/showmap.pl?client=maps&amp;image=76v01p41</biblScope>
                  <date>No date</date>
                  <biblScope type="DateOfVisit">29 May 2006</biblScope>
               </bibl>
               
               <bibl id="HOAC">
                  <title level="m">History of Allegheny county, Pennsylvania: Including its early settlement and 
                     progress to the present time; a description of its historic and interesting localities; 
                     its cities, towns and villages; religious, educational, social and military history; mining, 
                     manufacturing and commercial interests, improvements, resources, statistics, etc.; also, 
                     biographies of many of its representative citizens</title>
                  <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>A. Warner &amp; Co.</publisher>
                  <date>1889</date>
               </bibl>                  
            </listBibl>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>